<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Martyrion Christianon, or, A Christian and sober testimony against sinfull complyance wherein the unlawfulness of hearing the present ministers of England is clearly demonstrated, severall weighty queries proposed, objections impartially weighed in the ballance of the sanctuary and found wanting / by Christophilus Antichristomachus.</title>
            <author>Douglas, Thomas, fl. 1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 261 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36444</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2039</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26734</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09527584</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09527584</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43509</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36444)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43509)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1329:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Martyrion Christianon, or, A Christian and sober testimony against sinfull complyance wherein the unlawfulness of hearing the present ministers of England is clearly demonstrated, severall weighty queries proposed, objections impartially weighed in the ballance of the sanctuary and found wanting / by Christophilus Antichristomachus.</title>
                  <author>Douglas, Thomas, fl. 1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>98 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43509:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43509:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Or, A CHRISTIAN and SOBER TESTIMONY AGAINST Sinfull Complyance.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN, The Unlawfulneſs of Hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is clearly demonſtrated. Severall weighty <hi>Queries</hi> propoſed; <hi>Objections</hi> impartially weighed in the Ballance of the Sanctuary, and found wanting.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Chriſtophilus Antichriſtomachus,</hi> a Mourner in <hi>Sion,</hi> waiting for the day of her Salvation, and coming of her King.</p>
            <bibl>Rev. 14. 9, 10, 11.</bibl>
            <q>If any man worſhip the Beaſt, and his Image, and receive his Mark in his forehead, or in his hand; the ſame ſhall drink of the Wine of the Wrath of God, which is poured out without mixture, into the cup of his Indignation, and he ſhall be tormented with fire and brimſtone in the preſence of the holy Angels, and in the preſence of the Lamb. And the ſmoke of their torment aſcended up for ever and ever; and they have no reſt day nor night, who worſhip the Beaſt and his Image, and whoſoever receiveth the Mark of his Name.</q>
            <bibl>Acts 2. 40.</bibl>
            <q>Save your ſelves from this untoward generation.</q>
            <bibl>John 10. 3.</bibl>
            <q>The Sheep hear his Voice—<hi>v.5.</hi> and a ſtranger they will not follow.</q>
            <bibl>1 Joh. 4. 5.</bibl>
            <q>They are of the world, therefore ſpeak they of the world, and the world hears them.</q>
            <p>Printed for the Author, in the Year 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:43509:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43509:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Candid Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVE are almoſt at the end of theſe Paper-Conteſts, which are daily preaching their own Funeral. 'Tis in another way that <hi>Jehovah</hi> will ſhortly appear (for he hath already ſent his Harbingers before him) to convince the world, and worldly Church of their Wickedneſs, and Adulteries, whereby they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the pure eyes of his glory. For behold, the Lord cometh with Fire, and with his Chariots like a Whirle wind, to render his Anger with Fury, and his Rebuke with flames of fire; <hi>For by Fire, and by Sword, will the Lord plead with all fleſh, and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many.</hi> Happy art thou, if in the number of thoſe that ſhall be able to live, when the Lord doth this. Alas! <hi>Who may abide the day of his coming?</hi> and who ſhall ſtand when he appeareth? Men (as men) will be at their wits ends, when they behold the Earth to reel to and fro, like a drunken man, (its foundatious being out of courſe) the Mountains to Smoake, and the Hills to melt away, becauſe of the terribleneſs of his Anger: <hi>The Kings of the Earth</hi> (who now (as <hi>Pharoah</hi> of old) are with delight drinking the blood of the Saints, as ſweet Wine, and refuſe to let them go, from under their bonds to Sacrifice to the Lord, according to his appointment) <hi>and the Great men, and the Rich men, and the Chief Captains, and the Mighty men, and every Bond-man, and every Free-man,</hi> will then <hi>hide themſelves in the Dens, and in the Rocks of the Mountains, and cry to them, to fall upon them, and hide them, from the Wrath of the Lamb.</hi> The day of whoſe Wrath is ready to ſpring forth (though the wicked world think not ſo) all the ſigns of the near approach thereof, are already viſibly fulfilled. What Wars, and rumors of Wars? (Nation fighting againſt Nation) what ſtrange Signes in the Heavens, and in the Earth, with great Earth-quakes in many places? what a ſpirit of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and Offence, (Brother even betraying Brother to death) what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clenſion, and decaies of love to Jeſus Chriſt, amongst not only a profeſſing, but an once, Zealous profeſſing People, do we daily ſee, and hear of? how doth Iniquity abound? ſo that the Worlds fields are even white unto the harveſt: the Voice of the Daughter of <hi>Sion</hi> is louder than than ever, cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43509:3"/> out, <hi>My fleſh and my blood, be upon the Daughter of Babylon;</hi> the ſouls under the Altar are groaning, <hi>How long, O Lord God, Holy and True, will it be ere thou avenge our blood upon them that dwell on the Earth?</hi> and will the Lord refrain himſelf, and ſhut out the Prayers of his Priſoners of Hope? I tell you nay; but as a Lion, and as a young Lion roaring on his prey, when a multitude of Shepherds is called forth againſt him, he will not be affraid of their voice, nor abaſe himſelf for the noiſe of them: ſo ſhall the Lord of Hoſts come down, to fight for Mount Sion, and for the Hill thereof; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterly to dethrone the Antichriſtian Beaſt, and Whore, who have made themſelves drunk with the blood of the Saints (for which he will make them drunk with blood (even their own blood) for they are worthy) and to cauſe his poor oppreſſed ones, to inherit the Throne of Glory, in despite of their Oppreſſors! <hi>Reader,</hi> whoever thou art, into whoſe hand this little Tract may come, I cannot but crave thy ſtay, out of pure love, to ſpeak a few things to thee in the Portal. If thou art one that art a Scorner, Derider, Perſecutor of the Saints (under what denomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſoever) if thou art glad in thy heart (as was wicked <hi>Edom</hi> and <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> of old) at the ſufferings of the People of the Lord, yea; if thou art but a civilized perſon, or a meer outſide Profeſſor, without any acquaintance with the work of Regeneration upon thy ſpirit, and the Power, and My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Chriſtianity, and Godlineſs; whatever thy enjoyments, comforts, hopes, or confidences be, know of a certainty, that this day of the Lord's Wrath, will ſweep them away all, and thou wilt utterly periſh in the flames of his Indignation. Oh then thou wilt cry out, <hi>I Fool accounted their life madneſs, and their end to be without honour, but now they are numbred among the Children of God, and crowned with glory; but I am caſt out to be tormented, millions of millions of ages:</hi> O that I could prevail with thee, ſeriouſly to conſider of thy ſtate, (art thou able to meet, and contend with the Moſt High?) to proceed no further in rebellion, treaſuring up wrath againſt the day of wrath, and the revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the righteous Judgment of God. O fling away thy Weapons, kiſs the Son, that he be not angry with thee, and thou periſh in the way! Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent not thy ſelf, in being accounted a Chriſtian, that thou haſt eſcaped the pollutions of the World, nor in the performance of ſome dead, formal, ſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and ſpiritleſs ſervice to the Lord, which profiteth nothing: Get an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Chriſt, freely tendred in the Goſpel, deep humiliation for thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer iniquities, a ſpirit of Grace and Supplication, inward Purity and Heart-uprightneſs, or periſh for ever. Oh ſee that thou haſt Oyl in thy
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43509:3"/> veſſel, as well as in thy lamp, or thou wilt not be able to dwell with devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring fire, and everlaſting burnings! If thou art a Child of Light, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed begotten of the Lord, acquainted, and holding communion with him in his <hi>Ivory Pallaces;</hi> O what cauſe haſt thou to tryumph in God, for his wonderful, wonderful Grace to thee! O how ſhould'ſt thou love him? how ſhould'ſt thou praiſe him? with what eagerneſs ſhouldeſt thou be proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the concerns of his Glory? how tenderly ſhould'ſt thou be affected with his diſhonour? how full of Supplications and heart-groans for him, to ariſe thoroughly to plead his Cauſe? how ready to ſell all for his Glories ſake, and follow him whither ſoever he goes? O take heed of giving way to a ſpirit of ſlumber (the temptation of this day of the Bridegrooms tarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance) do not ſay a confederacy, with thoſe that ſay a confederacy, againſt the Lord; receive not the <hi>Mark</hi> of the Beaſt in thy forehead, or hand: Keep thy <hi>Virginity,</hi> in respect of Worſhip, that thou mayeſt be found without fault before the Throne of the Lamb: Hold faſt thy <hi>beginning-confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,</hi> that hath ſo great a recompence of reward: 'tis but a very little while, and thy God will come with Vengeance, even God with a Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, he will come and ſave thee. Stand faſt, and keep thy ground, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a ſmall moment thou ſhalt be ſinging, <hi>The Winter is paſt, the Rain is over and gone</hi>—Keep <hi>faithful</hi> to God, and while thou art in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs thou ſhalt not be without thy ſprings of living Water, he will ſpeak comfortably to thy heart, and give thee thy Vinyards from hence, and the <hi>Valley of Achor</hi> for a <hi>door of Hope;</hi> and he will bring thee ſafe (yea the right way) to <hi>Canaan,</hi> where thou ſhalt ſee thy King in his beauty, hunger no more, neither thirſt any more, nither ſhall the Sun light on thee, nor any heat, for the Lamb which is in the midſt of the Throne ſhall feed thee, and ſhall lead thee unto living Fountains of Waters, and God ſhall wipe away all Tears from thy eyes. O bleſſed Day! O royal State! do not your hearts ſing under the thought of it? who would refuſe (if the Lord would ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him) to ſwim through a Sea of blood (though his own blood) to follow JESUS who will aſſuredly crown us, with its Enjoyment? If thou art one who (through the power of Temptation) art turned aſide by the Flock of the Companions, and art worſhipping with the Nations, waiting at the poſts of an Antichriſtian Miniſtry for teachings, I do aſſure thee my bowels are troubled for thee, and with a Pen dipt in my own Tears could I write to thee. O why wilt thou forſake the <hi>Fountain of Living Waters,</hi> for <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Ciſterns</hi> that will hold no water? wilt thou change thy glory for that which will not profit? Is it becauſe there is not bread enough in thy Fathers
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43509:4"/> houſe, that thou goeſt a begging to the doors of ſtrangers? Is it nothing to thee to caſt contempt upon the pure Inſtitutions of Chriſt, to provoke the Lord to ſend leanneſs into thy ſoul? Is it a ſmall matter to be an occaſion of grief, and ſtumbling to thy Brethren, to pour contempt upon the Offices, Wiſdom and Faithfulneſs of Chriſt, to harden perſons in a falſe way of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of God, to their eternal ruine, to diſobey the Heavenly Voice, calling aloud to thee, to come from the Lions dens, and mountains of the Leopards, to come out of <hi>Babylon?</hi> O ariſe, depart hence, this is not your reſt, it is polluted, haſten thine eſcape, be like the <hi>He-Goat</hi> before the Flocks, in thy retreat from the Tents of theſe <hi>Falſe-worſhippers,</hi> leſt being partaker of their ſin, thou receiveſt of their plagues, that are even ready to be poured forth! Who knows but this may be the laſt Warning thou mayeſt have from God? I could eaſily expatiate (for great is my pity towards thee) were I not ſenſible how far I have already exceeded the limits of an Epiſtle, to ſo ſmall a Treatiſe, which I willingly ſubmit to thy cenſure (through the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of many judicious Chriſtians) with this requeſt <hi>That thou reade it with ſeriouſneſs and impartiality.</hi> It hath m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>mes been given up to the Lord, and the ſervice of his poor People, for above this year that it hath lain by me: if thou art any way advantaged or bettered by it, give God the glory; and let him have a ſhare in thy Prayers, when near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt the Throne, who accounts it his glory to be.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A Servant to the weakeſt of the Lord's Lambs. C. A.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43509:4"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: OR, <hi>A Chriſtian and Sober Testimony againſt Sinful Complyance.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The <hi>PREFACE</hi> to the enſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
               <p>BEing to treat of one part of the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt, under the Goſpel, with reſpect unto the duty incumbent upon the Saints, in order thereunto, it may ſeem to any indifferent perſon, but a reaſonable <hi>Poſtulatum</hi> in the preſent Enquiry, that the whole thereof be divolved upon the Scriptures of the New-Teſtament; and thoſe Royal Laws, that Chriſt (the alone King and Law-giver of his Church) hath given forth for Saints under the New-Teſtament-Diſpenſation to walk by, until they arrive unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 13. not perplexing our ſelves, nor the conſciences of any, with the judgments of men in generations paſt, (wherein they cannot aquieſce, though to take off the prejudices of ſome againſt Truth, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of its ſeeming novelty, we may here and there manifeſt their harmony with us, in the main Principles of the enſuing Structure) nor what was (or may be ſuppoſed to be) permitted, unto the Saints, before the time of Reformation, whilſt the worldly Sanctuary was yet ſtanding, the carnal Ordinances appertaining thereunto in being, at leaſt by the Providence of God, not fully diſſolved, as afterward, both it and they were, being buried in the aſhes and ruines of that Temple, to which they were inſeparably annext. Yet, inaſmuch, as ſome beams of Light may be communicated unto the preſent Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by a retroſpection into the ſtate of things in the time of the old Law, it ſhall not be grievous to us, (nor will it be altogether unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Reader) briefly to remark, ſo far as may concern the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43509:5"/> matter in hand, the ſtate and management of affairs, under that <hi>Oeconomy</hi> and Diſpenſation. Not to mention the Adminiſtration of holy things in the time of the <hi>Ante-Deluvian</hi> Fathers, not the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Apoſtacy from the pure wayes of God, in the dayes of <hi>Seth,</hi> (when according to their duty the faithful Remnant (the Sons of God) ſeparated from the wicked (or the daughters of men) and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly joyned themſelves together, to worſhip God according to his holy Appointments, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 26.) Let us take a brief view of things, with relation unto the People of God, after the giving of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, when a Standard was ſet up for them to repair unto, and they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came (being gathered into one) as a City on an Hill, conſpicuous unto all.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, that the Lord gave unto the People of the <hi>Jews</hi> (whom he had choſen out of all the Nations of the World, to be a People near to him, his peculiar treaſure above them all) Statutes and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances to walk by, both with relation to Civils and Eccleſiaſticks, which they were indiſpenſibly bound to conform to, without adding to, or detracting therefrom: That the management of all their affairs was ſingly to be bottom'd upon, and conform to, theſe Statutes and Judgments, is very frequently aſſerted in Scripture, <hi>Exod. 21. 1. Lev.</hi> 18. 4. and 19. 37. and 20. 22. and 25. 18. and 26. 15, 43. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 1, 5, 8. and 5. 1. and 7. 11. and 11. 1, 32. and 12. 1. and 26. 16. and 30. 16. 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. 12. and 28. 7. <hi>Pſal. 89. 30. Ezek.</hi> 5. 6. and 36. 27. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 5.</p>
               <p>2ly. That perſons were appointed by the Lord, to be choſen by the Congregation, for the publick adminiſtration of Ordinances and Worſhip, cannot be denied: Thus were the Livites, <hi>Exod.</hi> 13. 2, 12, 13. and 22. 29. <hi>Numb.</hi> 3. 12. called therefore the <hi>Wave-Offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Children of Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 8. 9, 10, 11. becauſe given up by them to the Lord as their Offering, by ſolemn Ordination and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands.</p>
               <p>3ly. That perſons thus inveſted into the Office of Prieſthood were not left to the liberty of their own wills, nor had they any depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Will or Authority of the ſons of men (one, or other of them) either in reſpect of the matter or manner of their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the whole whereof was purely of Sovereign Inſtitution, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment, <hi>Exod. 25. 9, 40. Numb. 8. 5. Heb. 8. 5. 1 Chron. 28. 11. Exod. 8. 27. Lev. 10. 1. Exod.</hi> 39. 1, 5, 7, 21, 26, 31, 43.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43509:5"/> and 40. 23, 25, 27, 29. <hi>Levit. 8. 9, 13, 17, 21, 29. Numb. 8. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Exod.</hi> 35. 10, 29. &amp; 36. 1, 5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 29. 13.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, That this Church, gathered by the Lord, and wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſeparated from the reſt of the world (though they had him nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to them than any people, had his Law made known amongſt them) did notwithſtanding quickly depart from his pure Inſtitutions, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling therewith the Inventions of men, and Cuſtoms of the Nations (after which they went a whoring) is frequently remarked in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: Of this the Lord ſorely complains, <hi>Deut. 32. 18. Jer.</hi> 2. 32. and 13. 25. and 18. 15. and 23. 27. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 6. and 8. 14. and 13. 6. 2 <hi>Chron. 13. 10. Iſa. 1. 4. Jer.</hi> 1. 16. and 2. 17, 19. and 9. 13. and 15. 6. <hi>Deut. 29 25. 1 Kings</hi> 11. 33. and 18. 18. and 19. 10. 2 <hi>Kings 22. 17. Ezra.</hi> 9. 10. for this he ſeverely threatens and puniſheth them, <hi>Deut. 29. 25. Judg. 10. 10. 1 Sam. 12. 10. 2 Chron.</hi> 12. 5. and 24. 20. and 34. 25. <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 11. and 19. 4. the very truth is, the Conteſts of God with that People from firſt to laſt, are to be bottomed upon this foot of account.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, That notwithſtanding their dreadful Apoſtacy from God, they were uſually confident, That they were the only People, Had not forſaken the Lord, nor done any evil, and could not bear the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies and Rebukes of the Prophets and Servants of the Lord againſt their abominations: Whom they perſecuted and put to death (as at laſt they did the Prince of Life and Glory) for no other cauſe, but for telling them the truth, and bearing teſtimony againſt their Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and Apoſtacy from God (the uſual practice of perſons dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated from the Way and Spirit of the Lord) <hi>Mal. 1. 6. Jer. 7. 4. Luke 3. 8. John 8. 39. Matth. 5. 12. Act.</hi> 7. 52.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, That they had all along their corruption in Worſhip, and degeneracy from the pure Wayes of God, falſe Prophets, (who ran before they were ſent, propheſying ſmooth things to them in the Name of the Lord, ſeeing lying vanities for them, according to the deſires of the hearts of them and their Rulers, who were therefore in great eſteem amongſt them) <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. 15. &amp; 28. 7. <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 13. &amp; 23. 11, 28. &amp; 28. 10. <hi>Hoſ. 9. 8. Jer.</hi> 2. 8, 26. &amp; 5. 31. &amp; 14. 14. &amp; 23. 13, 21. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 2. &amp; 22. 25, 28. <hi>Mic. 3. 5, 6, 7. Zeph. 3. 4. 2 Pet.</hi> 2. 1.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, That in the height of their Apoſtacy, God left not himſelf without a Witneſs, having one or other extraordinarily rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up and ſpirited by him, to teſtifie for his Name and Glory, againſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43509:6"/> all their Abominations and ſelf-invented Worſhip, reſerving alſo a Remnant unto himſelf, that were not carried away with the ſpirit of Whoredoms and Deluſions, 1. <hi>Kings 19. 14, 18. 2 Kings 17. 13. Rom. 11. 3, 4. Jer.</hi> 18. 11. and 25. 5. &amp; 35. 15.</p>
               <p>Eighthly, That it was the ſin of that People, to hearken unto the teachings of ſuch as were not ſent by the Lord (though they preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded never ſo much to be ſent by him) and the unqueſtionable duty of the Lord's perſevering Remnant, to ſeparate from them, as alſo from all the falſe, ſelf-deviſed Worſhip of that day, though com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by their Kings and Rulers, 2 <hi>Kings 17. 21, 22. Hoſ.</hi> 5. 11. The former is evident, ſuch Prophets were to be cut off from the midſt of them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 18. 20. and they are expreſly forbidden to hear them, <hi>Deut. 13. 3. Jer.</hi> 27. 9, 16. So is the latter, their deviſed Worſhip being a breach upon the Sovereign Authority of God, muſt needs be a greivous ſin, as the names of <hi>Adultery, Whoredom, Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Fornication,</hi> by which the Spirit of the Lord doth frequently ſet it forth, abundantly demonſtrates; <hi>Pſal. 73. 27. Iſa. 57. 3, 8. Jer. 9. 2. Ezek. 23. 45. Hoſ. 3. 7. and 7. 3. Lev. 20. 5. Jer. 13. 27. Ezek. 16. 17, 20, 30. Hoſ. 1. 2. Rev.</hi> 14. 8. &amp; 18. 9, 19, 20. which without controverſie, the People of God were to ſeparate from, and have no communion with any in, upon what pretence ſoever: Which is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly charged upon them as their duty in the Scripture, <hi>Hoſ. 4. 15. Amos 5. 5. Prov.</hi> 4. 14. and 5. 8. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4. 8.</p>
               <p>What may rationally be inferred from theſe Poſitions, ſo evidently comprized in the Scripture, and by way of analogie at leaſt, be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued from them, is evident to any ordinary underſtanding; for our parts being reſolved (as was ſaid) to try out the matter in controveſie, from ſuch Rules and Soveraign Inſtitutions, as our dear Lord hath left his New-Teſtament Churches to walk by, we ſhall not ſtand to make that improvement of them, as elſe otherwiſe we might: A few Queries upon the whole that hath been offered, ſhall put a cloſe to this Preface.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whether ſince the <hi>Apotomie,</hi> or Unchurching the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Lord hath ever ſince ſo eſpouſed a Nation or People to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as that upon the account thereof, the whole body of that Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple or Nation may be accounted his Church? whether there be any <hi>National Church</hi> under the Oeconomie of the Goſpel? if ſo, let it be ſhewed when, and where it was inſtituted by the Lord; what is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43509:6"/> by ſome to this purpoſe, is (but upon a ſlight view thereof) of no moment, it is <hi>Iſa. 49. 21. Kings ſhall be your Nurſing-fathers, &amp;c.</hi> which Prophecy waits the time of its accompliſhment; hitherto, both before and ſince the riſe of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> (being made drunk by the <hi>Whores</hi> intoxicating-cup) they have been, for the moſt part, cruel Butcherers of the Saints: and were we under its accompliſhment, a National Church would be far enough from being its reſult. Of a <hi>Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing born at once,</hi> we ſhall not ſure hear pleaded in this matter, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Prophecy expreſly relating to the <hi>Jews,</hi> and their miraculous Converſion: if there be no ſuch thing as a <hi>National Church</hi> of the Inſtitution of Chriſt, as moſt certain it is there is not (the Aſſertion whereof is wholly deſtructive of Goſpel-Adminiſtrations) Then,</p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether <hi>National Miniſters</hi> are the <hi>Miniſters of Chriſt,</hi> or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there can be a <hi>true Miniſtry</hi> in a <hi>falſe Church,</hi> as a National-Church muſt be, if not of Divine Inſtitution, upon what pretence ſoever it be ſo denominated?</p>
               <p n="3">3. Whether God doth not bear as much love to, and exerciſe as much faithfulneſs over, his New-Teſtament-Churches, as over the National-Church of the <hi>Jews?</hi> If ſo, Then,</p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether he hath not (as of old he did, with reference unto the then Church) determined the whole of the Worſhip, appertaining un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, to whoſe Inſtitutions, without any humane additions, its the duty of ſouls ſoley to conform? Yea,</p>
               <p n="5">5. Whether he hath not now (as then) deſigned the ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, and Offices, his Wiſdom thought ſufficient for the management of the affairs of his Houſe, ſo that the invention of new ones by the ſons of men, is not only needleſs, but a daring advance againſt the Soveraignty, Care and Wiſdom of God over his Churches?</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether the Priviledges of Saints, be not every way as great and extenſive under the Goſpel, as thoſe under the Law? if ſo, then Whether the ſolemn deputation of men, ſignally pointed out by the Lord, for the adminiſtration of holy things in his Houſe, by the Body of his Church, be not now (as then) their peculiar Priviledge?</p>
               <p n="7">7. VVhether any Church in the World (we ſpeak of a viſible, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Church) hath greater ſecurity againſt Apoſtacy from God, and that ſore Judgment of having its Candleſtick removed (and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unchurched) than that People of the <hi>Jews</hi> had? if not, then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſuppoſing a National Church to be of the Inſtitution of Chriſt, it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43509:7"/> may not ſo come to paſs, that it may be ſo over-ſpread with corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that it may loſe the Eſſence of a Church, and juſtly be diſrobed of that appellation?</p>
               <p n="8">8. VVhether the Eccleſiaſtick and Spiritual Rulers, Governours, and Officers of ſuch a Collapſed Church, may not righteouſly, as of old, be accounted and eſteemed as falſe Prophets that go about to cauſe the people to forget the Name of the Lord (or his pure Worſhip) by their Lies (or unſcriptural Traditions, Innovaſions, and Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pageantries.)</p>
               <p n="9">9. VVhether Separation from ſuch a Collaſped Church, in reſpect of its Worſhip, Miniſters and Miniſtry, be not only juſtifiable, but, as of old, the duty of the Lord's faithful Remnant, that deſire to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him according to his Appointments? Yea,</p>
               <p n="10">10. VVhether, ſuppoſing a Church (ſo called) thus dreadfully, as aforeſaid, departed from the pure Inſtitutions of Chriſt, never to be according to Truth, a viſible inſtituted Church of Chriſt, and the Lord's poor People living in the Nation, never by their free conſent Members thereof, as it is on the pretended Churches part, moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard-of-Cruelty to compel them, ſo it be not on the part of the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Children of God, moſt ſtupendous folly, and diſvaluation of the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and ingratitude to God, for the Light and Liberty from the Yokes of men, received, imaginable, to joyn affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with it in Worſhip, or attend upon the ſelf-invented Miniſtry that appertains thereunto? Many more Queſtions of the like nature and importance might unto theſe be added.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The great care of Souls in their Acceſſes to God, ſhould be to ſanctifie his Name. Divine Inſtitution to be heeded in the whole of our Worſhip. The Queſtion propoſed. That 'tis lawful to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> denied: one Argument propoſed to conſideration. Nothing may be practiſed in inſtituted Worſhip, but what is warranted by the Scripture: The Teſtimonies of the Ancients produced. That Hearing is part of inſtituted Worſhip, proved.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THis is that which the Lord hath ſaid, <hi>I will be ſanctified in all that draw nigh me, and before all the People will I be glorified:</hi> The great care of Saints in matter of Worſhip, is to ſanctifie the Name of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43509:7"/> Lord therein: This is the great thing that God looks at, the omiſſion whereof he often ſeverely puniſhes the children of men for: now in order hereunto, it's neceſſary that in all our approaches to God we ſee to the Inſtitution of the Lord, both in reſpect of the matter and manner of Worſhip, that it be according to Divine Preſcript, elſe we cannot ſanctifie the Name of God therein, nor glorifie him before the people. Hearing (as was ſaid, and ſhall beyond contradiction in its proper place be evinced) is part of inſtituted Worſhip, it therefore more nearly concerns Saints than many are aware of, to have their conſciences reſolved from the Scriptures of God, in the matter under enquiry, Whether it be lawful for the Saints to hear the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England?</hi> 'Tis the Negative, we have received under our maintenance; becauſe we are ſatisfied Chriſt hath ſo; To the proof whereof we now addreſs our ſelves.</p>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 1.</head>
                  <p>That which there is no warrant for in the Scripture, being part of inſtituted Worſhip, is not lawful for the Saints to practiſe: But there is no warrant in the Scripture for hearing the preſent Miniſters or <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and hearing is part of inſtituted Worſhip. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> (or firſt) Propoſition is evident.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. From the nature of inſtituted Worſhip, which conſiſts in this, that it be of Divine Revelation; elſe whatever it is, it is not inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Worſhip.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. From the Verdict of Chriſt, who pronounces all the Worſhip of man <hi>to be vain and fruitleſs,</hi> and ſo unlawful, that is bottom'd on any thing but Divine Revelation, <hi>Mark</hi> 7. 7.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If it be lawful to conform to any one part of inſtituted Worſhip without warrant from Scripture, 'tis alſo lawful to conform to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a third, the whole, which would baniſh inſtituted Worſhip out of the world.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. To aſſert that it is lawful to conform to any part of inſtituted Worſhip, without warrant from Scripture, reflects ſadly upon the Wiſdom and Faithfulneſs of Chriſt; for either he was not wiſe enough to foreſee that ſuch a part of Worſhip was, or would be requiſite, or had not faithfulneſs enough to reveal it, though the Scripture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares him to <hi>Moſes</hi> for faithfulneſs, who revealed the whole Will of God, to the making of a pin in the Tabernacle.</p>
                  <p>6. It pours out contempt upon the Care of God over the New-Teſtament
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43509:8"/> Churches (as if it were leſs to theſe, then to the Church under the Law) and the Oeconomie of the Goſpel, as not ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat as that of old, the whole of whoſe VVorſhip, Orders and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances (as was ſaid) was bottom'd upon pure Revelation.</p>
                  <p>7. It carries with it a ſad reflection upon the Authority of the Scripture, as not thorowly furniſhed to make the man of God perfect.</p>
                  <p>8. The Lord condemns not only that which is done againſt the warrant and direction of the VVord, but alſo that which is done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide it, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. and 12. 32. <hi>Mat. 15. 9. Lev.</hi> 10. 1. (their ſin lay not in this, that they offered <hi>ſtrange fire</hi> which was forbidden, but which God commanded them not) <hi>Prov. 30. 6. Jer.</hi> 7. 31.</p>
                  <p>9. Of the ſame mind with us in this matter are the renowned VVitneſſes of Chriſt in all ages; generally all that write upon the ſecond Commandment, ſpeak fully hereunto.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> (in his Epiſt. to <hi>Caecilius de Sacram.</hi>) ſayes roundly, <hi>Et quod Chriſtus ſolus, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> that Chriſt alone ought to be heard: we have the Father himſelf witneſſing from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>This is my belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Son, hear him.</hi> Wherefore if Chriſt only be to be heard, we ought not to attend to what others did before us, but what he hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. <hi>Beza</hi> (on <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 1.) ſayes, <hi>Epiſcopos igitur, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle meaneth by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſuch as were ſet over others in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the VVord, viz. <hi>Paſtors, Teachers</hi> and <hi>Elders,</hi> for ſo were Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of old called, until he which for Polities ſake, did preſide in the Aſſembly, began peculiarly to be call'd <hi>Biſhop:</hi> hereof the Devil began to lay the firſt foundation of Tyranny in the Church of God: <hi>Behold</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>of how great moment it is to decline from the Word of God, though but an hairs breadth.</hi> So he. To whom may be added the Teſtimony of that lively Witneſs of Chriſt <hi>Martin Luther</hi> 
                     <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>In a Tranſlation of the New-Teſtament in</hi> Edward <hi>the 6ths time, the Author of the Notes on</hi> Matth. 15. <hi>ſaith,</hi> God will not be worſhipped after the doctrine &amp; precepts of men, but as he himſelf hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed and taught us in his Word.</note>, who ſayes, on 1 <hi>Pet. 4. 11. To the Office of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, that properly belongs, which the Apoſtle</hi> Peter <hi>preſcribeth,</hi> viz. <hi>unto whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the vocation and charge of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Word is allotted, let him ſpeak as the Words of God; which Caveat and Leſſon ought moſt carefully to be taken heed unto, that no man preſume to preach and teach any thing, whereto he hath not the expreſs words of God for his
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43509:8"/> warrant, and except he be moſt certain that the ſame be directly to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouched out of the ſacred Scriptures. Which being ſo, what may be thought of the Pope</hi> (we may add of the Hierarchy) <hi>and his dirty Traditions?</hi> And anon after, he ſaith, <hi>A Biſhop ought to do nothing in the Church, unleſs he be certain and ſure of the warrantiſe thereof by God's Word; for God cannot abide to have his Service jumbled and mingled at pleaſure with every fooliſh gewgaw and light trumpery;</hi> yea further, ſaith he, <hi>And therefore we are ſtrictly forbidden not to rely unto, nor to allow whatſoever decree or conſtitution the Biſhops liſt to obtrude, and enjoyn, unleſs they ſtand upon a ſure ground, that the things which they do, are allowed of God—and unleſs they be able to ſay, Do this; for it is the Will and Commandment of God, and we have his expreſs Word and Commandment for our warrant: if they be not able to ſay thus, they ought to be accounted as Liars and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, much leſs ought any Chriſtian to yeeld unto them therein any obedience or ſubſcription:</hi> And afterwards, <hi>There is nothing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſo pernitious, nothing ſo monſtrous, nothing ſo beaſtly, as to go about to govern the Church of God, without the Warrant of God's own Word.</hi> Of the ſame mind is learned <hi>Whitaker, We acknowledge</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no Oyl in God's Service, becauſe we reade nothing of Oyl in the Scriptures, can you ſhew that ever Chriſt or his Apostles uſed it?</hi> To whom many others might be added.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) conſiſts of two parts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Hearing is part of inſtituted Worſhip, one would wonder ſhould it be denied; however 'tis evident it is ſo, from the light of this ſingle demonſtration: That in which we wait upon God in the way of an Ordinance for the communication of good, beyond the vertue of any creature to conveigh to us, is part of the inſtituted Worſhip of God (for what I wait for, not being in the thing it ſelf, in which I am waiting, no ground can be aſſigned, for my expecting of good through it, but Divine Inſtitution) but in the Hearing of the Word we wait upon God in the way of an Ordinance, for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of good, beyond the vertue of any creature to conveigh to us: Therefore.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That Hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> is not warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Scripture: This will be manifeſted, when we come to the ventilating and ſcanning of thoſe places, which are uſually produced for the abetting of the practice of ſome in this matter: in the mean while we crave liberty to profeſs, that it is not opinionativeneſs, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularity, vain-glory, uncharitableneſs, or any thing of that nature;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43509:9"/> (as ſome are apt uncharitably enough to cenſure) but the dread and awe of God (who is a jealous God, and eſpecially in point of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip) and an holy fear of offending him, that hinders us from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying in theſe matters: could but one word, tittle or <hi>iota</hi> be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from the Scriptures of God, for the warranting the Hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> we ſhould quickly lay our mouths in the duſt, confeſs and bewail our guilt and folly in refuſing to conform thereunto; but this we are fully aſſured, thoſe that diſſent from us, are not able to do; what they ſay herein, ſhall <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> be ſifted to the uttermoſt.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſecond Argument propoſed to conſideration: That 'tis not lawful to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> as Miniſters of Chriſt, nor as Gifted Brethren, proved. A Separation from them, if Brethren, evinced. That the beſt of them walk diſorderly, proved.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 2.</head>
                  <p>IF it be lawful to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> 'tis lawful to hear them, either as Miniſters of the Goſpel, or as gifted Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: But 'tis not lawful to hear them, either as Miniſters of the Goſpel, or as Gifted-Brethren: Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) will not be denied; That Chriſt hath appointed ſome, as Miniſters, by vertue of an Office-power, to diſpenſe the Ordinances of the Goſpel, until his ſecond coming, is granted by all, that 'tis permitted to others, as their liberty, enjoyned them, as their duty (having received Gifts and Enablements from the Lord thereunto) to improve thoſe Gifts in preaching, praying, &amp;c. for the Edification of the Body of Chriſt (though not ſolemnly inveſted into Office) is aſſented unto, at leaſt by ſome of thoſe with whom we have to do; whence a lawfulneſs to hear them as Miniſters, or as Gifted-Brethren, doth neceſſarily ariſe.</p>
                  <p>'Tis the <hi>minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) that is capable, in the thoughts of ſome, of a denial: which we prove, <hi>per partes,</hi> thus.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. 'Tis not lawful to hear them as Miniſters of the Goſpel: they are not ſuch, therefore may not be heard as ſuch. That they are not Miniſters of the Goſpel (but Thieves and Robbers) is manifeſt: Such as come not in by the Door, which is Chriſt, <hi>Joh. 10. 9. (viz.</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43509:9"/> of any Authority derived to them from him) are not Miniſters of the Goſpel, but Thieves and Robbers, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. 1. (from whom 'tis the property of the Sheep to flee, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.) But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> come not in by the Door: Therefore.</p>
                  <p>That they come not in by the Door (<hi>viz.</hi> by vertue of any Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity derived to them from Chriſt) is evident: If they have received any ſuch Authority or Commiſſion from him, they have received it, either mediately, or immediately: the latter will not be aſſerted, nor without the working of Miracles, ſhould it ſo be, would it to the world's end be made good: 'Tis the former muſt be fixt upon, <hi>viz.</hi> That they have received their Authority or Commiſſion, mediately from Chriſt, but to as little purpoſe; for thoſe that receive Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to preach the Goſpel mediately from Chriſt, have it from ſome particular inſtituted Church of Chriſt, to whom power is ſoley dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated for the electing of their own Officers, according to the tenour of the enſuing Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 5. &amp; 14. 23.</p>
                  <p>Theſe men (as it's known) have no ſuch Authority, pretend not to it, have it in deriſion, come barely with a Preſentation from a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, and Ordination, Inſtitution and Induction from a Lord-Biſhop (things forreign to the Scripture) and impoſe themſelves upon the people whether they will or no.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. 'Tis not lawful to hear them as Gifted-Brethren. 1. The moſt of them are not gifted; nor 2. Brethren, being <hi>Canonical-Drunkards, Swearers, Gamſters, &amp;c.</hi> 3. The beſt of them cannot by Saints, in reſpect of Goſpel-communion, be ſo accounted: for, 1. There was never any giving up of our ſelves, each to other, according to the will of God and primitive Example, whence ſuch a Brotherhood doth reſult. 2. We cannot (as things ſtand) perform the duties of Brethren to them, according to <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. nor will they, or can they, in the ſtate in which they ſtand, to us. 3. If we acknowledge the beſt of them for ſuch, we muſt alſo acknowledge the worſt of them: for, 1. They are all Members of the ſame Church. 2. Profeſs themſelves to be one Brotherhood, ſo ſayes their Rime upon the Lord's Prayer,</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Our Father which in Heaven art,</l>
                     <l>And mak'ſt us all one Brotherhood, &amp;c.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Nay, 3. we cannot ſo acknowledge them, but we muſt alſo acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the Biſhops for our Reverend Fathers, (for theirs they are) which how abhorring it is to any tender enlightned ſoul, may eaſily
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43509:10"/> be conjectured. But to hear this Plea ſpeak its uttermoſt, let it be granted they are Brethren, and may be ſo eſteemed; They are Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that walk diſorderly, or they do not: That they walk diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot be denied by ſuch as pretend to Reformation, If ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to Ordination or Re-ordination by a Lord Biſhop, covenanting and proteſting with deteſtation againſt a Reformation according to the Scripture, and the beſt Reformed Churches, to own (as conſonant to Scripture) a <hi>Lyturgy</hi> or ſtinted Forms of Prayer in the Church, and read them, to wear the Surplice, &amp;c. be diſorderly walking; they are (the very beſt of them) beyond contradiction, to be reputed in the number of <hi>diſorderly walkers;</hi> And ſo after due admonition (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture) and a perſeverance in their ſin, to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from, by vertue of poſitive and expreſs Precepts of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 18. 2 Theſſ. 3. 6. Now we command you, Brethren, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that you withdraw your ſelves from every Brother that walketh diſorderly, and not after the tradition he received of us:</hi> With what vehemency, authority and holy earneſtneſs doth the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle preſs <hi>ſeparation</hi> from Brethren that walk diſorderly? <hi>We command you,</hi> and <hi>we command you in the Name of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and <hi>we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you, Brethren, by vertue of our relation to each other, and that love and endearment that is betwixt us as Brethren, that you withdraw your ſelves, &amp;c.</hi> I ſcarce know any one thing preſſed by the Apoſtle, with greater vehemency than what is here inſtanc'd in: wherein we have alſo an undeniable convincing Argument, that the perſons of whom we are treating, walk diſorderly. Thoſe that walk not after the tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion received from the Apoſtles (we may adde, and the Primitive Church for above three hundred years after Chriſt, but according to the traditions of the old <hi>Bawd</hi> and <hi>Strumpet</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) are ſuch as walk diſorderly: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> walk not after the Tradition received from the Apoſtles, but after the Traditions of the Whoriſh-Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> Therefore they are ſuch as <hi>walk diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly.</hi> What Apoſtolical Tradition have we for ſtinted Forms of Prayer or Lyturgies in the Church, did they frame any? (thoſe that are aſcribed to ſome of them, are all ſpurious, as hath been over and over proved) for Surplice, croſſing in Baptiſm, and many other gewgaws uſed by them? if they have any Apoſtolical written tradition for theſe things, let them produce it, and we ſhall lay our mouths in the duſt, and for ever be ſilent, as to a charge of this nature: If they have
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43509:10"/> not (as there is nothing more certain) they are <hi>diſorderly walkers,</hi> if the Apoſtles Argument be valid, <hi>We command you to withdraw from ſuch as walk diſorderly.</hi> But who, I pray, are theſe diſorderly walkers? how ſhall we know them? <hi>they are</hi> (ſayes the Apoſtle) <hi>ſuch as walk not after the tradition received from us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A third Argument proving the unlawfulneſs of hearing the preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>England,</hi> produced. That they act by vertue of an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Office and Calling, proved. Their perfect agreement with the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Prieſts in ſeventeen Particulars, demonſtrated. That the Office of Lord Biſhops is Antichriſtian, proved. (The Teſtimonies of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients produced) Whence the Antichriſtianiſm of the Office of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England</hi> is evinced. An Objection anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 3.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that act in the holy things of God by vertue of an Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Power, Office or Calling, are not to be heard, but to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from: but the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> act in the Holy Things of God by vertue of an Antichriſtian Power, Office or Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> is evident. For 1. The Power, Office and Calling of Antichriſt is oppoſite and contrary unto the Power, Office and Calling of Chriſt: Not to ſeparate from ſuch as act by vertue of ſuch an Office-Power, is to ſtand by, and plead for Antichriſt, againſt Chriſt. 2. Its unlawful to attend upon the teachings of Antichriſt, therefore upon the teachings of ſuch as act by vertue of a Power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him. 3. Chriſt calls, and ſolemnly charges his, upon the penalty of moſt dreadful Judgments, to ſeparate from every thing of Antichriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 4. and 14. 9, 10, 11. 4. There is not a command in the Scripture enjoyning Saints to <hi>take heed of being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> to <hi>try the ſpirits,</hi> becauſe <hi>many Antichriſts are gone abroad into the World,</hi> but is an abundant demonſtration of the truth of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion. 5. The inſtitution of Officers of his own, by Chriſt, to be continued in the way appointed by him to the end of the World, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 11. 6. That there is not one promiſe of a bleſſing in the whole Scripture upon perſons atending on ſuch a Miniſtry, with innumerable things of the like tendency and import, that might be produced if
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43509:11"/> needful, are ſuch a baſis upon which the truth of the <hi>major</hi> Propoſition ſtands, as cannot be eaſily ſhaken or removed.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> wants not ſufficient demonſtration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> The preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> are either from Chriſt or from Antichriſt. There is no <hi>medium</hi> (a Linſey-woolſey-Miniſtry, that is partly of Chriſt, partly of Antichriſt, as 'tis not to be proved by Scripture, ſo will it not be abetted) That they are not from Chriſt, hath in part been proved already, and may farther be evinced.</p>
                  <p>1. Their Names are forreign to the Scripture: Where reade we of <hi>Deacons</hi> in their ſence, <hi>Prieſts,</hi> as diſtinguiſhed from Chriſtians, in the New-Teſtament, <hi>Deans, Cannons, Petty-Cannons, Prebendaries, Arch-Deacons, Lord-Biſhops, Parſons, Vicars? &amp;c.</hi> theſe are onely found in the Popes Pontifical, whence they are derived. So are 2. Their Offices: Deacons attending Tables we reade of, but Deacons Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Preaching, Adminiſtring Sacraments (ſo called) by vertue of an Office-power, an order of the firſt ſtep to the Prieſthood, we find not: Prieſts in the Old-Teſtament (both true and falſe) we reade of; in the New, Saints are ſo called; Firſt, in reſpect of analogie to the ritual Prieſts of old, whoſe prerogative it was to come near to God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 5. to whom, through Chriſt, Saints have acceſs with bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 18. and 3. 19. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 8. Secondly, in reſpect of their union and engrafture into Chriſt the great High-Prieſt over the Houſe of God. Thirdly, in reſpect of that analogy there is betwixt what Chriſt hath done for them as Prieſt, and by his Spirit worketh in them: He offered up Sacrifice; ſo do they, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116. 17. and 141. 2. <hi>Rom. 12. 1. Heb.</hi> 13. 14. He was crucified, died; ſo are they, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8. &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. Fourthly, as Prieſts, they are anointed to the participation of, do thereby attain to, a kind of holy and intimate communion with Chriſt, in all his glorious Offices, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 10. But an Office of Prieſthood in men for the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, that are to be bounded by men in that their Office, muſt preach what they would have them, and ceaſe when they would have them (as is the caſe of the preſent Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi>) the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is a ſtranger to: So is it 3. to their admiſſion into this their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>viz.</hi> by a Lord-Biſhop, without the conſent of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in which they act as Officers. The very truth is, both in their Names, Office, and admiſſion thereunto, the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> ſymbolize not with the Miniſters of Chriſt, but the Popiſh
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43509:11"/> order of Prieſts: (ſo that if theſe do act by vertue of an Antichriſtian office-power, then do they) as he that runs may read in the enſuing parallel particulars.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They are both called, and own themſelves <hi>Prieſts;</hi> which though ſome may make light of, yet conſidering that it is a term bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed, either from the Prieſts of the Law, the aſſertion of ſuch a Prieſthood being a denial of Chriſt come in the fleſh; or from the Prieſts of the Heathen (in conformity to whom, as the <hi>Druides</hi> of old, our Prieſts wear their white Garment or Surplice) or from the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian Church (ſo called) of <hi>Rome:</hi> Such idolatrous ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious names being commanded by the Lord to be aboliſhed, <hi>Hoſ. 2. 15. Zech.</hi> 13. 2. wants not its ſufficient weight; the retention where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being alſo a ſore ſuſpition of too great a compliance with, if not a willingneſs to return to that from whence they are derived. Of the ſame mind with us herein is <hi>Hierom</hi> upon the 2d of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew</hi> Doctors, <hi>Kimchi</hi> and <hi>Aben-Ezra,</hi> the <hi>Caldee</hi> Paraphraſt, <hi>Ribera</hi> (though a <hi>Jeſuit) Zanchi, Danaeus, Sanctius, Polanus, Rivet,</hi> and almoſt all that write upon the ſaid Scripture. The laſt mentioned, <hi>viz.</hi> Learned <hi>Rivet,</hi> hath theſe words in his Corollaries from <hi>Hoſ. 2. 15, 16. There are many names which in themſelves are good enough, and might be uſed, but God abhorreth the uſe of them, becauſe they have been abuſed to Idolatry:</hi> he inſtanceth indeed in the word <hi>Maſs;</hi> but Prieſt or Altar being of the ſame allay, upon the ſame foot of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, is to be rejected. The reformed Churches in <hi>Helvetia,</hi> in their harmony of Confeſſions, are of the ſame mind; <hi>The Miniſtry</hi> (ſay they) <hi>and the Prieſthood are things far different the one from the other—he himſelf</hi> (viz. <hi>Chriſt) remaineth only Prieſt for ever; and we do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the name<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Prieſt <hi>to any Miniſter, leſt we ſhould detract ſomething from Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be firſt Deacons ere they are Prieſts: So muſt the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be ordained to their Office by a Lord-Biſhop or his Suffragan: So muſt the Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt at their ordination, be preſented by an Archdeacon or his Deputy, with theſe words, <hi>Reverende Pater, &amp;c. Reverend Father, I preſent theſe men unto thee, to be admitted unto the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Prieſthood:</hi> So are the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. The Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be ordained to their office according
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43509:12"/> to their Pontifical, deviſed by themſelves: the Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Book of ordering Prieſts and Deacons (which is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Popes Pontifical, as is evident to any that ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the one with the other, and as hath been long ſince confeſt by ſome of themſelves, in an Admonition to the Parliament in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> dayes, in their ſecond Treatiſe.)</p>
                  <p n="6">6. The Popiſh Prieſts muſt kneel down upon their knees at the feet of the Lord-Biſhop that ordains them, and he muſt ſay to them, blaſphemouſly enough, <hi>Receive ye the Holy Ghoſt; Whoſe ſins ye remit, or forgive, they are remitted; whoſe ſins ye retain, they are retained:</hi> which exactly accords with the faſhion of ordaining the Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7. The Popiſh Prieſts are not ordained in and before the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to whom they are to be Prieſts, but in ſome Metropolitan, Cathedral City, ſeveral miles from the place: So are the Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. The Popiſh Prieſts take the care of ſouls, though not elected by them, from the preſentation of a Patron, by the inſtitution and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of a Lord-Biſhop: and do not the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> the ſame?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. The Popiſh Prieſts wait not the Churches Call to the Miniſtry, but make ſuit to ſome Prelate to be ordained Prieſts, giving mony for their letters of Ordination: So do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10. The Popiſh Prieſts are ordained to their Office, though they have no Flock to attend upon: So are the Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. The Popiſh Prieſts muſt ſwear Canonical Obedience to their Ordinary: So do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="12">12. The Popiſh Prieſts may at their pleaſure, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the People, reſign and give over their Benefices, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take themſelves to ſome other of greater value: A ſymmetrie with them herein is viſible, by the frequent practiſe of the Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. The Popiſh Prieſts, though ordained to preach, muſt have ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Licence from the Prelates ſo to do: So muſt the Prieſts of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">14. The Popiſh Prieſts are ſubject to be ſilenced, ſuſpended, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived and degraded by the Prelates; as are the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43509:12"/>15. The Popiſh Prieſts are not of like and equal Power, Degree, and Authority amongſt themſelves, but are ſome of them inferior to others herein; as Parſons to Archdeacons, Archdeacons to Lord Biſhops, Lord-Biſhops to Archbiſhops: So the Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">16. The Popiſh Prieſts muſt be diſtinguiſhed from other People by their Veſtments, as Surplice, Tippet, &amp;c. So muſt the Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="17">17. The Popiſh Prieſts are tyed to a Book of ſtinted Prayers, and a preſcript Order, deviſed by man, for their Worſhip and Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: So are the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> and that to ſuch an one as is taken out of the Popes <hi>Portuis,</hi> as hath been proved by divers: That the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> in <hi>Edward</hi> the 6ths time was ſo, you have his, with his Councils Teſtimony for it; thus they write, <hi>As for the Service in the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Tongue, it hath manifeſt Reaſons for it, and yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance it ſeemeth to you a New Service, and indeed is no other but the Old, the ſame words in</hi> Engliſh <hi>which were in</hi> Latine—<hi>If the Service of the Church were good in</hi> Latine, <hi>it is good in</hi> Engliſh. How little diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book</hi> now in uſe is thereunto, they that wil take pains to compare the one with the other, may be ſatisfied.</p>
                  <p>To theſe parallel particulars might be added ſundry more, wherein there is an exact ſymmetry betwixt the Popiſh Prieſts, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> but—<hi>Ex ungue Leonem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſum of what we have been offering in this matter, is this.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, Thoſe Miniſters that in their Names, Offices, admiſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Offices, are not to be found in the Scripture, are not Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, act not by vertue of an Authority, Office, Power, Calling, received from him.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Thoſe Minſters that in their Names, Office, admiſſion into their Office, are at a perfect agreement with the Miniſters of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt (ſuch are the Popiſh Prieſts acknowledged to be by thoſe with whom we have to do) are not the Miniſters of Chriſt, have not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived any Power, Office or Calling from him to act in the <hi>holy things of God:</hi> But ſuch (as hath been abundantly demonſtrated) are the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England;</hi> Therefore theſe have received no Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Office or Calling from Chriſt, and ſo are Antichriſtian.</p>
                  <q>—<hi>Quod erat demonſtrandum.</hi>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thoſe that receive their Power, Office and Calling from a Lord-Biſhop, and act in the holy things of God by vertue of that
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43509:13"/> Power, Office, or Calling, act in the holy things of God by vertue of an Antichriſtian Power, Office and Calling: But the preſent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>England</hi> receive their Power, Office and Calling from a Lord-Biſhop, and act in the Holy Things of God by vertue of that Power, Office and Calling. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The conſequence of the <hi>major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) is manifeſt, the Office of Lord-Biſhops is Antichriſtian, therefore thoſe that act by vertue of a Power, Office or Calling received from them, act by vertue of an Antichriſtian Power, Office or Calling.</p>
                  <p>That the Office of Lord-Biſhops is Antichriſtian, one would won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould be denied in ſuch a day as this, after ſo full a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof by many Witneſſes of Chriſt, who have wrote ſo cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this matter, as if they carried the Sun beams in their right hand, eſpecially that it ſhould be denied by perſons of <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregational</hi> Principles (if indeed any of them do deny it.) To pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute this matter to the uttermoſt is not our preſent intendment, the intelligent Reader knows where to find it done already to our hand; and if after all that hath been ſaid, any through ſelf-love, or fear of perſecution, will herein be ignorant, we might ſay, <hi>Let them be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.</hi> But we ſhall propoſe briefly a word or two in this matter.</p>
                  <p>1. That Office that is not to be found in the Scriptures of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, but is contrary to expreſs precepts and commands of his, is Antichriſtian: But the Office of Lord-Biſhops is not to be found in the Scriptures, is contrary to expreſs Precepts. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
                  <q>The <hi>minor</hi> Propoſition conſiſts of two parts.</q>
                  <p n="1">1. That the Office of Lord Biſhops is not to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the inſtitution of Chriſt: He gave indeed <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Paſtors and Teachers,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 11. of <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> we reade, <hi>Rom. 12. 7, 8. Eph. 4. 8. Biſhops</hi> alſo, and <hi>Deacons,</hi> without the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of any other order, we find, 1 <hi>Tim. 3. 12. Deacons</hi> we have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, <hi>Acts 7. Elders,</hi> Acts 14. 23. thoſe who are Biſhops we find called <hi>Presbyters, Tit.</hi> 1. 5, 7. and thoſe who are <hi>Presbyters,</hi> we find termed <hi>Biſhops,</hi> Acts 20. 28. (Gr. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Biſhops) but where the Office of Lord-Biſhops was inſtituted by Chriſt, we are yet to ſeek: indeed ſome appearances of a ſpirit ſtriving to aſcend into this Chair of wickedneſs, was ſeen in <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> and others in the Apoſtles time, but theſe were the Antichriſts that were then gone abroad into the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43509:13"/> world. The Scripture before mentioned, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11. ſpeaks as fully to the Officers and Offices inſtituted by Chriſt, as any we meet with: Fail they in their deduction of their Office from hence, and they will undoubtedly prove ſucceſleſs in their attempts. Let us then fix here a little; mention we find here of <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> none at all either here, or elſewhere, of Lord-Biſhops. But perhaps their Office, though they are called by another name, is comprized in ſome one or other of theſe, let that then be conſidered. Are they Prophets? that (in the ſence of the Spirit in this place) they will not pretend to. Are they Paſtors or Teachers? this is too great a debaſement of their Lordſhips, their Parochial Prieſts over whom they preſide, are ſuppoſed to be Officers in that degree. What then are they? Apoſtles! Their Succeſſors they do indeed boaſt themſelves to be, and are ſo accounted by their Abbettors (and ſo doth the Pope himſelf) but how prove they their Succeſſion from them? if they derive it through the Papacy, who ſees not the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>validity thereof? How lubricous and uncertain is that their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? how do they therein proclaim their ſhame, and yield the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in controverſie? what clearer Argument that they are Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, if the Pope be the Antichriſtian Head over many Countries, as is by the generality of Proteſtants believed, and will not by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves be gainſayed? But in what ſence do they pretend to be the Apoſtles Succeſſors? do they ſucceed them as Chriſtians? that is not the thing in queſtion, they ſtand or fall, in reſpect thereof to their own Maſter; herein we have no controverſie with them, as not willing to judge any thing before the time. Do they ſucceed them in reſpect of their Office? let them prove that, and take the Cauſe. The Apoſtles were firſt immediatly <hi>Sent</hi> by Chriſt: Secondly, Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Officers, <hi>Commiſſionated</hi> to the preaching of the Goſpel throughout the Nations of the world: Are their Lordſhips ſuch? what can be imagined more frivolous or falſe? where find we any Apoſtles after the departure of thoſe that were immediatly by Chriſt called to that Office? Did the Apoſtles ordain any as their Succeſſors therein, in any of the Churches of Chriſt? Where reade we of their ſo doing? yea, are any qualified with Gifts as they, for the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of ſuch an Office? or doth Chriſt indeed ſend forth Servants in any imployment, and not furniſh them with Gifts ſuitable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? <hi>Credat Apelles!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43509:14"/>
                  <p>What more diſhonourable to the Lord Jeſus can be aſſerted? it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains then, that they being neither Prophets, nor Apoſtles, nor Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, nor Teachers, that they are not to be found in the Scripture of the inſtitution of Chriſt. Nor are they dream'd of in the world for ſeveral hundreds of years after Chriſt. <hi>Clemens</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> takes notice of no other beſides <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons,</hi> which Biſhops he calls <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Presbyters</hi> or <hi>Elders:</hi> Yea, <hi>Lombard</hi> himſelf confeſſes, <hi>Hos ſolum Miniſtrorum duos ordines, Eccleſiam primitivam habuiſſe, &amp; de his Solis, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptum Apoſtoli nos habere: Lomb. l. 4. Sen. D. 24. li. 3. ext.</hi> The Primitive Church, he tells you, had no other Order of Miniſters, than Biſhops (or Presbyters) and Deacons; nor did the Apoſtles give commandment concerning any other. That their riſe and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion was from the aims and deſigns of men, to accommodate Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical or Church-affairs to the ſtate and condition of the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, is ingenuouſly confeſt by one that was looked upon to be as great an Admirer of, and as able a Champion for, Dioceſan and Metropolitical Prelates, as any one of late dayes; 'tis Dr. <hi>Hamond</hi> we mind, who in his Diſſertations about <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> Sect. 3. hath theſe words, <hi>His ſic poſitis, illud ſtatim ſequitur ut (in Imperli cognitione) in Provinciâ qualibet, cum plures urbes ſint, una tamen primaria, et prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalis conſenda erat, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> Ideo dicta cui itidem inferiores reliquae Civitates ſubjiciebantur, ut Civitatibus Regiones, ſic et inter Eccleſias, et Cathedras Epiſcopales, unam ſemper primariam, &amp; Metropoliticam fuiſſe:</hi> So far is the Office of Lord-Biſhops from being of the Inſtitution of Chriſt, that their Primacy and Supremacy was the reſult of the deſigns and contrivements of men to accommodate the ſtate and frame of the Church, to the ſtate and condition of the Government of the Nations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Office of Lord Biſhops is contrary to expreſs Precepts of Chriſt in the Scripture; the truth of which, he that runs may reade in the enſuing Scriptures, <hi>Mat. 20. 25. Mark 10. 42. Luke 22. 25. 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 3. the Engliſh of, <hi>Vos autem non ſic,</hi> but ye ſhall not do ſo; <hi>Neque ut Dominantes Cleris,</hi> not lording it over God's Clergy or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage, an ordinary Reader may eaſily conclude to be inconſiſtent with their fordly dignities. Not to multiply Arguments in a matter that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſo largely debated. 2. That Office that is derived from, and is only to be found in the Papacy, is ſurely Antichriſtian (if the Pope be the head of Antichriſt, this muſt not be denied) But the Office of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43509:14"/> Lord Biſhops is derived from, is onely to be found in, the Papacy. Which of the reformed Churches that have ſeparated from the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy have retained it? Did the <hi>Woman</hi> in her flight into the Wilderneſs carry it along with her? What more abſurd, then to run to the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Whore and Beaſt for an Office of Miniſtry? and what more evident demonſtration of its being an Antichriſtian office, than its entertainment only by that falſe Antichriſtian Church, and its utter rejection and deteſtation by the <hi>true Spouſe</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of Chriſt in all Ages? What is delivered over to us in this matter by ſome of them, we ſhall briefly affix hereunto. <hi>Hierome</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius,</hi> and in his Commentary upon the Epiſtle of <hi>Titus,</hi> profeſſes, <hi>That it is more by Cuſtom than by any Inſtitution of the Lord, that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are become greater than the Elders or Miniſters.</hi> Har. of Conf. <hi>ſect. 2. Tit.</hi> 11. So from him do the Churches of <hi>Helvetia</hi> proclaim, whence they infer (and that truly according to <hi>Act. 4. 9.) That no man by any right can forbid, but that we ſhould return to the old Appointment of God, and rather receive that, than the Cuſtom deviſed by men. Wickliff</hi> in his anſwer to King <hi>Richard</hi> the 2d, citing <hi>Mat. 20. 25. 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 3. ſayes, <hi>Lordſhip and Dominion is plainly forbidden to the Apoſtles, and dareſt thou then uſurp the ſame? if thou wilt be a Lord, thou ſhalt loſe thy Apoſtleſhip, &amp;c.</hi> The Univerſity of <hi>Geneva</hi> ſay, [<hi>Theſes Genev. 71.] Theſe Functions following, we hold to be altogether falſe, and deſtitute of all true foundation,</hi> viz. <hi>the Primacy of the Biſhop of</hi> Rome <hi>over all Churches; the Cardinalſhip, Patriarchſhip, Archiepiſcopalſhip, and briefly the whole Epiſcopal degree of Lord Biſhops over their fellow Elders. Marlorat</hi> in his Expoſition on the <hi>Revelation,</hi> chap. 17. 3. ſays, <hi>That Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Deans, &amp;c. are in office under Antichriſt;</hi> yea, upon chap. 9. <hi>that they are the tails of Antichriſt.</hi> Beza ſaith, <hi>They could not be brought into the Church, until they had driven him out who is the onely Maſter, Chriſt; and, there is neither holy Scripture, nor Council, nor Ancient Doctors which ever did know ſuch Monſters,</hi> Beza's Confeſ. Art. 7. c. 14. The Noble Ancient <hi>Old-Caſtle,</hi> Lord <hi>Cobham,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That the whole Epiſcopal degree of Lord Biſhops over their Fellow-Elders, is altogether falſe, and deſtitute of all true foundation—yea, that all other Functions and Offices beſides Prieſts and Deacons are unlawful, as being Sects devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by men deſtitute of all true Foundation.</hi> To theſe we might add Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt <hi>Bale</hi> upon the <hi>Revelation,</hi> viz. <hi>chap.</hi> 17. where he ſaith, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury <hi>and</hi> York <hi>are the Beaſtly Antichriſt's Metropolitans, and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates,</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:43509:15"/> and upon chap. 13. <hi>that Arch-Biſhop, Dioceſan, Arch-Deacon, Dean, Prebend, Doctor, Parſon, Vicar, &amp;c. are very names of Blasphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my: For Offices they are not appointed by the Holy Ghoſt, nor yet mentioned in the Scripture.</hi> Cartwright ſaies of them, <hi>That their functions are not in the Word of God, but of the Earth, new deviſed Miniſtries, and ſuch as can do no good: that their Office is the neek of the Popiſh Hierarchie, come out of the bottomleſs Pit of Hell. Fenner</hi> proclaims them, <hi>to be no natural Members of the Body of Chriſt's Church, as being of humane addition, not born with her, nor grown up with her from the Cradle.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Belgick</hi> Confeſſion ſayes, <hi>That they paſs not a Ruſh for them.</hi> The Church of <hi>Geneva, That the Hierarchie is deviliſh Confuſion, ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed (as it were) in despight of God, and to the mocking and reproach of all Chriſtian Religion.</hi> The <hi>Seekers</hi> of Reformation in Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> time ſpeak fully hereunto, [2 <hi>Adm. to Parl.] We have an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian and Popiſh ordering of Prieſts, ſtrange from the Word of God, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of in the Primative Church, taken out of the Popes ſhop, to the deſtruction of Gods Kingdome—The names and offices of Arch-Biſhops, Arch-Deacons, Lord-Biſhops, &amp;c. are, together with their Government, drawn out of the Popes ſhop, Antichriſtian, Deviliſh, and contrary to the Scriptures: Parſons, Vicars, Pariſh-Prieſts, are birds of the ſame feather, to whom might be added many others.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> One ſtone of offence muſt be removed out of our way ere we paſs on further, it is this: <hi>Though Lord Biſhops are Antichristian, yet it doth not follow, that the Office and Ministry derived from them is ſo: For they are alſo</hi> Presbyters, <hi>and ordain as</hi> Presbyters.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> Give me leave to ſay, That were not men reſolved to ſay any thing that they might be thought to have ſomewhat to ſay, we had not heard of this Objection. For, 1. That they act in the capacity of <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the matter of Ordination, is falſe (1.) Contrary to their own avowed principles; their Lordſhips think it too great a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſement, to be degraded from their Lordly Dignity, to ſo mean an Office. (2.) Contrary to the known Law of the Land, by which they receive power to act therein, in which they are known and owned onely in the capacity of Lord-Biſhops. (3.) Contrary to their late practice, whereby they have ſufficiently declared the <hi>nullity</hi> of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial Office, received from the hands of a <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> in thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of doors ſeveral hundreds of Miniſters ſo ordained. Strange! that it ſhould be pleaded, they act as <hi>Presbyters</hi> in the matter of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:43509:15"/> and yet they themſelves judge a <hi>Presbyterian-Ordination</hi> invalid. But 2. What if this ſhould be granted? it would avail nothing, except it can be proved, that they are and act as <hi>Presbyters</hi> of the Inſtitution of Chriſt, which (theſe being only in a particular inſtitued Church of Chriſt) will never be to the worlds end. Thus far of the third Argument.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A fourth Argument, proving the unlawfulneſs of hearing the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters of <hi>England.</hi> A twofold denial of the Offices of Christ, aſſerted. That the preſent Ministers deny his Kingly and Prophetical Office, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from their Non-conformity to the Orders and Ordinances appointed by Christ for his Houſe. Several Inſtitutions of Chriſt remarked: Their Non-Conformity thereunto, manifeſted. An Objection anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 4.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that oppugn or deny any of the Offices of Jeſus Chriſt, are not to be heard, but ſeparated from: but the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England</hi> oppugn and deny ſome of the Offices of Jeſus Chriſt: Therefore.</p>
                  <p>Before we come to clear the ſeveral parts of this Argument, we ſhall crave liberty breifly to premiſe,</p>
                  <p>Firſt, That there is a twofold denying or oppugning of the Offices of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Verbal and Profeſſional. Such was, and is that of the <hi>Jews;</hi> the <hi>Papists</hi> are not guilty hereof; in words they own, preach up, plead for all the Offices of Chriſt as much as any: So do alſo the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England:</hi> This is not then the denial of the Offices of Chriſt we implede them as guilty of.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Real and actual, when perſons do that which enwraps in the bowels of it, an impugning and denial of the Offices of Chriſt. This the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Synagogue are eminently guilty of: So are the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England,</hi> as ſhall (we doubt not) be clearly demonſtrated in its proper place.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That a Verbal Profeſſional acknowledgement of the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Chriſt is nothing, when contradicted in practice: This the Apoſtle avowedly aſſerts, in reſpect of the knowledge of God, <hi>Tit. 1. 16. They profeſs they know God, but in works they deny him:</hi> And
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43509:16"/> may congruouſly enough be applied to the matter in hand. This, as applied to the Combination and Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſome of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have long ſince acknowledged, Whilſt they profeſs Chriſt to be King, and ſubmit not to the Laws he hath preſcribed in his Word, they make him an Idol, and put a Scepter of reed in his hand: So ſome of their own.</p>
                  <p>But I interrogate; What if a man ſhould with the greateſt earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs profeſs, and in the height of a confident Spirit aver, That he were Born again of God, Waſhed, Sanctified in the Blood of Chriſt, and by the Spirit of the Lord, that he did receive and own Chriſt as his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> when I ſee this man at the ſame time walking in a way of Rebellion againſt Chriſt, in open contempt and defiance of his Laws and Government, ſubjecting to the Yoak of other Lords and Lawgivers; Shall his Plea be admitted? ſurely no!</p>
                  <q>Quid verba audiam, cum facta videam.</q>
                  <p>Tis long ſince decided by Chriſt, That <hi>Falſe-Prophets</hi> are to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcried, Not by their words (they may <hi>ſpeak</hi> like Angels, cry <hi>Hail Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, kiſs him,</hi> yet be <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> yea <hi>Judaſses</hi> to him) but by their <hi>fruits:</hi> Let them profeſs a thouſand times over, <hi>That they own all the Offices of Christ,</hi> if they are in the mean while found in the practiſe of thoſe things that are inconſiſtent with the truth of ſuch a Profeſſion, they are really <hi>Deniers</hi> and <hi>Oppoſers</hi> of the Offices of Chriſt. This is that then we affirm in this matter. 1. That thoſe that do really oppoſe any of the Offices of Chriſt, are not to be heard, but ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from: This carrying a brightneſs along with it, that is ſufficient to convince all, except ſuch, whoſe eyes the god of this world hath blinded; that its original is from God, we ſhall take for granted will not be denied by a Profeſſing Enlightened People, though otherwiſe it were eaſie to multiply Arguments for its demonſtration. 1. To oppoſe Chriſt in any of his Offices, beſpeaks ſuch as are guilty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be <hi>Antichrists, 1 John</hi> 2. 22. and 4. 2, 3. 2 <hi>John</hi> 7. (of the ſame mind with us herein is learned <hi>Beza</hi> upon the forecited Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) and none will ſurely be ſo inconſiderate (not to ſay worſe) as to aſſert, It's lawful to attend upon the Miniſtry of Antichriſt. 2. To hear ſuch, is to ſtrengthen and encourage them in that their <hi>denial</hi> of, and <hi>oppoſition</hi> unto, the Offices of <hi>Christ;</hi> and thereby be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come partakers with them in their ſin: The thought of which, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be grievous to the poor Lambs of <hi>Christ.</hi> But this will not be denied.</p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43509:16"/>
                  <p>'Tis the ſecond thing may ſound harſh in the ears of ſome (as did ſome Sayings of Chriſt, but if Truth, where God ſhall give the ſeeing eye and hearing eare, 'twill be received) <hi>viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. <hi>That the preſent Ministers of</hi> England <hi>do</hi> oppoſe <hi>and</hi> deny <hi>ſome of the Offices of Christ,</hi> viz. <hi>His Kingly and Prophetical Office,</hi> which we come now to the proof of.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument. 1.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that hearken not to the Revelation Chriſt hath made, and as Supream Lord and Law-giver, hath enjoyned to be obſerved touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Orders and Ordinances of his Houſe, deny the Prophetical and Kingly Office of Chriſt, <hi>Deut. 18. 18. Acts 3. 22. Iſa.</hi> 9. 6. But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> hearken and conform not to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation Chriſt hath made touching the Orders and Ordinances of his Houſe: Therefore.</p>
                  <p>Tis the <hi>minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) that in the thoughts of ſome is capable of a denial, but the verity thereof ſhines forth as the Sun in its brightneſs, in the review of the Orders and Ordinances of the Houſe of Chriſt appointed by himſelf; and the preſent frame and deportment of the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> with reſpect thereunto: Which of them have they not made void by their Traditions? This is that which Chriſt hath ſaid, (1.) That <hi>all power</hi> for the Calling, Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, Order and Government of his Church, <hi>is inveſted ſolely in him,</hi> as the alone Lord, Sovereign-Ruler, and Head thereof, <hi>Mat. 28. 19. 1 Tim. 6. 14, 15. John 3. 35. Acts</hi> 3. 22. and 5. 31. Tis upon this foot of account that Chriſt chargeth his Diſciples, not to be called of men <hi>Rabbi,</hi> nor to call any <hi>Father (viz.</hi> not to impoſe their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority upon any, or ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed upon by any in the matters of their God) <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 8, 9, 10. becauſe <hi>one is their Master and Lord</hi> (viz. <hi>Christ</hi>) Hence alſo the Apoſtles lay the weight of their Exhortations upon the Commandment of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 23. and 14. 37. proclaim all <hi>to be accurſed that preach any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Gal.</hi> 1. 8. (yea <hi>though Angels from Heaven,</hi> ſhould they live and ſpeak as ſuch) charge thoſe to whom they write, <hi>Not to receive any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their houſes that bring any other Doctrine</hi> (much more not to receive them as their Teachers) 2 <hi>John</hi> 10. yea, the Spirit of the Lord in the cloſe of the laſt Revelation of his Will, it pleaſed this great King and Lawgiver, in ſuch a way to give forth; teſtifies, <hi>That if any man ſhall adde unto theſe things, the Lord ſhall adde unto him the Plagues that are</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:43509:17"/> 
                     <hi>written in his Book,</hi> Rev. 22. 18. Do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> conform unto this great Inſtitution? in words indeed they do ſo: <hi>But what meaneth the bleating of the ſheep, and lowing of the Oxen in our ears?</hi> Do they not own other Lords, Heads and Governors, that have a Law-making power, and would enforce the conſciences of the Free-born Subjects of Chriſt over his Churches, beſides him? What doth this leſs than evidently proclaim their diſobedience and rebellion (which is as the ſin of <hi>Witchcraft</hi>) againſt the <hi>KING</hi> of Kings, and their rejection of his Scepter and Soveraign Authority over them! But of this more hereafter.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. This great Prophet and King hath alſo revealed and proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>That 'tis his Will, that thoſe whom he hath called by his Word, ſhould ſeparate from the world, walk together in particular Societies and Churches, having given up themſelves to the Lord and one another according to the Will of God, for their mutual Edification and comfort in the Lord.</hi> The truth of this Soveraign Inſtitution of Chriſt, he that runs may reade in the Scriptures hereunto annexed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. and 5. 12. 2 <hi>Cor. 6. 17. Rev. 18. 4. John</hi> 15. 19. and 17. 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 40. and 19. 9. <hi>Phil. 1. 5. Act.</hi> 2. 41. and 17. 4. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 5. with many more. In the proof of this matter we might be copious, but that we ſtudy brevity: The diligent Reader knows where to find this <hi>theam,</hi> at large treated of by learned <hi>Ainſworth, Bartlet, Cotten, Rogers, &amp;c.</hi> How do the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> acquit themſelves, in reſpect of this Solemn Appointment of the Lord? alas! who ſees not that they are in their practice at open defiance herewith, have it in deriſion and contempt, making no difference betwixt the Holy and Prophane, admitting per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>led captive by the Devil</hi> at his will, that <hi>openly blaspheme the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>deride</hi> its effectual opperation in the conſciences of men, <hi>into</hi> their <hi>Society?</hi> Are any too vile (except ſuch as truly fear God, and deſire to preſs after Holineſs) to be admitted by them into their Communion? Is not their Church-State (ſo unlike is it to the Inſtitution of Chriſt) a very <hi>Babel,</hi> a Den of <hi>Dragons,</hi> and Hold of <hi>Unclean-Beaſts?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. That he hath entruſted them, ſo called and united together, with Power, and given them Rules for the due and right exerting thereof, for the carring on the Worſhip of his Houſe, to chuſe Officers over them to act in the Holy Things of God for and to them (of which more ſhall be ſpoken in its proper place) to admit Members, excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:43509:17"/> Offenders, &amp;c. all which we find ſhining forth in brightneſs in the enſuing Scriptures, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 23. and 6. 3, 5. and 14. 23. 2 <hi>Cor. 8. 19. Mat. 18. 17. 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 4. Do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> conform unto this Inſtitution of Chriſt? nothing leſs; is there any thing like this in the whole oeconomie invented and practiſed by them? do they not to the utmoſt of their power, labour to break this Bond of Chriſt aſunder, caſt away this Cord from them, by ſtirring up the Magiſtrate to perſecute by Fines, Impriſonments, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, &amp;c. the precious People of the Lord, that deſire to be found in the practice of this Law of Chriſt, branding them with the odious names of <hi>Phanaticks, Sectaries, Schiſmaticks, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Officers of his appointment are only ſuch as theſe, <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons, Widdows</hi> or <hi>Helpers:</hi> Who as they are in one particular Congregation, ſo they have not any Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or lordly Authority over each other, being all Brethren, <hi>Epheſ. 4. 11. Rom.</hi> 12. 7. and 16. 1. 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 28. Phil. 1. 1. 1 Pet. 5. 1, 2, 3. Acts</hi> 6. 5. and 15. 2. and 20. 17. and 28. 21, 28. 1 <hi>Tim. 3 chap.</hi> and 5. 9, 10, 17. This Law of Chriſt ſo clearly revealed in the Scripture, they are ſo far from ſubjecting to, that they have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the name nor thing required by him therein. Set up other Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Offices, as if in open contempt and defiance of his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; of which it may righteouſly be ſaid, <hi>He did at no time command them, neither did it ever enter into his heart, ſo to do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That theſe Officers be choſen by the common <hi>Suffrage</hi> of the Church of Chriſt, and ſolemnly ſet apart by Faſting and Prayer, this is evidently comprized in the enſuing Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 15. and 6. 1, 2, 3, 5. and 14. 23. and 1. 23, 26. and 9. 26, 27. In conformity whereunto, we find the Saints for many centuries of years after Chriſt, in the peaceable poſſeſſion of this their Priviledge and Right.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Clemens</hi> in his Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> p. 57. ſaith, <hi>Our Apoſtles alſo knew by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that contention will be about the name of</hi> Epiſcopal-Charge: <hi>Therefore for this reaſon, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a full predetermination, they conſtituted ſuch as were fore nominated, and in their inſtructive diſtribution delivered; that if they were negligent, other aproved men ſhould receive their miniſtration, being ordained by them, or in the mean time by other choice men, all the Church conſenting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</hi> Yea afterwards,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Let ſome one among you, Ingenious, Merciful, filled with Love, ſpeak, if
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:43509:18"/> through me Faction, and Contention, Schiſms, I will depart: Of which if you are willing, I return and will do the things appointed by the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi> Wherein he fully aſſerts the Priviledge of the Church or Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt we are pleading for. And afterwards, during the raign of Antichriſt, Chriſt hath not left himſelf without a Witneſs, nor his People without Champions to plead their Right in this matter. To inſtance but in a few: That lively Witneſs of Chriſt <hi>Martin Luther</hi> loudly proclaims, <hi>that the voice of the People ought not to be ſevered from the chuſing of Eccleſiaſtical perſons:</hi> And long before him, <hi>Cyprian</hi> (who lived about two hundred ſixty years after Chriſt) ſayes, <hi>Plebs obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens, &amp;c. The People that obey the commands of God, and fear him, ought to ſeparate themſelves from a wicked Paſtor, ſeeing the People them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves chiefly, have either power to chooſe Paſtors that are worthy, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe thoſe that be unworthy,</hi> Cypr. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 68. and tells us plainly, <hi>That this is bottom'd upon the Authority of God: That that is a juſt and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ordination which is tryed by the judgment and voice of all,</hi> viz. <hi>that fear and obey God.</hi> Of the ſame mind long after, was <hi>Francis Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard,</hi> the companion of <hi>Luther</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> in the Preface of his Book, entituled, <hi>The Sum of Chriſtianity,</hi> who ſayes, <hi>Verily every Pariſh ought to have his proper Biſhop, the which ſhould be choſen by the People, and confirmed by the Commonalty of every Pariſh, who if they ſwerve one jot or tittle from the Doctrine of the Gospel of the Kingdom, ought to be depoſed by the People; and others more fit, to be elected by them.</hi> And in chap. 5. of the ſaid Book, he profeſſes, <hi>That 'tis the moſt grievous crime, and by no means to be ſuffered, that many children of perdition do deprive the People of God of their juſt Right and Title,</hi> viz. <hi>to chuſe them a Paſtor. Peter Martyr</hi> in his common places, refers the chuſing and election of Miniſters to the People as their undoubted Right: To whom we may joyn Mr. <hi>Bullinger,</hi> who ſayes, <hi>That the Apoſtles exerciſed not Tyranny in the Church, in ordaining Miniſters without the conſent of the People.</hi> Bullin. Decad. 5. Serm. 4. Tit. 1. 1 Tim. 5. <hi>Gualter</hi> alſo upon <hi>Acts</hi> 1. 25. ſaith, <hi>That thoſe that profeſs the Gospel handle the matter as evil as the</hi> Monks <hi>and</hi> Popiſh Biſhops, <hi>in that they reſtore not again to the Church the liberty of chuſing Miniſters, which by Tyranny they took from them.</hi> Of the ſame mind is <hi>Zanchio, Calvin, Beza, Danaeus, Tilenus, Tyndall</hi> (the Martyr) with many others, as Mr. <hi>Fox, Cartwright,</hi> Mr. <hi>Jacob, &amp;c.</hi> We cannot omit the famous Caſe of the United Brethren of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> who concluding the whole Papacy to be purely Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43509:18"/> could not allow of the Ordination of their Miniſters by any in communion with it, and yet being perſwaded of a neceſſity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing that Ordinance in a way of ſucceſſion, ſend ſome to the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Armenian</hi> Churches; who returning with diſſatisfaction, they thereupon commit themſelves and their cauſe to God, and chuſe Elders from amongſt themſelves, and by Faſting and Prayer ſolemnly ſet them apart to the work of the Preaching of the Goſpel. To theſe many more might be added. The practice pleaded for (as is evident) is as antient as the dayes of the Apoſtles, and the firſt election of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary New-Teſtament Officers, continued in the Church till after the dayes of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> when Pride and Tyranny ſoon brought all things into horrible confuſion, upon the pretext of Decency and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; yet in the worſt of times have the Witneſſes of Chriſt born their Teſtimony hereunto. What ſay our Reverend Fathers and Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to theſe things? have they not an equal reſpect to this Appointment of Chriſt, as to thoſe before inſtanc'd in? is there any thing like it almoſt, practiſed by them, in this great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, of ſeparating perſons for the preaching of the Goſpel of Chriſt? is not the liberty of the <hi>Brethren</hi> and Churches of Chriſt, as much as lies in them, wholly diſannulled, and broken by them? have they any ſuch call to the Miniſtry? do they at all value or eſteem of it? are they in the practice of the Primitive Church, or of the Reformed Churches of this day, in this matter? is not the print of the feet of the old Strumpet of <hi>Rome,</hi> the bloudy Perſecutor of the Saints, the cunning Deviſor of a new ſelf-invented and whoriſh Worſhip, to be ſoley found in the paths, they are in this matter traverſing? and can ſuch be accounted as the ſubjects of the Kingdom of Chriſt, and the real owners of his Authority and Power? To theſe, many other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt may be added, which they ſubject not to. What, ſhould I mention</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That Royal Command of our Soveraign King and Lawgiver, (which the profound, ſelf-philoſophically wiſe, but indeed fooliſh and unlearned Doctors of this day, wreſt, to the countenancing of the diſorders and confuſion of Antichriſt (darkneſs ſo groſs that it may be felt) that <hi>all things be done decently and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 40. <hi>viz.</hi> that the Saints may propheſie one by one, and ought to admoniſh, exhort, and build up one another in their moſt holy Faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. &amp; 12. 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 17. &amp; 5. 4. &amp; 11. 23. <hi>Epheſ. 4. 7, 11, 12. 1 Tim.</hi> 2. 1.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:43509:19"/> &amp; 3. 15. <hi>Jude 20. 1 Cor. 12. 7, 11. Mat. 25. 24. 1 Pet. 4. 10, 11. 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 15. &amp; 14. 12, 24. <hi>Epheſ. 4. 3, 7, 15, 16. Act. 2. 42. Rom. 15. 14. Eph. 5. 19. Col. 3. 16. 1 Theſſ. 5. 14. 2 Theſſ. 3. 15. Heb.</hi> 3. 13. to which might be added the frequent examples of the Saints, in the Old and New-Teſtament, 2 <hi>Chron. 17. 7, 8, 9. Job 2. 11. Mal. 3. 16. Luke 4. 16. Act. 13. 15. 1 Cor. 14. 24 to</hi> 34. and the practice of the Primitive Church, as witneſs <hi>Origen</hi> (in his Epiſt. to <hi>Celſum.) Tertullian</hi> (in his Apology) <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> (in his Apology) and many others. Yea,</p>
                  <p n="7">7. What, ſhould I mention that grand Inſtitution of this Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord and Lawgiver, that nothing be offered up to the Father, but what is of his own preſcription (Divine and Spiritual, without affectation of Legal ſhadows, (<hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24.) of worldly pomp, or carnal excellency, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 12. &amp; 2. 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 12. &amp; 6. 13.) 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 28. Iſa. 33. 22. Jam. 4. 12. Mat. 15. 6, 9. Heb. 8. 5. 1 King.</hi> 13. 33. &amp; 12. 33. <hi>Jer. 7. 31. Numb. 15. 39. Deut.</hi> 12. 1, 4, 31. It's evident the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> conform not to the Orders and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Chriſt, as the great Prophet and Lawgiver to his People, hath appointed them to walk by; and therefore really diſown the Kingly and Prophetical Office of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But perhaps to theſe things, ſome may ſay; <hi>Theſe are but ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, good men differ amongst themſelves herein.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which we anſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That they are part of the Inſtituted Worſhip of God; the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders he hath left his Children to conform to, hath already been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: to ſay, that any part of the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt, <hi>is a ſmall matter,</hi> is no ſmall derogation to the Wiſdom of the Lawgiver that gave it forth.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What if it ſhould appear, that as <hi>ſmall</hi> as theſe things ſeem to be, they are the <hi>great Grounds</hi> of the late Controverſies of God, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Fire and Sword in moſt of the <hi>Europaean</hi> Kingdoms? this may perhaps a little ſtay ſober perſons from ſo raſh a concluſion, that theſe are <hi>ſmall matters:</hi> A ſerious review of the late Conteſts of God in the Nations, with the conſideration of the Grounds and Riſe of them, will to perſons of ſobriety, ſufficiently evince the truth of the Suggeſtion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As <hi>ſmall matters</hi> as theſe have been ſeverely puniſhed by the Lord: he is a jealous God, and ſtands upon <hi>Punctilio's</hi> (if I may ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:43509:19"/> call them) in his Worſhip; hence is that expreſſion, <hi>Ye cannot ſerve the Lord, for he is a jealous God,</hi> Joſh. 24. 19. What ſhould I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the caſe of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> 2 Chr. 26. 16. of <hi>Corah, Dathan</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram,</hi> Numb. 16. of <hi>Uzzah,</hi> whoſe ſin lay meerly in, whoſe judgment was ſingly upon this foot of account, his not ſeeking the Lord after the due order, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15. 13. God commands that when the Ark was removed, it ſhould be covered by the Prieſts, that no hand touch it, that it be carried upon mens ſhoulders, <hi>Numb.</hi> 4. 11, 15. which Order was violated, when they brought it from the houſe of <hi>Abina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab,</hi> 'twas Uncovered, and upon a Cart, after the manner of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> 1 Sam. 8. 7. for which breach of Order <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah</hi> is ſtruck dead.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. As <hi>ſmall matters</hi> as theſe, when once commanded by the Lord, are of that force, as not only to deface the wel-being, but to overturn the true-being of the Worſhip of God. Take one pregnant inſtance herein. The Lord commanded the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> by <hi>Moſes,</hi> to bring their Sacrifices to the place that he ſhould chuſe, and offer them there; which in it ſelf was but a circumſtance of place; yet all the Sacrifices offered elſewhere, were a ſtink in the noſtrils of God, and not accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by him as any Worſhip performed unto him.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. But the Objection is altogether impertinent; we are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating the greatneſs of the ſin, but the truth of what is charged upon the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England:</hi> what we have mentioned, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Appointments of Chriſt, or they are not; if they are, (as hath been proved) the preſent Miniſters conform to them, or they do not; if they do not (as nothing more ſure) they conform not to the Orders and Ordinances Chriſt hath left his People to walk by, (which is the thing in debate) and therefore really deny his Kingly and Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Office.</p>
                  <p>As for what is added, <hi>that good men differ amongst themſelves in this matter,</hi> it's of no more weight than what went before: for, 1. 'Tis not at all to the buſineſs in hand. 2. 'Tis poſſible good men may for a while do that which really enwraps in the bowels of it a denial of the Offices of Chriſt. We ſhall not deny but ſome of the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> may be ſo in the account of God. 3. That good men dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, is an Argument of their Ignorance and Darkneſs, which though in ſome caſes it excuſes <hi>a tanto,</hi> yet not <hi>a toto;</hi> it may alter the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, never the nature of the ſin. 4. 'Tis falſe, that good men preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43509:20"/> after Reformation, and the reſtitution of the Worſhip of God according to the Primitive Pattern, do differ touching the ſubſtance of the things inſtanc'd in: Were but the pride and paſſion of mens ſpirits a little more allaied; and they diſentangled more from their ſelfiſh intereſts, a greater harmony would appear amongſt them in theſe matters. But 5ly, as was ſaid, The particulars inſtanc'd in, are commanded by Chriſt, or they are not; if they are (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) doth it in the leaſt diſcharge perſons that conform not to them, from the charge they are impleded as guilty, <hi>viz.</hi> Non-conformity to the Laws of Chriſt; that good men differ in theſe matters (<hi>i. e.</hi> ſome good men tranſgreſs the Laws of Chriſt, which is ſure no part of their goodneſs, nor any warrant to juſtifie me, in the doing of what may ſtrengthen their hands in ſuch a Non-conformity)</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſecond Argument demonſtrating, that the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> deny the Prophetical and Kingly Office of Chriſt. That they own, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit and ſubſcribe to Orders and Ordinances that are not of Chriſt's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealing, proved by the induction of 14 Particulars. An Objection anſwered. That they own Laws and Inſtitutions, contrary to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt, proved, by the induction of 10 Particulars. A 3d Argument, proving their denial of the Offices of Chriſt, produced. That there is no other Head of the Church but Chriſt, proved. Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> deny the Kingly and Prophetical Offices of Chriſt, and therefore are not to be heard, but ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from, hath been aſſerted, and by one Argument, proved, in the foregoing Chapter: To the further evidence whereof, a few things more are to be offered in this.</p>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 2.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who own, ſubmit and ſubſcribe to Orders and Ordinances which not only, are not of Chriſt's revealing, but contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, do really deny, and oppoſe the Prophetical and Kingly Office of Chriſt. But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do own, ſubmit and ſubſcribe to Orders and Ordinances, that are not only, not of Chriſt's revealing, but contrary thereunto: Therefore.</p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:43509:20"/>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) is beyond exception: If an own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſubmitting and ſubſcribing to Orders, and Ordinances, that are not onely, not of Chriſt's revealing, but contrary thereunto, be not a denial of his Kingly and Prophetical Office, I muſt profeſs, I know not what is. Suppoſe the Chief Magiſtrate or Magiſtrates of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould give forth a Declaration of their will, touching this, or that other concern, were not perſons Non-conformity thereunto (ſuppoſing it to be what lies within the verge of their Authority, and power to command, and may righteouſly be exacted of them, whoſe Conformity is thereunto required) a ſilent oppoſition of their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but ſhould any preſume to give forth Laws of their own, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt ſtamp of Authority upon them, yea contrary unto the Statutes and Declarations of their Governours, would not all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that theſe perſons and their Abettors were guilty of Rebellion againſt their Rulers, and did really deny the lawfulneſs of their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? This is the preſent caſe, if men ſhall be found traverſing paths, in the poſſeſſion and practice of Orders and Conſtitutions that are forreign to the Edicts of Chriſt, yea contrary thereunto, ſhall we not as rationally conclude that theſe perſons are really oppoſers of his Soveraign Authority and Government? doubtleſs ſo!</p>
                  <p>'Tis the <hi>minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) that may be under ſuſpition amongſt ſome, <hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> (the very beſt of them) do own, ſubmit and ſubſcribe to Orders and Ordinances, that are not only, not of Chriſts revealing, but contrary thereunto: In which two things are incumbent upon us to prove.</p>
                  <p>1. That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do own, ſubmit and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to Orders and Ordinances, that are not of Chriſt's revealing. This being a charge, as to matter of Fact, the production of a few Particulars, that lie near at hand, for its confirmation, will give it a ſpeedy diſpatch.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. They own, ſubmit and ſubſcribe to the Orders and Offices, of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Arch-Deacons,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. Canons Can. 7.</note> with many others appertaining unto this <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> as Orders needful and neceſſary in the Church of Chriſt, and promiſe ſubjection and obedience unto them.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. They own, and ſubmit (<hi>Can.</hi> 4.) to a Lyturgy, or Preſcript form of Worſhip, deviſed by men, and impoſed ſolely by their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, to which they tie themſelves, neither diminiſhing, nor ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:43509:21"/> any thing in the matter or form thereof.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. They own, ſubmit, &amp; engage to conform to all the Orders, Rites and Ceremonies preſcribed in the ſaid Book of <hi>Common-Prayer, (Can.</hi> 36.) ſuch as <hi>bowing at the Name of JESUS,</hi> uſing <hi>the Croſs in Baptiſm, kneeling at the Lords Supper</hi> (which though we do not, ſome would ſay, <hi>ſmells very ſtrong of the Popiſh Leven, and is but one peg beneath the adoration of their Breaden-god) wearing the Surplice, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. They own <hi>that the Office of a Deacon is the firſt ſtep or degree to the Miniſtry</hi> (Can. 32. 36.) <hi>to which they are to ſubmit and ſubſcribe, before they are made Priests.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. That <hi>no perſon be admitted to expound the Scripture, though judged worthy of the Cure of Souls</hi> (as they ſpeak, Can. 49.) <hi>without Licenſe from the Biſhop thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>That there be ſome lawful Ministers, which are no Preachers,</hi> (Can. 49. 57.)</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>That theſe unpreaching Ministers</hi> (Can. 57.) <hi>may lawfully admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Ordinances of Baptiſme and the Lord's Supper.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>That perſons refuſing to have their Children Baptiſed,</hi> by ſuch dumb Miniſters, <hi>or receive the Communion from them, worthily deſerve Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication if they ſhall perſist herein</hi> (Can. 57.)</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>That Confirmation by Dioceſan Biſhops, is an Ordinance of God.</hi> (Can. 60.)</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>That it appertains to the Office of Ministers to Marry.</hi> (Can. 62.)</p>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>That the Biſhop of the Dioceſs may lawfully for a while, ſuspend a Minister from his Ministry, for refuſing to Bury the Dead.</hi> Can. 68.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>That 'tis not lawful for Ministers to preach or administer the Communion in private houſes, except in times of neceſſity.</hi> Can. 71.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. <hi>That no Miniſter may lawfully appoint or keep any ſolemn private Faſts, or be wittingly preſent at any of them, nor hold any meetings for Sermons, in market Towns or other places; which if he do, and perſevere therein, he may lawfully be depoſed from his Miniſtry.</hi> (Can. 72.)</p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>That Miniſters ought to be diſtinguiſhed by their Veſtments and Apparel, as Gowns, Hoods, Tippets, Square-Caps, and in their journeys, Cloaks with ſleeves (called<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Prieſts Cloaks. Can. 74.) with many more that might be added, to which the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe, and own as agreeable to the Word of God, before their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Miniſtry according to the 38th <hi>Canon Eccleaſiastical.</hi> Are any of theſe Ordinances and Conſtitutions of the appointment of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:43509:21"/> Chriſt? when, or where were they inſtituted by him? that theſe are poſts ſet by the Lord's poſts, and threſholds by his threſholds, (of which the Lord complains, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 43. 8.) who ſees not? That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do conform and ſubſcribe hereunto, cannot be denied, and thence an owning ſubſcribing and ſubmitting to Orders and Conſtitutions that are not of Chriſts appointment, is evidently evinced.</p>
                  <p>Object. If it be ſaid, <hi>That though theſe Canons, and Conſtitutions owned by the Miniſters of</hi> England, <hi>be not <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, to be found in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Inſtitution of Chriſt in ſo many words, yet by conſequence they may rationally be deduced from thence: As where it is commanded,</hi> That all things be done decently and in order, 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 40. which 'tis the duty of the Church to make Rules and Conſtitutions about, which when it hath done, it is the duty of every Son thereof, to own, or ſubject to, without queſtioning its Authority.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſ.</hi> That there is any thing of moment in this Objection, though their <hi>Achilles</hi> in this matter, and that which they are upon every turn producing, is eaſily demonſtrated. The whole of it being built upon as uncertain principles, yea upon as notoriouſly falſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as ever objection in ſo weighty a caſe was built upon.</p>
                  <p>1. 'Tis ſuppoſed, that Chriſt hath not determined in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, how the Affairs of his Houſe ſhould be managed with decency and order, as well as commanded that they be ſo; which is, 1. No ſmall derogation to the perfection of the Scriptures. 2. To the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Faithfulneſs of Chriſt, debaſing of him herein, below <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> though the Scripture in this reſpect prefers him before him. 3. Diametrically oppoſite to the Scripture inſtanc'd in, which ſtands as a two-edged Sword to cut the throat of their cauſe, in its ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches thereto for ſhelter: Of which take this brief account; The Apoſtle having in the beginning of the chapter, preſt the Church of <hi>Corinth, to follow after Spiritual Gifts, but especially that they might prophecy;</hi> the liberty of the Saints therein being fully aſſerted, and ſeveral directions thereabout given, he condemns their diſorderly practiſe, in reſpect of this important Duty and Priviledge, <hi>ver.</hi> 26. and gives direction touching its regular performance; and this he doth, firſt, generally, <hi>ver. 26. Let all things be done to edifying,</hi> which with a little alteration he re-preſſes, <hi>ver. 40. Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> Secondly, Particularly, by telling them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43509:22"/> how they ought to manage this affair, in a way of <hi>Decency, Order</hi> and <hi>Edification;</hi> wherein ſeveral Rules are comprized, too long to be here inſiſted on, as in caſes of <hi>ſpeaking in an unknown Tongue,</hi> ver. 27, 28. of <hi>propheſying by two or three,</hi> ver. 29, 30. of the <hi>duties of Women</hi> with reſpect thereunto, ver. 34, 35. that from hence a power inveſted in the Church for the binding of the conſciences of men, touching ceremonies in Worſhip, ſhould be regularly deduced, is the firſt-born of improbabilities and abſurdities. 1. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking by an infallible Spirit of Prophecy, adviſes the Church of <hi>Corinth, that all things be done decently and in order;</hi> therefore perſons that have not, pretend not to ſuch a Spirit, may of their own heads bind our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences by Laws and Rules of their own in the ſervice of God. 2. <hi>Paul</hi> doth not onely tell them, <hi>that all things ought to be done decently and in order,</hi> but diſcovers to them, <hi>wherein that Decency and Order lies;</hi> therefore the Church hath power to determine in this matter, are ſuch <hi>Non-ſequiturs</hi> as will not in haſt be made good. But let this be granted, ſuppoſe that 'tis the priviledge and duty of the Church to make Laws and Conſtitutions, for the binding of the conſciences of men in matters of Decency and Order; this Church herein is bounded by the Scripture, or it is not: If it be <note n="†" place="margin">Learned <hi>Maccovius in loc. com. cap. 83. p.</hi> 851. ſayes, <hi>Leges ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quas judicare debent recto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Eccleſiae ſunt leges in verbo Dei praeſcriptae.</hi> The Laws he tells you by which the Governours of the Church are to judge, are ſuch as are preſcribed in the Word of GOD.</note> bounded by the Scripture, then when it hath no preſcription therein, for its com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, its not to be obeyed, and ſo we are where we were before, that Decency and Order is to be determined by the Scripture: If it be not bounded therby, then what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Ceremonies it introduceth, not directly contrary thereunto, they muſt be ſubjected to; which how fair an inlet it is to the whole <hi>Farago</hi> of <hi>Popiſh Inventions,</hi> who ſees not? yet were this alſo yielded them, they were never a jot nearer the mark aimed at, except it can be proved, that ſuppoſing a power of introducing Ceremonies to be inveſted in the Church, thence a power for the inſtitution of new Orders and Ordinances, the introducing of <hi>Heatheniſh, Jewiſh</hi> and ſuperſtitious practices in the Worſhip of God, may be evinced: And yet ſhould all this be yeelded them, none of which will they be able to prove to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43509:22"/> the worlds end; how will they manifeſt, thoſe Lordly Commands and Conſtitutions are the Conſtitutions of a truly-conſtituted Church of Chriſt, (a ſtrong ſuppoſition hereof is the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of the preſent Objection:) and yet fail they in the making good their ground herein: who ſees not that their plea hitherto impleaded, ſinks of it ſelf? what is it then they mean by the Church, whoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, we are without diſputing to ſubject to? is it the National Church of <hi>England?</hi> But where find they any National-Church of the inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt, in the Oeconomie of the Goſpel? how prove they that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is ſo? Yet ſhould this alſo be granted, where are the Conſtitutions and Laws of this Church, that we may pay the homage to them as is meet? when was it aſſembled <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> in the ſame place together, in its ſeveral Members freely to debate, (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 20. &amp; 14. 23.) and <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Maccovius in loc. com. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend. de Adi. p.</hi> 861. ſayes, <hi>Conditio tertia quae requiritur in adiaphoris eſt haec, quod haec non debeant introduci in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam, niſi communi conſenſu Eccleſiae,</hi> Acts 15. <hi>Things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different,</hi> he tells you, <hi>ought not to be introduced into the Church, but by the common conſent thereof, according to</hi> Acts 15.</note> determine what Laws and Conſtitutions were fit to be obſerved by them? If it be ſaid, That this is not requiſit, it is enough that it be aſſembled in its ſeveral Officers, or ſuch as ſhall be choſen by their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, whoſe Laws every Member is bound to be obedient to. We anſwer, But theſe Officers are the Church, or they are not; if they are not (as there is nothing more ſure) I owe no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to their Laws or Conſtitutions, it being pleaded that 'tis the Church that hath only power in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: if they are the Church, let them by one Scripture prove they are ſo; or, where the true Officers of a true Church are ſo called, and as <hi>Nonius</hi> ſaith out of <hi>Naevius</hi> to them, <q>—<hi>Dum vivebo fidelis ero.</hi>
                     </q> Yet except this alſo be yeelded them, there is nothing of moment in the Objection produced: It remaineth therefore that the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England,</hi> ſubmit, own, and ſubſcribe to, Laws and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, that are not, in any ſenſe, of Chriſt's revealing, and therefore oppoſe the Kingly &amp; Prophetical Office of Chriſt. But this is not all.</p>
                  <p>2dly. The preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do own, ſubmit, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to Laws, Conſtitutions and Ordinances, that are contrary to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:43509:23"/> the Revelation of Chriſt, whence an oppoſition to the Kingly and Prophetical Office of Chriſt may rationally be concluded: This al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo by the induction of a few particular inſtances, will be evinced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond exception.</p>
                  <p>They own and acknowledge,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there may be other Arch-Biſhops, and Lord-Biſhops in the Church of Chriſt, beſides himſelf: which is contrary to 1 <hi>Pet. 5. 3. 1 Cor. 12. 5. Eph. 4. 5. Heb. 3. 1. Luk.</hi> 22. 25, 26.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That men may, and ought to be made Miniſters, only by theſe Lord-Biſhops: which is contrary to <hi>Heb. 5. 4. Joh.</hi> 10. 1, 7. &amp; 13. 20. &amp; 14. 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 23. with 6. 3, 5.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That Prelates, their Chancellors and Officers, have power from Chriſt to caſt out of the Church of God; contrary to <hi>Mat. 18. 16, 17. 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That the Office of Suffragans, Deans, Canons, Petty-Canons, Prebendaries, Queriſters, Organiſts, Arch-deacons, Commiſſaries, Officials, Parſons, Vicars and Curats, are lawful and neceſſary to be had in the Church: evidently contrary to 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 18, 28. Rom. 12. 7. Eph.</hi> 4. 11. The Officers inſtituted by Chriſt are ſufficient for the edification and perfecting of the Saints, till they all come unto a perfect man, unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt, <hi>ver.</hi> 12, 13. in what ſenſe the fore-mentioned, being not one of them of the inſtitution of Chriſt, may be owned as lawful or neceſſary, without an high contempt of the Wiſdom and Soveraignty of Chriſt, cannot by ſuch dull perſons, as my ſelf, be conjectured. That any others ſee them any way uſeful to the Church of Chriſt, may be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to ſuch a ſharp-ſightedneſs as was that of <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> to whom, when he enquired of <hi>Vitellius,</hi> whether he ſaw him not imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Moon? 'twas anſwered,</p>
                  <q>Solis (Domine) vobis Diis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> licet ſe invicem videre.</q>
                  <p n="5">5. That the Office of Deacons in the Church, is to be imployed in publick Praying, Adminiſtration of Baptiſm, and Preaching, if licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Biſhop thereunto. Contrary to <hi>Act. 6. 2. Eph.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That the Ordinance of <hi>Breaking-Bread,</hi> or the <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> may be adminiſtred to one alone; as to a ſick-man ready to dye: which is diametrically oppoſit to the nature and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of that Ordinance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 16. &amp; 11. 33. <hi>Mat. 26. 26. Act.</hi> 2. 42. &amp; 20. 7.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:43509:23"/>7. That a preſcript form of words in Prayer, a ceremonious, pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous Worſhip, deviſed by Man, and abuſed to Idolatry, is according to the will of God, and may lawfully be uſed under the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-diſpenſation; contrary to <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 9. &amp; 28. 20. <hi>John 4. 23. Deut. 12. 32. Jer. 51. 26. Rom. 8. 26. 1 Cor.</hi> 14. 15.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. That wicked and ungodly perſons, and their Seed, are lawfull Members of the Church, and if they conſent not willingly to be ſo, they may be compell'd thereunto: contrary to <hi>Pſal. 110. 3. Act.</hi> 2. 40, 41, 47. &amp; 19. 9. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14, 17. &amp; 9. 13.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. That Women may adminiſter the <hi>Sacrament of Baptiſm:</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 34. 1 Tim. 2. 12. Matth. 28. 18, 19, 20. Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>That the Lord's Supper is to be received kneeling,</hi> which is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly oppoſit to the practice of Chriſt, in the firſt inſtitution thereof, <hi>Mark</hi> 14. 18, 22, 23. and poſitive precept, as being what hath an appearance of evil in it (being a geſture uſed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the adoration of their <hi>Breaden-god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>) 1 Theſ. 5. 22. as alſo to the practiſe of the Churches of Chriſt for ſeveral hundred years after, to the time of the invention and introduction of the Popiſh <hi>Breaden-god.</hi> Not to mention its contrariety to the judgment and practiſe of moſt of the reformed Churches (if not all) at this day. What ſhould I mention the Conſtitutions and Canons before pointed to, wherein 'tis for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to any to preach, not licenſed by the Biſhops thereunto, to Marry, or eat Fleſh at certain times, with many more of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; all directly contrary to the Soveraign Edicts of Chriſt, and ſome of them evident characters of the laſt dayes Apoſtates, 1 <hi>Tim. 4. 3. from whom</hi> Saints are warned by the Lord, <hi>to turn aſide,</hi> ver. 5. Theſe we have produced, carry an undeniable evidence with them, that the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do own, ſubmit and ſubſcribe to Orders and Ordinances, that are contrary to the revelation of Chriſt, and therefore deny his Propheticall and Kingly Office. To all that hath hitherto been offered in this matter, we ſhall yet adde, as a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther demonſtration of the truth we are in the diſquiſition of,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument. 3.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that acknowledge another Head over the Church beſide Chriſt, deny his Prophetical and Kingly Office: but the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>England</hi> do own and acknowledge another Head over the Church beſide Chriſt: Therefore.</p>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:43509:24"/>
                  <p>If the aſſertion of another King in <hi>England,</hi> that as the Head there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, hath power of making and giving forth Laws to the free-born ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects therein, be a denyal of his Kingly Authority (as no doubt it is) the <hi>major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) cannot be denied. If Chriſt be the alone King of his Church (as ſuch) he is its alone Head &amp; Lawgiver: If he hath not by any Statute-Law eſtabliſhed, any other Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in and over his Church, to act in the holy things of God, from and under him, beſides himſelf; who ſees not the aſſertion of ſuch an Headſhip, carries with it a contempt and denial of his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? if there be any ſuch Headſhip of the inſtitution of Chriſt, let us know when and where it was inſtituted; whether ſuch a Dominion and Soveraignty over the Subjects of his Kingdom, with reſpect to Worſhip, be granted by them to any of the Sons of men, abſolutely, or conditionally: if the firſt, then muſt the Church (it ſeems) be governed by perſons, caſting off the Yoak of Chriſt, trampling upon his Royal Commands and Edicts: for ſo it's poſſible, it may fall out thoſe that attain this Headſhip may do; as it's evident many Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> (the great Pretenders hereunto) have done. If the ſecond, let one <hi>iota</hi> be produced from the Scripture, of the inſtitution of ſuch an Headſhip, with the conditions annexed thereunto, and we ſhall be ſo far from denying of it, that we ſhall chearfully pay, whatever reſpect, homage, or duty by the Laws of God or man, may righteouſly be expected from us. But this will not, we humbly conceive, in haſt be performed; and that becauſe,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Scripture makes mention of no other Head, in, and over the Church, but Chriſt, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 22. &amp; 5. 23, 29. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If there be any other Head, he muſt be either within, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Church: The latter will not be affirmed; Chriſt had not ſure ſo little reſpect unto his Flock, as to appoint Wolves and Lions to be their Governours and Guides in matters Eccleſiaſtical, nor can the former; for all in the Church, are Brethren, have no dominion or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over each others Faith or Conſcience, <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 25.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If any other be Head of the Church but Chriſt, then is the Church the Body of ſome others, beſides Chriſt; but this is abſurd, and falſe, not to ſay impious and blaſphemous.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There was no Head of the Church in the Apoſtles dayes, but Chriſt.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. If any be Head of the Church beſide Chriſt, they either have
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:43509:24"/> their Headſhip, from an original right ſeated in themſelves, or by donation from Chriſt. To aſſert the firſt, were no leſs than blaſphemy; if the ſecond, let them ſhew, when, and where, and how they came to be inveſted in ſuch a right, and this controverſie will be at an end.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. He that is aſſerted in Scripture to be the Head of the Church, is ſaid to govern, feed, and nouriſh it to Eternal life; is her Spouſe and Husband, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 2. In which ſenſe, none of the ſons of men, one or other, can be the Head thereof; and yet of any other Head, the Scripture is wholly ſilent. But of this matter thus far. It cannot by any ſober perſon be denied, but an owning of a viſible Head over the Church, having power of making and giving forth Laws, with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to Worſhip, (ſuch an Headſhip not being of the Inſtitution of Chriſt) muſt needs be a denial of his Soveraign Authority and Power. That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do own and ſubmit to ſuch an Headſhip, is undeniable: witneſs their Subſcription, Oath, Conformity in Worſhip, to Laws and Edicts, made and given forth by the ſons of men, as Heads and Governours of the Church; which are not onely forraign to, but (as hath been already demonſtrated) lift up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in oppoſition againſt the Royal Inſtitutions of Chriſt. This being matter of fact, the Individuals charged herewith, muſt either acquit themſelves, by a denial of what they are impleaded as guilty, or prove that what they do, is not criminous, but lawful to be done. The former being too notoriouſly known to admit of a denial: 'tis the latter muſt be inſiſted on: what is therein offered, is nextly to be conſidered. This is that ſome ſay,</p>
                  <p>Obj. 1. <hi>That they acknowledge another Head beſides Chriſt, cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed be denied: but the Headſhip owned and acknowledged by them, is an Headſhip only under Chriſt.</hi> To which we anſwer:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. But this Headſhip is either of Chriſt's Appointment, or 'tis not; if it be, let it be ſhewn where it was inſtituted by him, and (as we ſaid) this controverſie is at an end: if it be not, the Aſſertion of ſuch an Headſhip, even in ſubordination to Chriſt over his Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches as ſuch, hinders not but perſons owning, ſubmitting thereunto, are guilty of denying the Kingly Office of Chriſt. 2. The Headſhip pleaded for by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no other. 3. 'Tis not ſo as is pretended, they own an Headſhip that is not in all things ſubordinate to Chriſt, having a Law-making and Law-giving Power touching Inſtitutions of Worſhip, that never came into his heart, are flatly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43509:25"/> againſt his Appointments, as hath been proved. 4. One Head in ſubordination to another, doth as really make the Body a Monſter, as two heads conjoyned. If it be ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Obj. 2. <hi>That the Kings of Iſrael were the Heads, ſucceſſively, of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> then Church; and therefore a viſible Headſhip over the Churches of Chriſt, in the New-Teſtament is lawful.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We anſwer, 1. That betwixt the Oeconomy of the Law and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, there is a vaſt diſproportion; many things were lawful in that day, which to do, or ſubject to now, were no leſs than a denial of Chriſt come in the fleſh. 2. The Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were Types of Chriſt. 3. That the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were Heads of the Church, is falſe. God was its alone Head and King. Hence their Hiſtorian ſaith, their Government was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and when they would needs chooſe a King God ſaid, <hi>they rejected him,</hi> to whom even, as to their Political Head, a Sicle was paid yearly as a Tribute, called, <hi>The Sicle of the Sanctuary.</hi> True indeed, as they were a Political Body, they had viſible Political Governours, who when they ceaſed, their Polity was at an end; but that theſe had any Headſhip over them, to make any Laws, introduce Conſtitutions of their own fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in matters relating to Worſhip, will never be proved.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A fifth Argument againſt hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> advanced. That they have the characters of falſe Prophets upon them, manifeſted in 15 Particulars.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 5.</head>
                  <p>THoſe who have the characters and properties of <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> upon them, are not to be heard, but ſeparated from: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have the characters and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of falſe Prophets and Prieſts upon them. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) ſtands upon too firm a <hi>baſis,</hi> to be quickly removed: nor will any attempt ſo to do, Chriſt having charged his to beware of ſuch, <hi>Mat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 7. 15. to take heed that none deceive them, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 4, 5, 23, 24, 25. not to believe every ſpirit, but to try the ſpirits, becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out in the world, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 1. not to receive ſuch into their houſes, 2 <hi>John</hi> 10, 11. to watch againſt them, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 29, 30, 31. with much more that might be ſaid (if needful) for its confirmation, is a ſufficient evidence
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:43509:25"/> of the truth thereof. But herein the parties litigant are at a perfect agreement.</p>
                  <p>'Tis the <hi>minor</hi> Propoſition that is iudged by ſome to come ſhort of a ſufficient ſubſtraction, <hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have the properties and characters of falſe Prophets and Prieſts upon them. This we doubt not, by a ſerious obſervation of the characters are given of ſuch in the Scriptures by the Holy-Ghoſt, will to any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary underſtanding be made exceeding perſpicuous and evident. The ſignal Characters of whom are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>That they run before they are ſent,</hi> Jer. 23. 21. That a Miſſion from the Lord is of the eſſence of a lawful Miniſtry, that whoever wants ſuch a Miſſion, is no Officer of Chriſt, but a falſe Prophet, and Miniſter of Antichriſt, may hence rationally, at leaſt by way of analo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, be deduced, is evident. Which alſo exactly accords with what is aſſerted by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 15. That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> want ſuch a Miſſion, hath already been demonſtrated, and we ſhall not <hi>actum agere.</hi> In a word, when it ſhall be proved, that they have received their Authority from Chriſt, either immediatly or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly, from any rightly conſtituted Church of Chriſt, or by ſucceſſion from the Church in the Wilderneſs, we ſhall acknowledge them to be the Miniſters of Chriſt, and look upon our ſelves as obliged to pay them all the honour and duty, that as ſuch, we are charged in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to do: But if they have nothing elſe to plead for themſelves but what is uſually inſtanced in by them, a ſucceſſion from the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> That Apoſtate Church having loſt her Churchſhip, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, all lawful power for the ſending forth Officers into the Churches of Chriſt, we ſhall not fear to ſay, That they are ſuch as are characte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized here by the Prophet, perſons that run before they are ſent.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>That they commit Adultery and walk in Lies,</hi> Jer. 23. 14. Which none as I ever yet met with, interpret literally of corporal Whoredome and Adultery, but myſtically of ſpirituall Adultery, a departure from the pure Wayes and Inſtitutions of the Lord in Worſhip, to the <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>In an old Tranſlation of the New-Teſtament, dedicated to</hi> Edward <hi>the 6th, the Author thereof in his Notes on</hi> Mat. 21. <hi>ſays, They which in their Miniſtry and Preaching do otherwiſe than God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, are no true Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </note> Devices &amp; Inventions of men (a ſin uſually in the Scripture expreſſed, for the nature and greatneſs of it, under that notion, <hi>Jer. 3. 8. Ezek. 23. 37. Rev.</hi> 2. 22. which is alſo in
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43509:26"/> Scripture called a <hi>Lye, Iſa. 28. 15. Amos 2. 4. John</hi> 8. 44. The whole Worſhip of Antichriſt being patch'd up with ſuch dirty Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is ſo called, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 11.) That this character alſo doth rightly appertain unto the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> the beſt of whom, do in the ſence of the Spirit, in the forecited Scripture, commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and walk in lies, hath already been proved (and more hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhall afterwards be ſpoken) ['twere well if upon ſome of them it had not a literal accompliſhment] which of the Inſtitutions of Chriſt have they not mixed with their inventions? From how many have they gone a whoring? Is not a great part of their Worſhip drops of the Whores <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Fornication,</hi> and ſhreds of the great lye of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt? who that hath ſoberly and unbiaſſedly conſidered of theſe things, but muſt acknowledge it?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>That they ſtrengthen the hands of evil-doers, that none doth return from his wickedneſs,</hi> Jer. 23. 14. That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> really do ſo, is capable of an ocular demonſtration: perhaps they do in their Sermons reprove ſin, thunder out the Judgments of God againſt tranſgreſſors of his Law, as much as any; but alas! what is this, to condemn them in the ſtate wherein they ſtand, without-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to the pit of Hell in the Pulpit; and by and by to <hi>Saint</hi> them in the Chancel, and tell them there, without exception, that the Body of Chriſt was broken for them, his Blood ſhed for them? Oh how many millions of ſouls are and have been hereby hardened to their own undoing, and had their hands ſtrengthened in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs? what ſhould I mention their admiſſion of the Children of all to Baptiſm, without exception, their owning them as Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, yea, die they never ſo wickedly, as Brethren, of whoſe <hi>joyful Reſurrection</hi> they profeſs they have <hi>a ſure and certain hope;</hi> thereby proclaiming their undoubted perſwaſion, that they are a People in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God? not to take notice of the terrible reflections, and uncharitable cenſures are publickly by them paſt upon men truly fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, becauſe they cannot conform to them: How deſperately are the hands of the wicked hereby ſtrengthned? So that none indeed doth return from his wickedneſs: How rare a thing is it to hear of one ſoul that is brought over to God by all their preaching? ſo that viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly that Judgment of God ſeems to be upon them, <hi>ver. 32. therefore they ſhall not at all profit this People.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>That they propheſie</hi> placentia, <hi>ſmooth things, according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:43509:26"/> tempers and luſts of men, to the pleaſing of whom they addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> Jer. 6. 14. and 27. 9. Ezek. 13. 10, 11. and 22. 28. What viſible lineaments of ſuch a frame of ſpirit, are drawn upon the faces of that Generation of men, concerning whom we are now diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing? Have they not been of all others (I am now ſpeaking of ſuch as are look'd upon by Profeſſors, as men of the greateſt parts and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs) the moſt ready to ſtrike in with, preach up, and plead for what was moſt ſuitable unto the ſpirits of ſuch, upon whom they have had a dependance: 'Twere indeed well for them, could they in their preſent ſtanding and practiſe acquit themſelves from that ſore crime, of <hi>ſeeking to pleaſe men,</hi> which if they do, they cannot be the Servants of Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. 10.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. <hi>That they are greedy Dogs, that can never have enough, and look every man for</hi>
                     <note place="margin">In a Tranſlation of the N. T. dedicated to <hi>Edw.</hi> 6th the Authour of the Notes on chap. 10. ſayes, <hi>We muſt preach the Truth with out any respect of reward or gaines. They therefore that preach for their bellies ſake or preach after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of man—are not the Diſciples of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>his gain from his quarter,</hi> Iſa. 56. 11. <hi>ſeeking and ſerving themſelves in their Miniſtration</hi> Ezek. 13. 19. Mich. 3. 5, 11. That herein there is a perfect harmony betwixt theſe <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> and the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> cannot be denied: What means elſe their frequent <hi>Calls,</hi> from places of leſs, to places of greater value; their ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and greedy deſires after preferment; the vexations they put poor men to, that cannot in conſcience put into their mouths, preparing War againſt them?</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>That they ſadden the hearts of the Righteous,</hi> Ezek. 13. 22: What need I turn aſide to make application of this to the Prophets of this day? who that is ſerious, doth not experiment the truth thereof in his own ſoul? to ſee the Name and Ordinances of God prophaned, the Ceremonies and Inventions of man ſubjected unto, by ſuch as pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be Miniſters of Chriſt, would make an heart of ſtone to bleed; much more thoſe whoſe hearts are made tender by the Lord. Thoſe of our Brethren that as yet attend upon their Miniſtry, will tell us, <hi>they are troubled at their Compliance and Conformity</hi>—all that look in the leaſt after Reformation, ſay, <hi>they could wiſh it were otherwiſe;</hi> ſo that this character alſo is viſibly upon them.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:43509:27"/>7. <hi>That they mix the Word of God with their</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Notes on</hi> Matth. 28. <hi>in the foreſaid Tranſlation are, Here do all Preachers learn what they ſhould teach; nothing elſe but God's Word; nothing elſe but that the Lord hath commanded them: Not their own Dreams and Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Dreams,</hi> Jer. 23. 25, 29. So do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> as hath been proved.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>That they come in Sheeps cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, having the horns of a Lamb, but are inwardly ravening Wolves, and ſpeak like Dragons</hi> (i. e. pretend to the <hi>Holineſs</hi> and <hi>Meekneſs</hi> of Chriſt, and Saints, but are inwardly full of <hi>Raven</hi> and <hi>Cruelty,</hi> yea terrible in their <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Laws,</hi> ſtirring up &amp; making uſe of the Powers of the world, to perſecute, kill &amp; deſtroy the Saints) <hi>Mat. 7. 15. Rev.</hi> 13. 11. (which <hi>ſecond Beaſt</hi> is no other than the <hi>falſe Prophet,</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 20. as might eaſily be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated) As face anſwers face in a Glaſs, ſo do the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> the <hi>Falſe Prophets</hi> there ſpoken of. Are not all the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, Impriſonments, Slaughters and Butcheries of the Children of God, that the <hi>firſt Beaſt</hi> hath exerciſed upon the Saints for this 1260 years, to be charged upon this Generation of men? yea, who do more eagerly preſs a rigid Conformity (not only contrary to the Kings Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> and others ſince publiſhed by him, but alſo (as is thought) to his natural temper, and the inclination and bent of his ſpirit) though to the infringing of the Liberty, the Baniſhment, the taking away of the Lives of the Saints, who love Truth and Peace, and humbly beg, <hi>That they may be ſuffered for the Tribute they pay</hi> (as in the Dominion of the <hi>Grand Seignior</hi> they are) <hi>in quietneſs to ſerve God according to their perſwaſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>That they put no difference betwixt the Holy and Prophane,</hi> Ezek. 22. 26. Do not even the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> the ſame? Are not <hi>All</hi> their <hi>dear Brethren and Siſters,</hi> living and dead, though Drunkards, Swearers, Adulterers and Adultereſſes? &amp;c. Are not, as was ſaid, the Children of them all admitted to the Font, and they themſelves to the Lord's Table? Is not the Childrens meat frequently given by them unto Dogs, and the holy Ordinances proſtituted to be polluted by the worſt of men?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. <hi>That they exerciſe not pity to the weak broken ſcattered Sheep of Chriſt, nor ſhew bowels in their recovery, but with Force and Cruelty rule over them,</hi> Ezek. 34. 4. One would think the former part of the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:43509:27"/> chapter, were rather an Hiſtory of what is practiſed by the falſe Shepherds of this day, than otherwiſe: ſo perfect an Agreement is there betwixt their practice, and this Prophecy of the Lord. They tell us 'tis our weakneſs and diſtemper that we conform not to their Worſhip; that we are perſons gone aſtray: VVe profeſs to them, that we would not give way to Spiritual diſtempers, nor ſtray one ſtep from the wayes of God might we but know it; we would thank any to convince us of our miſtakes, and reduce us to the true Sheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, if we are gone aſtray: Do they ſeek after us; in a ſpirit of tenderneſs labour to convince us, and carry us in their boſoms, like tender Shepherds to the true Fold? what leſs? with force and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty they rule over us, threaten us with Excommunications, Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, Baniſhments, diſpoiling us of what God hath graciouſly given us, yea, condemning us to Death: in all which (through the Grace of God) we can rejoyce, though they thereby abundantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, that they are the ſucceſſors of the falſe Shepherds here ſpoken of. VVhat ſhould I mention,</p>
                  <p n="11">11. <hi>That they come up out of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 13. 11. are raiſed up by men of earthly ſpirits and principles.</p>
                  <p n="12">12. <hi>That they exerciſe the power of the firſt Beaſt,</hi> or make uſe of the Civil Power for their ſupportment, <hi>ver.</hi> 13.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. <hi>That they make an Image to the Beaſt, v. 14, 15. (i. e.</hi> erect an Eccleſiaſtical State of Government, in a proportionableneſs to, and reſemblance of the Civil State.)</p>
                  <p n="14">14. <hi>That they compel all under the penalty of Death, to worſhip or bow down to this Image of the Beaſt,</hi> (or Eccleſiaſtical Government, in its Courts, Canons, Laws, and Ceremonies deviſed by it) <hi>v.</hi> 15.</p>
                  <p n="15">15. <hi>That they compel all to receive a mark, either in their right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hands or foreheads;</hi> ſecretly or openly, one way or other to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſubjection unto this Beaſt, without which they may neither buy nor ſell, being cut off from the Church, by their Excommunications, for their ſtubornneſs, <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17. All which <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Beaſt</hi> (or falſe Prophet) he that runs may reade upon the preſent Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy and Miniſtry of <hi>England.</hi> It remaineth then that the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have the Characters and Properties of the falſe Prophets and Prieſts upon them, and therefore are not to be heard, but ſeparated from.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:43509:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſixth Argument againſt hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. Of the ſeveral ſorts of Idolatry, that the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are hereof guilty, proved. An Objection anſwered. That the preſent Miniſters act in Divine things by vertue of a power received from Idolaters, offer up a Worſhip abuſed to Idolatry, with the Rites and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of Idolaters. That the Romiſh Church are Idolaters. Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 6.</head>
                  <p>THoſe that are guilty of Idolatry, Saints may not have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with (much leſs own them as their Teachers) but ought to ſeparate from them: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) will not be denied, becauſe bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd upon expreſs Commands from Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 11. &amp; 10. 14. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 14, 18. Before we deſcend to the confirmation of the <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) we ſhall crave leave to premiſe; That Idolatry may be conſidered under a threefold notion. 1. Moſt groſs and abſurd Idolatry, when the creature is worſhipped terminatively; this <note n="*" place="margin">Rab. M. Maimonides de Idolat. 8. 2, 3, &amp;c. Obſerves that never any Idolater was ſo ſilly as to think that an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol of wood, ſtone or mettal, was a God that made the Heavens and Earth, but through them all Idolaters intend to worſhip God.</note> few are guilty of, the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> of old wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped not the Calf terminatively, but God in it; therefore they are ſaid to proclaim a Feaſt to Jehovah, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. 5. 2dly, Somewhat more refined Idolatry (<hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of what we but now in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanc'd in) when we offer up any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or homage, proper and due to God only, before any creature, as the <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> or Repreſentative of God: Such was the Idolatry of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Golden-Calf, Brazen-Serpent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of this are the Synagogue of <hi>Rome,</hi> amongſt all the combinations of men in the world, moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently guilty. To this Head may be added, 1. The aſcription of the Godhead to any creature, as to <hi>Herod,</hi> Acts 12. 22. 2. The aſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Properties of the Godhead to any creature. 3. The worſhipping of God in any other way than what he hath preſcribed: which all that write upon the ſecond Commandment ſay, is the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:43509:28"/> therein forbidden. 4. The Oblation of Worſhip or Service to God, that hath been offered up to Idols, for which there is no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription in the Scripture. 3dly. Moſt refined Idolatry, when the heart goes forth in deſires after any thing beyond what is limited by the Lord, or truſts and relies on any creature on this ſide God.</p>
                  <p>In the firſt ſenſe, there are (as was ſaid) few or no Idolaters in the world: the <hi>Papiſts</hi> come as near thereunto as any, praying to the Croſs, the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> Saints, Angels, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> expreſly affirming, that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> may be worſhipped with that worſhip, which they call <hi>Cultus Latriae,</hi> which yet they ſay is due only to God.</p>
                  <p>In the laſt ſenſe there are none but at one time or other may be ſaid to be Idolaters; the hearts of the beſt of men too too often going forth too far in deſires after, and ſecret dependance upon, things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath the Lord: which yet they are watching and warring againſt, waiting and longing for the day, in which they ſhall be compleatly ſwallowed up in the will of God. 'Tis in reſpect of the ſecond parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, before inſtanc'd in, that we aſſert the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be Idolaters: to the proof whereof we now addreſs our ſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 1.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe that worſhip the true God in any other way than he hath ſaid he will be worſhipped in, and is preſcribed by him, are Idolaters: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> worſhip the true God in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, than he hath ſaid he will be worſhiped in, and is preſcribed by him. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) is evident, from this ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: To worſhip the true God through falſe <hi>mediums</hi> is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, ſuch as ſo worſhip him are Idolaters; (this muſt be ſo, or elſe there is little or no Idolatry in the world, nor ever was: The <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians</hi> (and other Gentiles) worſhipped the true God, for they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped him whom <hi>Paul</hi> declared to them, even that God that made the world, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 23, 24. yet none doubts but they were Idolaters, which they cannot be charged with upon any other account, than their worſhipping the true God through falſe <hi>mediums.</hi>) But to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God in any other way than what is of his own preſcription, is to worſhip him through a falſe <hi>medium.</hi> Therefore ſo to worſhip him is Idolatry, and they that ſo worſhip him are Idolaters.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) <hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Miniſters
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:43509:29"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:43509:29"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:43509:30"/> of <hi>England,</hi> worſhip the true God in another way than he hath ſaid he will be worſhipped in, and is preſcribed by him, is that which is denied by ſome; but the truth thereof, we doubt not, will to the unprejudiced Reader be beyond exception evident, from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing demonſtration, <hi>Viz.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe that worſhip God after the way of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> worſhip him in another way, than that he hath ſaid he wil be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in, and is preſcribed by him: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> worſhip God after the way of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book:</hi> Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) cannot be denied, their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription before they are admitted to the Miniſtry, together with their daily and conſtant practice, are ſufficient evidences hereof.</p>
                  <p>As for the <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition, That to worſhip God after the way of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> is to worſhip him in a way that is not of his Appointment. 1. Let any ſhew, when, and where, ſuch a ſtinted-form of Service was appointed by Chriſt, and this part of the controverſie is at an end: ſure we are, there are not the leaſt foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of ſuch a way of Worſhip to be found in the New-Teſtament, no, not in the whole Book of God (whatever is pretended by ſome touching Lyturgies (in the ſenſe we are ſpeaking) amongſt the people of the <hi>Jews;</hi>) no, nor yet was there any ſuch a way of worſhip thought of, much leſs impoſed, in the firſt and purer times of the Goſpel, for ſeveral centuries of years, after the dayes of Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. In the Epiſtles of the Church of <hi>Smyrna</hi> (about the Martyrdom of <hi>Polycarpus</hi>) and of the Churches of <hi>Vienna</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi> (concerning their Perſecution) in the Epiſtle of <hi>Clemens</hi> (or the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> in the Writings of <hi>Ignatius, Juſtin Martyr, Clemens, Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian,</hi> and their contemporaries, there is not only an utter ſilence of ſuch a thing, but Aſſertions wholly <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and oppſit thereunto. <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſayes expreſly, <hi>Illuc ſuspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes Chriſtiani, manibus expanſis, quia innocuis, capite nudo, quia non crubeſcimus, denique ſine monitore, quia de pectore oramus. Apol. cap.</hi> 30. The <hi>Christians</hi> in thoſe dayes (he tells us) looking towards <hi>Heaven</hi> (not on their <hi>Common-Prayer-Books</hi>) with their hands ſpread abroad, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> prayed to God without a <hi>Monitor,</hi> becauſe from their hearts. And in ſeveral places he teſtifies, that they praiſed God in a way of Prayer and Thankſgiving according to their abilities. Indeed <hi>Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius de Sainctes</hi> and <hi>Pamelius</hi> (two Popiſh Divines) tell us of Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:43509:30"/> compoſed by the Apoſtles, <hi>James, Peter,</hi> and <hi>Mark:</hi> Of <hi>Peter</hi>'s and <hi>Mark</hi>'s Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf, not only takes no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar notice, but upon the matter condemns them, <hi>as ſuppoſititious and ſpurious:</hi> which that they are, is abundantly demonſtrated by learned <hi>Morney,</hi> and no more need be added thereunto. There are ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo fathered upon <hi>Baſil, Chryſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> but as theſe lived about the years 372, 381, 382, in which time many corruptions had crept into the Churches of Chriſt, ſo the ſpuriouſneſs thereof, as being falſly fathered upon the perſons whoſe names they bear, may eaſily be demonſtrated: 'Tis already done to our hands by learned <hi>Morney,</hi> in his Book <hi>De Miſſâ,</hi> l. 1. chap. 6. <hi>Durantus</hi> himſelf (the great <hi>Lyturgy-munger</hi>) acknowledges, <hi>That neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles, uſed any preſcribed Forms, but the Lords Prayer and the Creed</hi> (that <hi>they uſed theſe,</hi> he ſayes, but proves not, nor will it ever be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the worlds end) That about the year 380. <hi>Theodoſius</hi> (the Church being rent by Hereſies) intreated<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> (at whoſe election, though the conteſt was betwixt him and <hi>Urſinus,</hi> a Deacon of the Church, there were not fewer than one hundred thirty ſeven per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſlain) <hi>that ſome Eccleſiaſtical Office might be made,</hi> which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly done by <hi>Hierome,</hi> and approved by Pope <hi>Damaſus,</hi> and made a Rule. The unlikelihood of this latter part of the Story is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: <hi>Theodoſius</hi> was too well acquainted with the Spirit of Prayer, than to go about any ſuch thing; had he judged it neceſſary, having aſſembled the great Council of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein were not leſs than an hundred and fifty perſons convened; Is it probable this good man <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> would in ſo momentous a concern, rather conſult with one ſingle perſon, than ſuch an Aſſembly as were by his Authority met together? and yet ſhould this be granted, it would not from hence appear, that at this time there was any <hi>Lyturgy</hi> deviſed and impoſed; all that is pretended to be done by <hi>Hierome,</hi> was the appointing an Order for the reading of the Scriptures, which is another thing to the impoſition of Forms of Prayer in Worſhip. There is one paſſage in <hi>Socrates</hi> his <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> l. 5. c. 21. who lived about the year 430. that carrying an undeniable evidence with it that at that time there were no Lyturgies, we cannot paſs over in ſilence, 'tis this: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; wherein he tells us, <hi>that among all the Chriſtians in that age, ſcarce two were to be found that uſed the ſame words
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:43509:31"/> in Prayer.</hi> Not to tire the <hi>Reader</hi> in this diſquiſition; Though one part of the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> was not long after introduced by one Pope, and another part by another, yet till <hi>Gregories</hi> time (who to the honour of <hi>Lyturgies</hi> be it ſpoken, was the very worſt of all the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> that preceded him) <hi>viz.</hi> about the year 600. was there any conſiderable uſe, or any impoſing of them? Yea till the time of Pope <hi>Hadrian</hi> (which was about the year 800. was it not (as I find) by publick Authority impoſed: Then indeed the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Great being moved thereunto by the foreſaid <hi>Hadrian</hi>) by his Civil Authority commands <hi>the uſe of a Lyturgy</hi> (viz. <hi>Gregories Lyturgy,</hi> as is thought) to which he compels his Miniſters by Threats and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; the uſual attendancies and ſupport of <hi>Lyturgyes</hi> ever ſince their production in the world.</p>
                  <p>The ſum is, That in as much as firſt, it cannot be proved (the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary being moſt manifeſt in the Scripture) that any <hi>Lyturgy</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by Chriſt or his Apoſtles, or in uſe in the firſt Churches planted by them. 2dly, It is evident that for the firſt four hundred years and more after Chriſt, there was no <hi>Lyturgy</hi> framed, nor any by ſolemn Authority impoſed, to the year eight hundred; it follows un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniably from hence, That to worſhip God in the way of a <hi>Lyturgy,</hi> or ſtinted Forms of Prayer, is to worſhip him in a way that is not of his appointment. To which we adde,</p>
                  <p>2. That Worſhip which is an obſtruction of any poſitive duty charged by Chriſt, to be performed by the Saints, is not a Worſhip that is of his appointment. But this is undeniably true of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book-Worſhip:</hi> Therefore.</p>
                  <p>That <hi>Chriſt</hi> did upon his Aſcention <hi>give unto his Church, Officers,</hi> as ſignal characters of his <hi>Love</hi> to, and <hi>Care</hi> of it, will not be denied, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 11. is an evidence hereof beyond exception. That to theſe Officers <hi>He gave Gifts</hi> and Qualifications, every way ſuiting the imployment which he call'd them forth unto, cannot without a moſt horrid advance againſt the Wiſdome, Faithfulneſs, Love and Care of Chriſt towards the Beloved of his Soul, be gainſayed. That be not onely expects, but ſolemnly charges upon theſe Officers, <hi>an improvement of the Gifts beſtowed upon them, for the edification of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> is evidently comprized, and very frequently remarked in the Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim. 1. 6. 1 Cor. 12. 7. Epheſ. 4. 11. Prov. 17. 16. Luke</hi> 19. 20. To imagin after all this, that any Worſhip ſhould be of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:43509:31"/> the inſtitution of Chriſt, that ſhould ſhut out of doors as unneceſſary, the exerciſe of the Gifts given by him, to be made uſe of in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn diſcharge of the Worſhip of his Houſe, is ſuch an imputation of folly to him, as may not be charged upon any perſon of an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry capacity or underſtanding: Yet this is righteouſly to be imputed to him (<hi>abſit Blasphemia</hi>) if the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip,</hi> be a Worſhip of his appointment: The exerciſe of the Gift of Prayer (to mention no more) being wholly excluded hereby. Nor will it in the leaſt take off the weight of this Argument to ſay, <hi>that liberty is gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the exerciſe of this Gift before and after Sermon:</hi> For</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The whole Worſhip of God may according to theſe mens prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, be diſcharged without any Sermon at all; and its manifeſt, it is frequently ſo, at one time or other, in moſt of the Aſſemblies of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Thoſe their Prayers are alſo bounded and limited by the 55th <hi>Canon</hi> of the Conſtitutions and Canons Eccleſiaſtical.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. We had alwayes thought that Chriſt having given Gifts unto men, did require the uſe of thoſe Gifts at all times, when ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were called to the performance of that Service for which they were deſignedly given by him, by vertue of the forementioned Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. When Chriſt hath given a Gift of Prayer unto his Children, and charged them to <hi>ſtir up the Gift given, and not to napkin their Talent,</hi> we had verily thought, that when ever they had been called forth to the performance of that duty, he did really intend and expect, that they ſhould be found in the exerciſe of the Gift given, and ſee as yet no reaſon to change our apprehenſions in this matter.</p>
                  <p>But 3dly. The <hi>Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip,</hi> is a Worſhip of which we find no footſteps in the Scripture (nor in ſome centuries of years after Chriſt) as hath already been demonſtrated: Whence it follows, that 'tis a Worſhip of <hi>pure humane invention,</hi> which is not onely not of Chriſt's appointment, but contrary to the very nature of inſtituted Worſhip (as is proved in our firſt Argument) and to very many Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Lord in the Scripture, <hi>Exod. 20. 4, 5. Deut.</hi> 42. &amp; 12. 32. <hi>Prov. 30. 16. Jer. 7. 31. Mat. 15. 9, 13. Mark. 7. 7, 8. Rev.</hi> 22. 18. The mind of God in which Scriptures we have exemplified, <hi>Lev. 10. 1, 2, 3, 4. Joſh. 22. 10. &amp;c. Judg. 8. 24. 2 King. 16. 11. 1 Chron.</hi> 15. 13.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That Worſhip which is not neceſſary for the edification, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or preſervation of the Saints in the Faith and Unity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:43509:32"/> is not of the inſtitution of Chriſt. But ſuch is the Worſhip of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book:</hi> Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) will not be denied. The Lord Jeſus having freed his Diſciples from all obligations to the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the Law, inſtitutes nothing <hi>de novo,</hi> but what he knew to be neceſſary (at leaſt would be ſo by vertue of his inſtitution) for the ends aſſigned; which was the great aim of Chriſt in all Goſpel-Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, <hi>Epheſ. 4. 7, to 15, Col. 2. 19. Acts 9. 31. Rom. 14. 14, 15. 1 Cor. 10. 23. and 14. 3, 4, 5, 12, 26. 2 Cor. 12. 10. 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 4.</p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip</hi> is not neceſſary for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, comfort or preſervation of the Saints in the Faith and Unity of the Goſpel (whatever is pretended by its admirers) might many wayes be demonſtrated. Take one pregnant inſtance inſtead of all, that will make it exceeding manifeſt. The Churches of Chriſt for the firſt four centuries of years, and more, after his Aſcention, knew not any thing of ſuch a Worſhip (as hath been already demonſtrated; not to mention the Reformed Churches at this day, to whom it is as a polluted, accurſed, abominable thing) yet, than thoſe firſt and purer Churches, for Light, Conſolation, truth of Doctrine, &amp; Goſpel-Union, hitherto there hath not been any extant in the world, more Famous, or Excellent, no nor by many degrees comparable to them. But we ſhall not further proſecute this Argument; enough hath been ſaid to demonſtrate that the <hi>Common prayer-Book-Worſhip</hi> is not of the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord: Therefore ſuch as worſhip him in the way thereof, worſhip him in a way that is not of his preſcription. If the former, notwithſtanding all that hath been ſaid, be ſcrupled by any, we refer them to Tracts written by <hi>Smectymnuus, V. Powel,</hi> to a Treatiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe concerning the interest of words in Prayer,</hi> by <hi>H. D.</hi> M. A. <hi>the Common-Prayer-Book unmask'd,</hi> as alſo to a Treatiſe lately publiſhed, by a Learned (but nameleſs) Author, entituled, <hi>A Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe concerning Lyturgyes and their impoſition:</hi> In which that matter is induſtriouſly and largely debated.</p>
                  <p>Object. If to what hath hitherto been propoſed, it be ſaid, <hi>That the Lyturgie or Common-Prayer-Book is no eſſential part of Worſhip, but meerly circumſtantial: Praying, 'tis true, is part of Worſhip, but praying in this or that Form is not ſo, but meerly a circumſtance thereof: And therefore, though it be true, that the preſent Miniſters of</hi> England
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:43509:32"/> 
                     <hi>worſhip God after the way of the Common-Prayer-Book, yet it follows not, that they worſhip him after a way that is not of his appointment.</hi> To this we anſwer;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That many things are ſtrenuouſly ſuppoſed, as the <hi>baſis</hi> upon which the weight of this Objection is laid, which the Framers thereof knowing to be <hi>no eaſie</hi> task to demonſtrate, do earneſtly <hi>beg</hi> us to grant unto them: Which being matters of greater moment than many are aware of, we ſhall not part with on ſuch eaſie terms. 'Tis ſuppoſed, firſt, That there are ſome things in the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt, that are meerly circumſtances thereof, as ſuch. Secondly, That it is lawful for Saints to pray in a Form. Thirdly, That Forms of Prayer impoſed, are but meer circumſtances of Worſhip, and no eſſential parts thereof. Fourthly, That Circumſtances of Worſhip, as ſuch, are not determined by the Lord in the Scripture, but left to the wills of men, to determine therein as they ſhall judge meet. All unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Of the laſt we have already ſpoken, and ſhall not here reaſſume the debate thereof. Touching the firſt, That there are ſome things in the inſtituted Worſhip of Chriſt, that are meerly Circumſtances thereof, as ſuch, we crave liberty to deny, which till the proof thereof be attempted, may ſuffice. Circumſtances in the Worſhip of Chriſt attending Religious Actions, as actions, we grant; but Circumſtances of Worſhip, as ſuch, will never be proved: To infer that becauſe time and place, with ſundry things of the like nature, are Circumſtances in Worſhip, therefore there are Circumſtances of Worſhip as ſuch, is frivolous: Thoſe things being the attendments of religious Actions, common to any civil actions of the like nature to be performed by the ſons of men; no action to be managed by a Community, can be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly performed by them, without ſuch an aſſignment of time and place: Publick Prayer being ſo to be managed as a religious Action, hath the Circumſtances before mentioned attending it, and ſo it would were it a meer civil action to be performed by a Community, though it related not at all to the Worſhip of God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That 'tis lawful for Saints to pray in a Form (<hi>i. e.</hi> to tie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a written ſtinted form of words in prayer) is not yet proved, not like to be, 'tis too large a field for us to enter into, nor is it needful to do ſo till it be proved, That to pray in the form of the Common-Prayer-Book, or impoſed deviſed Lyturgies is ſo: yet <hi>in tranſitu,</hi> we crave leave humbly to offer, that to pray in a form, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:43509:33"/> explained, is altogether unlawful, being, 1. A quenching of the Spirit of Prayer. 2dly, A rendring uſeleſs the donation of the Spirit, as a Spirit of Prayer, unto the Children of God. 3dly, Directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit unto the many poſitive Precepts of Chriſt, before inſtanc'd in, of ſtirring up the gift given to us of God, improving the talents he hath been graciouſly pleaſed to entruſt us withal. 4thly, If it be lawful for Saints to pray in a form, 'tis lawful either becauſe they have not the Spirit, or that having the Spirit, he is not a ſufficient help to them in their approaches to God: If the firſt, they are not Saints, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. to aſſert the ſecond, is little leſs than Blaſphemy; beſides its direct oppoſition to <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26. As for the third, <hi>viz.</hi> that Forms of Prayer impoſed, are but meer Circumſtances of VVorſhip, and not parts thereof, it cannot be proved. The contrary thereunto is evident; That which is made <hi>ſo</hi> the condition of an Action, that without it the Action is not to be done, is not a Circumſtance of it, but ſuch an Adjunct as is a neceſſary part thereof: But Forms of Prayer impoſed, are ſo made by that their Impoſition. Therefore, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Sacrificing of old on the Altar at the Tabernacle and Temple, was part of the Worſhip of God; that they were to perform this Worſhip only, at thoſe places, being once commanded, was not a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that Worſhip, but as real an eſſential part thereof, as ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing was. The caſe is the ſame here; Prayer is commanded, ſo is the uſe of theſe Prayers, which are as really by vertue of that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, made alike parts of Worſhip. But,</p>
                  <p>2dly, That the <hi>Lyturgy</hi> or Common-Prayer-Book, is no eſſential part of Worſhip, is utterly denied by the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> who make it not only a part, but the principal part (to which Preaching muſt give place, and be omitted, if they have not time for both) yea, the <hi>whole</hi> of the Worſhip of God, which being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, they ſuppoſe they have ſerved him acceptably, without more ado; and if omitted, whatever elſe is done, God is not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped at all.</p>
                  <p>And thus far of the firſt Argument, for the demonſtration of what we are in the diſquiſition of, <hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are Idolaters: The ſum whereof is this, Thoſe that worſhip God in any other way than he hath ſaid he will be worſhipped in, and is preſcribed by him, are Idolaters; But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> worſhip God in another way than he hath ſaid he will be
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:43509:33"/> worſhipped in, and is preſcribed by him, (<hi>viz.</hi> in the way of the Common-Prayer-Book, which that it is not of Divine Preſcription, hath been demonſtrated) Therefore—. To which we add,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 2.</head>
                  <p>Thoſe who act in the holy things of God, by vertue of an Office-Power received from Idolaters, and offer up to him, a Worſhip meerly of humane compoſition, once abuſed to Idolatry, with the Modes and Rites of Idolaters, are guilty of the ſin of Idolatry: But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> act in the holy things of God, by vertue of an Office-Power received from Idolaters, and offer up to him a Worſhip meerly of humane compoſition, once abuſed to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry with the Modes and Rites of Idolaters. Therefore—</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) carrying a brightneſs along with it, ſufficient to lead any one into the belief of the truth thereof, one would think might be taken for granted. Two things are aſſerted therein.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That ſuch as act in the holy things of God, by vertue of an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice-Power received from Idolaters, are themſelves ſuch (at leaſt in reſpect of that their Office-Power ſo received by them.) That <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi>'s Prieſts were all of them Idolaters we ſuppoſe will not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied: Suppoſing ſome one or more to Act in the Worſhip of God by vertue of an Office-Power received from them, were theſe to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted in that reſpect, Idolaters? it ſeemeth ſo: nor can there be the leaſt pretence of reaſon to the contrary: Certainly ſuch as act by vertue of Authority committed to them, in matters Civil, from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, are equally guilty of Rebellion, as thoſe from whom they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive that their Authority. The caſe is here the ſame.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That ſuch as offer up to God a Worſhip meerly of humane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, once abuſed to Idolatry with the Modes and Rites of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, are Idolaters: If theſe be not ſuch, I muſt profeſs I know not who are. That there are few, or none, that worſhip the creature ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minative, will not be denied, the moſt of Idolaters in the world are ſuch, upon the account of their worſhipping the true God through <hi>Mediums</hi> of their own deviſing, with Rites and Modes that never entered into the heart of God to preſcribe. To aſſert that any ſhould ſymbolize with Idolaters herein (who are ſoley upon this foot of account ſuch) and not be guilty of the ſin of Idolatry, is abſurd and irrational. The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition then (as was ſaid) may be
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:43509:34"/> taken for granted; Such as act in the holy things of God by vertue of an Office-Power received from Idolaters, and offer up to God a Worſhip meerly of humane compoſition, once abuſed to Idolatry, are Idolaters. Whether this be true of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is in the next place to be conſidered; of which briefly.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> (ſo called) are Idolaters, their Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, in the complex thereof, Idolatry; will not (we ſuppoſe) be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by any that call themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> the moſt learned of whom have aſſerted and proved it ſo to be: If any of our Reverend Fathers are of another mind, we would entreat them to conſtrue to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves a Copy or two of Verſes, compoſed by Perſons of Eminency in that Combination of men, and then give us their ſecond thoughts, which are uſually better than the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus ſome of them,
<q>
                        <l>—O felix Puerpera,</l>
                        <l>Noſtra pians Scelera,</l>
                        <l>Jure Matris Impera Redemptori.</l>
                     </q> VVherein the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is not only prayed unto, but Chriſt in his Exalted ſtate is ſubjected to her Authority; which is not only a ſpice of Idolatry, but alſo ſome of the moſt horrid Blaſphemy imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Their praying to Images, Adoration of Saints, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is known. Take a taſte hereof in the enſuing Inſtances; thus then they ſpeak:
<q>
                        <l>O Crux ſpes unica,</l>
                        <l>Auge piis conſtantiam</l>
                        <l>Hoc paſſionis tempore,</l>
                        <l>Reiſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> dona veniam.</l>
                     </q> In which the Croſs it ſelf is invocated, as their only Hope, to beſtow pardon upon the guilty, patience and conſtancy upon the Godly. And who comes not in the leaſt ſhort hereof, for Blaſphemy and Idolatry. <hi>Bonarous</hi> the Jeſuite, <hi>Lib. 3. Amphitrial. Honor. l. 3. cap. ult. ad Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Hallenſem, &amp; Puerum Jeſum,</hi> ſaith as followeth:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Haereo haec inter meditans, interque cruorem,<note place="margin">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Thomas de Aquino 3a parte Sum: Quaeſt. 25. Arti:</hi> ſayes, <hi>Sequitur, quod eadem reverentia exhibeatur imagini Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, &amp; ipſi Chriſto, cum ergo Chriſtus adoratur adoratione latriae, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quens eſt, quod ejus ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſit adoratione latriae adoranda.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>
                              <hi>The Image of Chriſt,</hi> he tells you, <hi>is to be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiped with the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that Chriſt is.</hi> Yea, <hi>Bellarmine de Imag. cap.</hi> 21. ſays, <hi>Imagines Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, &amp; Sanctorum vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randae ſunt, non ſolum per accidens, &amp; impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè, ſed etiam per ſe, &amp; propriè, ita ut ipſae termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent venerationem, ut in ſe conſiderantur, &amp; non ſolem, vicem gerunt exemplaris.</hi>
                           </p>
                           <p>In which he aſſerts, what I had thought had not bin own'd by any Idolater in the world, <hi>viz. That Images are to be worſhipped, not as the repreſentatives of the Deity, &amp;c. and</hi> per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidens, <hi>but properly and</hi> per ſe, <hi>ſo as that they ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate the Worſhip.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inter delicias uberis, &amp; lateris.</l>
                     <l>Et dico (ſi forte oculos ſuper ubera tendo)</l>
                     <l>Diva parens mammae gaudia poſco tuae.</l>
                     <l>Sed dico (ſi deinde oculos in vulnera verto)</l>
                     <l>O Jeſu lateris gaudia malo tui.</l>
                     <l>Rem ſcio prenſabo ſi fas erit ubera dextrâ,</l>
                     <l>Laevâ prenſabo vulnera ſi dabitur.</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:43509:34"/>
                     <l>Lac matris miſcere volo, cum ſanguine nati,</l>
                     <l>Non poſſum antid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>to nobiliore frui.</l>
                     <l>Vulnera reſtituant turpem, ulceribus mendicum,</l>
                     <l>Teſta cui ſaniem radere ſola poteſt.</l>
                     <l>Ubera reficient <hi>Iſmaelem</hi> ſitientem,</l>
                     <l>Quem <hi>Sara</hi> non patitur, quem ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nutrit <hi>Agar.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Iſta mihi ad peſtem, procul &amp; procul, expungendam,</l>
                     <l>Iſta mihi ad longas evalitura febres.</l>
                     <l>Ira vomit flammas ſumat<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> libidinis <hi>Aetna,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Suffocare queo ſanguine lacte queo.</l>
                     <l>Livor inexpleta rubigine ſaevit in artus</l>
                     <l>Detergere queo lacte, cruore queo.</l>
                     <l>Vanus honos me perpetua, prurigine tentat,</l>
                     <l>Exſaturare queo ſanguine lacte queo.</l>
                     <l>Ergo parens, &amp; nate meis advertite, votis,</l>
                     <l>Lac peto, depereo ſanguinem, utrum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> volo.</l>
                     <l>O ſitio tamen! O vocem ſitis intercludit.</l>
                     <l>Natae cruore ſitim comprime, lacte parens.</l>
                     <l>Dic matri, meus hic ſitit optima mater,</l>
                     <l>Vis e fonte tuo promere; de<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> meo.</l>
                     <l>Dic nato, tuus his frater, mi mellee fili</l>
                     <l>Captivus monſtrat vincula, lytron habes.</l>
                     <l>Ergo Redemptorem monſtra te jure vocari,</l>
                     <l>Ubera ſi reliquis divitiora geris.</l>
                     <l>O quando lactabor ab ubere vulnere paſcar,</l>
                     <l>Deliciiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fruar, mamma, latuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> tuis.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>To which might be added as ſecond hereunto, the blaſphemous poetry of <hi>Franciſcus de Mendoza, in viridario utriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eruditionis,</hi> lib. 2. Prob. 2. The uſual aſcription of <hi>Laus Deo, Virgini<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> matri Mariae,</hi> in the cloſe of their writings; in which, Divine honour with God is aſcribed to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> is known to all: Any ordinary Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der knows where to furniſh himſelf with many more inſtances of the like nature, equalizing, if not exceeding in expreſſion the greateſt Idolaters that ever were in the world. We judge it not neceſſary to ſtand longer upon this matter, 'tis beyond exception evident, that that Aſſembly of men that are uſually known, by the name of the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:43509:35"/> 
                     <hi>Church of Rome</hi> are Idolaters: If there be any ſuch in the world, they are ſo.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> act by vertue of an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice-Power, from this Combination and Aſſembly of Idolaters, they themſelves will not deny: Succeſſion from hence being one of the beſt pleas they have for the juſtification of their Miniſtry: (which when they have proved, that ever the Lord Jeſus did entruſt an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of the greateſt Murderers, Adulterers and Idolaters in the world, with any power for the ſending forth Officers to act in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Things of God, to, and for the <hi>Church,</hi> his <hi>Spouſe,</hi> will be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but this they ſhall never be able to do) So hugely importunate are ſome of them herein, that they are not aſhamed to ask us, why Ordination may not be received from the Church (ſo called) of <hi>Rome,</hi> as well as the Scripture? To which we ſhall onely ſay, that when it is proved that we received the Scripture from that Apoſtate Church, by vertue of any Authority thereof, as ſuch, ſomewhat of moment may be admitted in that enquiry, but this will never be done. 'Tis true, the Bible was kept among the People in thoſe parts where the Pope prevaileth, yet followeth it not from hence that we received it from their Authority, as Ordination is received; if we did, why did we not keep it, as delivered from them to us, in the vulgar Latine? ſo that of theſe things there is not the ſame reaſon! It will not then be denied, but the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> act in the holy things of God, by vertue of an Office-Power received by Succeſſion from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo from Idolaters (that Church being eminently ſo, as hath been proved.)</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Nor can it be denied, but they offer up to God a Worſhip meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Humane Compoſition</hi> (as the Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip hath been proved to be) once abuſed to Idolatry, with the Modes and Rites of Idolaters. That the Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip is a VVorſhip that was once abuſed to Idolatry, being the VVorſhip of that Church, whoſe VVorſhip (at leaſt in the complex thereof) is ſo, cannot, with the leaſt pretence of Reaſon, be denied. That the <hi>whole</hi> of it is derived from, and taken out of the Pope's <hi>Portuis,</hi> as are the Common-Prayers out of the <hi>Breviary;</hi> the Adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Burial, Matrimony, Viſitation of the Sick, out of the <hi>Ritual,</hi> or Book of Rites: The Conſecration of the Lord's Supper, Collects, Epiſtles, Goſpels, out of the <hi>Maſs-Book:</hi> The Ordination of Arch-Biſhops,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:43509:35"/> Biſhops, and Prieſts, out of the <hi>Romane Pontifical,</hi> hath been aſſerted and proved by many. Which might be evidenced (if need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful) beyond exception, not onely by comparing the one with the other, but alſo from the offer was made by Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the 4th, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13th, to Q. <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to <hi>confirm the Engliſh Lyturgy,</hi> which did it not ſymbolize with the Service of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they would not have done. Yea, when the ſaid Queen was interdicted by the Popes <hi>Bull,</hi> Secretary <hi>Walſingham</hi> procures two intelligencers from the Pope, who ſeeing the Service of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the Pomp thereof, wonder <hi>that their Lord, the Pope, ſhould be ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adviſed, as to inderdict a Prince, whoſe Servive and Ceremonies did ſo ſymbolize with his own:</hi> When they come to <hi>Rome,</hi> they ſatisfie the Pope, <hi>That they ſaw no Service, Ceremonies, or Orders in</hi> England, <hi>but might very well ſerve in Rome;</hi> upon which the <hi>Bull</hi> was recalled. Not to mention what we have already minded, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of King <hi>Edward</hi> the 6th and his Council; witneſſing <hi>the Engliſh Service to be the ſame, and no other but the old, the ſelf-ſame words in Engliſh that were in Latine</hi> (which was the worſhip of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes) it's evident, that the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> offer up a Worſhip to God, once abuſed to Idolatry. That they do this with the Rites, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and Modes <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Maccovius loc. com. append. de adiaph. p.</hi> 860. ſaith, <hi>Non licet mutuari, aut retinere res aut ritas Sacros Idololatrarum ſive Ethni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum ſive Pontificiorum, &amp;c. etſi in ſe res fuerint adia Phorae quia vitandam eſſe omnem conformita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem cum Idololatris docemur.</hi> Lev. 19. 4, 27. and 21. 5. Deut. 14. 1.</note> of Idolaters (<hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are in uſe in that Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) needs not many words to demonſtrate; what elſe is the Prieſts change of Voice; Poſture and Place in Worſhip en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned them? not to mention their <hi>Holy Veſtmentes, Bowings, Cringings, Candles, Altars, &amp;c.</hi> all of which as it's known, owe their original unto the appointments thereof. It remaineth, That the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England,</hi> acting in the Holy Things of God, by vertue of an Office-Power received from Idolaters, and offering up to him a Worſhip meerly of humane compoſition, once abuſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to Idolatry with the Rites and Modes of Idolaters, are deeply guilty of the ſin of Idolatry. To which we adde,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:43509:36"/>
                  <head>Argument 3.</head>
                  <p>Adoration in, by, or before a creature <hi>respectivè,</hi> or with relation to the creature, is Idolatry; ſuch as ſo adore, or worſhip God are Idolaters. But the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> do adore or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God, in, by, or before a creature <hi>reſpectivè,</hi> or with relation to the creature: Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> (or firſt propoſition) being generally owned by <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> it being the very ſame <hi>maxime</hi> they make uſe of, and ſtop the mouth of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> with, in the point of adoring God mediately by the creature, we ſhall not ſtand upon the proof of it: None that know what they ſay, will deny it.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>minor</hi> Propoſition (<hi>viz.</hi> That the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> do adore, or worſhip God, in, by, or before the creature <hi>respe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctivè,</hi> or with relation to the creature) will receive a quick diſpatch: Not to mention their bowing and cringing at the <hi>Altar:</hi> That <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Didoclavius</hi> p. 755. ſaith, <hi>Genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectere non modo excludit ritus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutionis, ſed etiam praeceptum ſecundum de vitandâ Idololatriâ multis modis violat;</hi> which <hi>Macco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi> aſſents to, <hi>loc. com. p. 861.</hi>
                     </note> they kneel at the receiving of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is known, that they with their Communicants ſhould do ſo, is enjoyned by their Church, That their ſo doing is an adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or worſhipping of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the creature <hi>respectivè,</hi> or with relation to the creature, is too manifeſt to admit of a denial: Nothing being more certain than that the Elements are the <hi>objectum ſignificativè à quo,</hi> or the motive of their kneeling, which if they were not there, they would not do.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> To what hath been hitherto offered in this matter, if it be ſaid, <hi>That the charging the preſent Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>with Idolatry, is exceeding harſh, and that which is an argument of a very unchriſtian, and cenſorious ſpirit.</hi> Though this makes nothing to the enervating of what hath been offered, yet we anſwer,</p>
                  <p>1. That many words of Chriſt himſelf, were accounted <hi>hard ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> and not to be <hi>born,</hi> and that by ſuch Hearers as were once his Admirers, and did with ſeeming-great affection attend upon his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry: That ſuch poor worms as we ſhould be recharged herewith, is no great marvel, it is enough for the Diſciple to be as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:43509:36"/>
                  <p>2dly, We have in this matter ſaid nothing, but what is <hi>in Theſi,</hi> over and over aſſerted, by moſt or all Proteſtant VVriters, upon the ſecond Commandment: who aſſert fully, that the <note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Calvin, Perkins, Ames, Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covius, Altingius, Wendeline. Paraeus, Explicat. Cate. p. 3. Q. 96. p.</hi> 528. ſaith, <hi>Quid po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulat ſecundum praeceptum? Reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Deum ullâ imagine, aut figurâ exprimamus neve ullâ alia ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione eum colamus, quam quâ ſe in ſuo verbo coli praecepit,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 23. Deut. 12. 30. Mat. 15. 9. And afterwards he addeth, <hi>Huic ſecundo Praecepto contraria ſunt ea, quae vero cultui divino adverſantur. 1. Idololatria, quae est cultus numinis fictitius, aut ſuperſtitioſus. Sunt autem Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatriae duae ſpecies, praecipuae: una craſſior, cum fictitium nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men colitur—haec ſpecies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibetur in imo praecepto, &amp; ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quâ ex parte, in tertio: altera eſt ſubtilior, cum verus Deus coli fingitur, ſed errator in genere cultus, hoc eſt, cum vero Deo cultus fingitur praeſtari, aliquo opere, quod ipſe non praecepit haec ſpecies Idololatriae, hoc praecepto propriè damnatur, &amp; nominatur <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, ſive ſuperſtitio.</hi> And pag. 529. <hi>Qui peccant contra ſecundum praeceptum, peccant &amp; contra primum, quia qui Deum aliter colunt, atque vult coli, illi fingunt Deum aliter effectum, atque eſt, hoc eſt alium Deum: Ita non Deum, ſed cerebri ſui commentum, quod ſic affectum eſſe ſibi perſuadent, colunt—fingere alium Dei cultum, eſt aliam Dei voluntatem, proinde &amp; alium De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um fingere, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> worſhipping God in a way not preſcribed by him, is Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry; ſuch as do ſo, are Idolaters: with our application hereof unto the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> if they are guilty (as that they are, hath been abundantly demonſtrated) why ſhould any be offended? To ſpeak Truth, when our ſilence would be prejudicial to the ſouls of our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, methinks ſhould not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted unchriſtian or cenſorious.</p>
                  <p>But 3dly, What would theſe Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors have ſaid to <hi>Tertullian,</hi> (that renowned Servant and VVitneſs of the Lord Jeſus in his day) who is by far more nice in this point of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaty, than we have declared our ſelves to be; He in his Book <hi>De Idololatria,</hi> chargeth ſuch as make Statues or Images, build or adorn Idols Temples, (though it were their trade) Aſtrologers, Schoolmaſters, (that name the names of Idols, making honorable mention of them in their Orations) ſuch as keep holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayes, dedicated to Idolatrous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as their <hi>Saturnalia</hi> (in the ſtead
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:43509:37"/> of which, is the time with us called <hi>Chriſtmaſs</hi>) &amp;c. ſuch as adorned their Gates, Poſts, Houſes after the Pagan manner at Feſtivals, with Lawrel, Ivy, &amp;c. as ſympolizing with Idolaters: yet ſure we are, he could not juſtly be charged with an unchriſtian or cenſorious ſpirit. If it be further ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Obj. 2. <hi>But what ſhall we judge of</hi> Latimer, Ridley, Hooper, <hi>and many other famous Witneſſes and Martyrs of Chriſt, who worſhipped God after the ſame way of Worſhip that theſe do now? were they alſo Idolaters? how could they be ſaved then, when the Scripture ſayes, that</hi> no Idolater ſhall inherit the Kingdom of God, <hi>and we do not find that they repented hereof?</hi> To this we anſwer.</p>
                  <p>1. That the perſons inſtanc'd in, were eminent Witneſſes of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt in their day (whoſe very Names are in our noſtrils as ſweet Perfume) we readily grant, and would be loth to ſpeak one word to abate of that juſt eſteem is due to their Names and Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny for Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>2dly, That they are now with Chriſt, and ſhall come with him, and ſit upon Thrones to judge their unjuſt Judges in the day appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereunto, we have not the leaſt ſcruple.</p>
                  <p>But 3dly, they were but men encompaſſed about with many infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; that they were guilty of the ſin of Idolatry, cannot (from what hath been ſaid herein it's evident) be denied.</p>
                  <p>Yet, 1. They were in that day but juſt peeping out of the Gates of <hi>Babylon,</hi> beginning to ariſe and ſhake themſelves out of the duſt of the Abominations of the great Whore; and 'tis no wonder if ſome of the filth of her Fornications did cleave to them. 2. They wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God in ſincerity according to the light he was pleaſed in that day to communicate, and God accepted of them in Chriſt, granting to them a general Repentance for thoſe Iniquities they ſaw not to be ſo, knew not themſelves guilty of. Which is all we ſhall at preſent ſay hereunto. The intelligent Reader knows that theſe things are not of any moment for the invalidating of what hath been offered upon this ſubject. Thus far of this eighth Argument, The preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are guilty of Idolatry; therefore 'tis the duty of Saints not to hear, but ſeparate from them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:43509:37"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A 7th Argument againſt hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi> 'Tis an offence, grief, and cauſe of ſtumbling to the Saints, proved. Two Objections anſwered. The nature of Scandal given. An eighth Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument propoſed to conſideration. The various wayes of partaking with others in their ſin, conſidered. That hearing the preſent Miniſters, is a partaking with them in their ſin, proved.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="7" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 7.</head>
                  <p>'TIs not lawful for Saints to do any thing, for the doing whereof, there is no poſitive Precept in the Scripture, that is an Offence, Grief, Scandal and cauſe of ſtumbling to their Brethren: But the hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> (as there is no poſitive Precept in the Scripture for it, ſo it) is an Offence, Grief, Scandal and cauſe of ſtumbling to the Brethren. Therefore—</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) is bottom'd upon expreſs Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts in the Scripture, <hi>Rom. 14. 13, 15, 20. 1 Cor.</hi> 8. 9, 13. and 10. 24.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) conſiſts of two parts.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That for hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> there is no poſitive warrant in the Scripture; if there be, let it be produced, and this Controverſie is at an end: The contrary thereunto, hath all along been manifeſt in this preſent Diſcourſe. It cannot enter into our hearts, to imagin, that the Lord Jeſus having inſtituted Officers of his own, for the management of Affairs in his Houſe, ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, that any of his Houſhold ſhould attend upon the Miniſtry of ſuch as are not of his inſtitution (as hath been abundantly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated touching the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> that they are not) nor is it by many, pleaded as their duty ſo to do; but onely as their Liberty, which they judge they may, or they may not do, without ſin.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That for the Saints (ſuch as are viſibly ſo, profeſs themſelves to be ſuch) to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is an Offence, Grief, Scandal and occaſion of ſtumbling to their Brethren. This is too evident to be denied, to how many thouſands in <hi>England</hi> for whom (thoſe that as yet attend upon the preſent Miniſtry thereof, dare not but think) Chriſt dyed, is the practiſe of ſome herein, a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:43509:38"/> Grief, Scandal and occaſion of Stumbling? Their groans and tears, alone, and together upon this foot of account, will better demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the truth hereof, than our words can. Yea, how many poor ſouls have been drawn, by reaſon of the practiſe of ſome Leading Brethren in this matter, againſt the checks of their own conſciences, to a Conformity herein, to their after-grief and wounding? Upon whoſe doors 'tis to be feared (and we wiſh they would in the fear of God lay it to heart) may be written, <hi>THE BLOOD OF SOULS.</hi> If it be ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Object. <hi>That there is a twofold Scandal,</hi> 1. Scandalum acceptum, <hi>a Scandal, or Offence taken.</hi> 2. Scandalum datum, <hi>a Scandal or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence given. In respect of the former, poſſibly many may be offended at their practiſe in the matter treated of, and ſo would ſome or other whatever is done by them: 'Tis impoſſible but Offences ſhould come, that there is any juſt Offence given by them, herein, is denied.</hi> To this we an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That as we admit of the diſtinction, ſo no doubt there is a truth in what is ſuggeſted thereupon, That whatever I do, ſome one or other will be offended at it: There are a generation of men, whom the <hi>doing</hi> of my duty will offend, and cauſe to blaſpheme; theſe are not to be minded, but to be pitied: Chriſt himſelf was to ſome <hi>a Rock of Offence, and Stone of Stumbling.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. But 'tis not yet proved (nor like to be) that the Scandal treated of, is a Scandal <hi>taken</hi> and not <hi>given,</hi> the very nature of Scandal given, as is confeſt by all, and evident beyond exception from the Apoſtles diſcourſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 10. lying in the doing of what is judged, by me, to be my liberty, which other Saints are not fully perſwaded of in their own minds to be ſo, but are ready to conclude it to be my ſin, and evil, and from thence have occaſion of Grief, or Stumbling ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to them. This was the very caſe of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> (upon the occaſion whereof <hi>Paul</hi> writes to them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.) ſome of them judged it their <hi>liberty to ſit at meat in the Idols Temple;</hi> others not being fully perſwaded hereof, were ſcandalized many wayes, at this their practiſe, which the Apoſtle therefore condemns as <hi>unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi> Should it for Arguments ſake be granted (though in truth it be not ſo) that 'tis the liberty of Saints, to hear the preſent Miniſters, yet many of the ſincere Lambs of Chriſt, being ſtumbled, grieved and Scandalized herear, for that very reaſon (if no more could be
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:43509:38"/> ſaid herein) it becomes our ſin (to be guilty whereof, who can chuſe but be filled with trembling, that hath ever with ſeriouſneſs read that terrible Commination of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 18. 6. Whoſo ſhall offend one of theſe little Ones that believe in me, it were better for him that a milſtone were hanged about his neck, and he were drowned in the depths of the Sea?</hi>) eſpecially when thoſe that are thus ſcandalized, are able to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, <hi>that their Offence is not any peviſh Humour, or fooliſh Nicety, but what is too really adminiſtred by the actions of their Brethren:</hi> When they ſhall hear Chriſt, commanding them <hi>to ſeparate from every thing of Antichriſt,</hi> Rev. 18. 4. and therefore <hi>from his Miniſtry,</hi> and they are in conſcience perſwaded the Miniſters of <hi>England are ſuch,</hi> which they judge they are able to demonſtrate: When they conſider, how the Laws of their dear Lord and Law-giver are made void, by the traditions of theſe pretended Miniſters, whoſe Kingſhip they ſee them viſibly oppoſing, when they find upon them the characters of <hi>Falſe Prophets,</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and are able to manifeſt, <hi>that they are deeply guilty of the ſin of Idolatry</hi> (from whom they are enjoyned by Chriſt <hi>to turn away</hi>) yea when they take a veiw of the frame of the ſpirits of their now Conforming-Brethren in dayes paſt, and the Principles were then owned by them: That they did then (ſome of them at leaſt) ſeparate from the Aſſemblies of <hi>England,</hi> as <hi>not true Churches of Chriſt,</hi> and accounted the Common-Prayer-Book-Prieſts, <hi>perſons not meet to preach, unworthy to be attended upon in their ſo doing,</hi> and ſee them now ſaying, <hi>A confederacy with,</hi> and <hi>attending upon</hi> the miniſtry of thoſe very perſons and things, from whom, not onely Chriſt hath commanded them to <hi>ſeparate,</hi> but theſe very Brethren did formerly <hi>decry,</hi> and at leaſt ſeemingly <hi>abominate,</hi> they judge, they <hi>have juſt ground of Offence given to them:</hi> Nor can it be denied, but it is indeed ſo. If it be yet further ſaid,</p>
                  <p>Object. 2. <hi>But if I do not go to hear the Preachers of this day, many truly godly and ſober Chriſtians will be offended at my forbearance; ſo that whether I hear, or whether I forbear, I ſhall offend.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this I anſwer, 1. That granting the caſe to be as is ſuggeſted (though perhaps ſomewhat elſe, upon a ſerious and ſtrict ſearch, may be found to lye at the bottom of our Conformity beyond what is here pleaded: I am very apt to believe were but a toleration granted, 'tis not the fear of offending any, would cauſe our Conforming-Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to attend upon the Miniſtry of the preſent Prieſts of <hi>England.</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:43509:39"/> Yet ſuppoſing it to be as is intimated) we ask, 1. Do you look upon your going to hear as your duty, or meerly as your liberty? if the firſt, let it be proved from any poſitive precept of Chriſt, and we are ſatisfied: If the ſecond, you are bound by many ſolemn injunctions (which are at leaſt reduceable to the Moral Law) not to uſe your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to Scandalize your Brethren.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Let both parties be weighed in an upright Ballance, ſuch as you judge to be offended with you for <hi>not hearing,</hi> and ſuch as are offended <hi>thereat.</hi> I am bold to ſay, That the laſt mentioned, for Number, Holineſs, Spirituallity and Tenderneſs, do far ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount the former, who will really be Scandalized at your forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Let alſo the grounds of the offence on both ſides, be weighed; the one are offended at you, <hi>That you build not up in practiſe, in a day of trouble;</hi> and cauſe thereby the Enemies of the Lord to tryumph and blaſpheme, what in a day of liberty, you did in your preaching and practiſe, pull down and deſtroy: The other, becauſe of your <hi>diſobedience to what they are ſatisfied;</hi> and you your ſelves once were, God is calling you to (<hi>viz. to have nothing to do with, ſeparate from, this generation of men.</hi>) But</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That 'tis your duty (eſpecially if in a Church-Relation) to meet together as a People <hi>called,</hi> and picked <hi>by the Lord</hi> out of the Nations of the World, in a way of diſtinction from them, cannot be denied: the neglect of which, is charged by the Lord, as <hi>the firſt ſtep to Apoſtacy,</hi> Heb. 10. 25. Be you in the practiſe of this duty, and ſee, what Spiritual Saint will be offended at you; if any ſhould, you might have peace therein; you doing your duty, no juſt cauſe of Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is given. Yet further,</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, Conſider on which ſide the Croſs lies; which the Fleſh, and fleſhly intereſt is moſt oppoſite to, whether in <hi>going,</hi> or <hi>forbearing</hi> to go to hear theſe men, and let that be choſen: Uſually, that is the way of God that hath moſt of the Croſs in it, and the fleſh is moſt ſtrugling and conteſting againſt. But thus much of the ſeventh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument. 8.</head>
                  <p>That which Saints cannot do without being guilty of <hi>partaking with others in their ſin,</hi> is utterly unlawful for them to do. But the Saints cannot attend upon the Miniſtry of <hi>England,</hi> without being guilty of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:43509:39"/> partaking with them in their ſin. Therefore—</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition is clearly bottomed upon Scripture, <hi>Pſal. 50. 18. Epheſ. 5. 7. 1 Tim. 5. 22. 2 John 11. Rev.</hi> 18. 4. which might be abundantly demonſtrated were it needful: Sure that God who commands me <hi>to abſtain from all appearance of evil,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5. 22. never enjoyned, expects not that I ſhould be found in the practice of what, without ſin, cannot be performed by me.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> Propoſition, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Saints cannot attend upon the preſent Miniſtry of <hi>England,</hi> without being partakers with them in their ſin, will admit of a ſpeedy diſpatch. Two things are briefly to be enquired into.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What that, or thoſe ſins are we ſuppoſe the Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be guilty of.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. How it will appear that any perſon's attending upon their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, renders him guilty of partaking with them therein. Of the former we have already treated, and proved (beyond what any are able to ſay to the contrary) That they are guilty of the ſins of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God in a way that is not of his appointment, of acting in the Holy things of God, by vertue of an Antichriſtian Power, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Calling; of oppoſing really the Prophetical and Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Chriſt; of uſing and conforming to Modes and Rites in Worſhip, not appointed by the Lord, that have been abuſed to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, &amp;c. Nor is it denied by our Conforming-Brethren, but with ſome of theſe things the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> may be juſtly charged: That they worſhip God after the way of the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book,</hi> with Modes and Rites uſed in the Papacy, cannot be denied: Nor can their undue adminiſtration of that great Ordinance of our Lord Jeſus, <hi>of breaking Bread to all,</hi> according to the form therein preſcribed: That they are Ordained, and ſome of them Re-ordained by the <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> is alſo known. I ask, are theſe things the ſin and evil of theſe men, or are they not? If they are not, why did not our preaching-Brethren receive the Ordination from the Biſhops theſe received? Yea, why do not our half-conforming-Brethren attend upon the reading<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of the Service uſed, joyn with them in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper as adminiſtred by them? Doth not their abſenting themſelves herefrom, abundantly demonſtrate, that they in their conſciences are perſwaded, that 'tis the ſin and evil of the preſent Prieſts of <hi>England</hi> thus to act, and from ſuch a Miſſion in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:43509:40"/> the Worſhip of the Lord? As for the ſecond, That the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is that which renders a man guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of being partaker with them in their ſin; the conſideration of the ſeveral wayes perſons may juſtly be charged with <hi>being guilty of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with others in their ſin,</hi> will abundantly demonſtrate the truth thereof. To inſtance in a few particulars; Then may perſons juſtly be charged as guilty hereof,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. When they are found any way conſenting with them in their ſin, <hi>Pſal. 50. 18. When thou ſaweſt a Theif, then thou conſentedſt with him, and haſt been partaker with Adulterers.</hi> 'Tis not the doing of the act that was done by theſe wicked perſons, that is here called <hi>partaking</hi> with them, but a ſecret conſenting with them therein.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. When they do that which hath a real tendency to encourage perſons in their ſin, 2 <hi>John 11. Receive them not into your houſes, bid them not Godspeed; for he that biddeth them God ſpeed is partaker of their evil deeds.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. When they neglect the doing of thoſe duties which the Lord requires at their hands, for the reclaiming of them from their ſin; ſuch are <hi>Watching over, Rebuking, Admoniſhing,</hi> firſt <hi>privately,</hi> then by <hi>two,</hi> and in caſe of obſtinacy and perſeverance therein, <hi>telling it to the Church:</hi> which are duties eminently comprized in the enſuing Scriptures, 1 <hi>Theſ. 5. 14. Heb. 3. 12, 13. and 10. 24, 25. Lev. 19. 17. Mat.</hi> 18. 15, 16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. When they (notwitſtanding all that they have done, or can do, being under an utter incapacity of proceeding further therein) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them to perſevere in their ſin, ſhall ſtill continue to hold com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them, and not ſeparate from them. <hi>Rev. 18. 4. Come out of her my People; leſt being partakers of her ſins, ye receive of her plagues:</hi> The abiding with obſtinate perſevering Offenders (as it is againſt poſitive injunctions of the Moſt High, <hi>Rom. 16. 17. 2 Cor. 6. 14, 15, 16, 17. 1 Tim. 6. 5. Epheſ. 5. 8, 11. Rev.</hi> 18. 4. So is it in the laſt place inſtacn'd in) aſſigned by the Spirit to be one way of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with others in their ſins. Not to multiply more particulars, let us in a few words make Application of theſe remarked. To the buſineſs in hand.</p>
                  <p>Is there any thing in the world that carries a greater brightneſs and evidence with it, than this, That the hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is to be partakers with them in their ſin? is not our ſo
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:43509:40"/> doing, a ſecret conſenting with them, and encouraging of them in their evil deeds? Is this to diſcharge thoſe duties incumbent upon us (if we indeed look upon them as Brethren) for their reclaiming? yea, is this to come out of, and ſeparate from them? what leſs? So then, except it can be proved, that the particulars inſtanc'd in, are not ſome of thoſe wayes, whereby perſons do become guilty of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with other mens ſins; or that to attend upon the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England,</hi> is not what doth ſymbolize with ſome one, more, or all of them (which can never be done) it evidently follows, that 'tis not lawful for Saints to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> the doing whereof, is apparantly a partaking with them in their evil deeds.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ninth Argument againſt hearing the preſent Miniſters. That it caſts contempt upon the Wayes and Inſtitutions of Chriſt, hardens perſons in a falſe way of Worſhip and Rebellion against God, proved. A tenth Argument produced, That 'tis not lawful to go into the Aſſemblies of falſe Worſhippers, proved. An eleventh Argument, that there is no promiſe of a Bleſſing upon the hearing theſe men, proved. A twelfth Argument, proving, that ſo to do, is the firſt ſtep to Apoſtacy. Several Queries propoſed.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="9" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 9.</head>
                  <p>THat the doing whereof doth caſt contempt upon the Wayes and Inſtitutions (ſome one or more of them) of our Lord Jeſus, and hardens perſons in a falſe way of Worſhip and Rebellion againſt him, is utterly unlawful for the Saints to do: But the hearing of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> is that, the doing whereof doth caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the VVayes and Inſtitutions (ſome one or more of them) of our Lord Jeſus, and hardens perſons in a falſe way of VVorſhip and Rebellion againſt him. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>major</hi> Propoſition is laid down in ſuch full, clear, and evident expreſſions, bottom'd upon Scripture and right Reaſon, as carry a brightneſs with them, that none but ſuch as are deſperately and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicially blinded, will or can gainſay.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) <hi>viz.</hi> That the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is the doing of that which doth caſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon the VVayes and Inſtitutions of our Lord Jeſus, and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:43509:41"/> hardens perſons in a falſe way of VVorſhip and Rebellion againſt him, is by our diſſenting-Brethren gainſayed. Three things are therein aſſerted.</p>
                  <p>1. That our hearing theſe perſons is that which caſts contempt upon the VVayes and Inſtitutions of Chriſt. 2dly. That it hardens perſons in a falſe way of VVorſhip. 3dly. That it hardens and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courages ſouls in their Rebellion againſt the Lord. As for the firſt, a brief Obſervation of ſome of the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, clearly bottom'd upon the Scripture, will abundantly evince its original to be from God.</p>
                  <p>Firſt then, That ſeparation from the world and men of the world, from all wayes of falſe VVorſhip, and the Inventions of men there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, until the Saints of the Moſt-High be apparently a People dwelling alone, and not reckoned amongſt the Nations (however it be decryed, and ſound harſh in the ears of carnal men) is one grand Inſtitution, a man may run and reade in the following Scriptures; <hi>Numb. 23. 9. Joh. 15. 19. 2 Cor. 6. 14, 15, 17, 19. Eph. 5. 8, 11. 2 Tim. 3. 5. Hoſ. 4. 15. Rev. 18. 4. Prov.</hi> 14. 7. (nor is it denied by ſome of our Conforming-Brethren.)</p>
                  <p>Secondly, That Saints ſeparate from the world, ſhould frequently meet together as a diſtinct body therefrom, for the edification and building up of each other in the VVay and VVill of God, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the gifts beſtowed upon them, is ſo evidently aſſerted, as the Inſtitution of our alone King and Lawgiver in the Scripture, that it cannot be gainſayed; <hi>Mal. 3. 16. 1 Theſſ. 5. 11. Heb. 3. 12. Jude 20. Heb. 10. 24, 25. 1 Cor. 12. 9. Acts</hi> 12. 12. &amp; 18. 23. <hi>Epheſ. 5. 19. Jam. 5. 16. 1 Theſſ.</hi> 5. 14.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, That particular Congregations, or Aſſemblies of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, gathered into one body, for the Celebration of the Worſhip of God (in oppoſition to any National Church or Churches whatſoever) is of the Appointment of Chriſt, is alike evident as the former. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 1, 3. &amp; 12. 1. &amp; 13. 14. &amp; 15. 22. &amp; 18. 22. &amp; 20. 14, 28. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 2. &amp; 6. 4. <hi>Acts 9. 1. 1 Cor. 16. 19. Rom. 16. 4. 2 Cor. 8. 1. Gal. 1. 2. Acts</hi> 16. 4, 5. &amp; 14. 23. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, 12. &amp; 14. 4, 5, 12, 19. 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 1. Rev.</hi> 1. 2, 3, 11.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, That Chriſt hath appointed Officers of his own, to act in the Holy-things of God, in and over theſe Aſſemblies, whom he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth with Gifts every way ſuiting their Imployment, to whom,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:43509:41"/> without turning aſide to the voice of ſtrangers, or attending upon the Miniſtery of ſuch as are not of his Appointment, it's the duty of Saints to hearken, is very conſpicuous in the enſuing Scriptures, <hi>Eph. 4. 11. Heb. 13. 7, 13. Mat. 24. 4, 5, 23, 24. 1 Joh.</hi> 2. 18. &amp; 4. 1. 2 <hi>Joh. 10. Acts 20. 29, 30, 31. Rev.</hi> 2. 14, 15, 16. which exactly agrees with what was practiſed by primitive Believers, who it ſeems received none without the Teſtimony of ſome Brethren of known integrity in the Churches; 1 <hi>Cor. 16. 3. Act.</hi> 9. 26. Not to mention more, let it be weighed, whether the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> doth not caſt contempt upon theſe Inſtitutions of Chriſt. VVhat is more evidently preached forth by ſuch a practice, than, 1. That ſeparation from the Aſſemblies of <hi>England</hi> (though in their conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, carnal and worldly) and the worſhip thereof (although falſe and meerly of humane invention) was and is our ſin and evil? 2dly. That 'tis not by vertue of any Soveraign Inſtitution of Chriſt, the duty of Saints to meet together, as a body diſtinct (without going out to other Aſſemblies to worſhip with them) for their mutual edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in the Lord. 3dly. That particular Aſſemblies are not ſoley of the Inſtitution of the Lord Jeſus, but that National are alſo to be accounted as the true Churches of Chriſt (though they have no footing in the Scripture of the New-Teſtament, from whence the Pattern of Goſpel-Churches is ſoley to be deduced.) Yea, 4thly, That the Officers of Chriſt's Appointment are not ſufficient for the Saints, but together with them, the help of falſe and Idol-ſhepherds is to be ſought after, than which, what greater contempt can be poured upon the forementioned Inſtitutions of our dear Lord? Yet who ſees not all this to be the language which is heard and goes forth into the Nations, from the practice of our Brethren in the matter we are debating? If they look upon Separation in the ſenſe before-minded, to be of the Inſtitution of Chriſt, can they offer a greater affront thereunto, than to run into the Aſſemblies of the Nation? If they judge it their duty to meet together diſtinct from the World and its VVorſhippers, why run they thereunto? If they apprehend National Churches to be the reſult of humane prudence, without bottom in the Scripture, and the Miniſters of Chriſt to be onely (in contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinction to the Miniſters that are not of his Appointment) attended unto; why give they the right-hand of fellowſhip unto ſuch Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, as profeſs themſelves to be parts of ſuch a National Church,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:43509:42"/> and hear Miniſters that have relation thereunto? who have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived (as hath been proved) no Miſſion from Chriſt to their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. If this be not evidently to pour contempt upon the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and confeſſedly ſo, we ſhall for ever diſpair of ſucceſs in the moſt facile and righteous undertaking. As for the ſecond Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that hereby poor ſouls are hardened in a falſe way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, what can be thought leſs? (ſuppoſing the Worſhip in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh-Aſſemblies of <hi>England</hi> to be ſo, as hath been proved) when they ſhall ſee Profeſſors, that were wont to pray and preach together, to profeſs, and proteſt againſt Common-Prayer-Book-Prieſts, and Worſhip, to cry up, or at leaſt approve of, Laws made for their ejection, if guilty of no other crime, than conforming to the Worſhip they now conform to and practiſe, now flock unto their Aſſemblies, and hear their Prieſts: what can they imagine leſs, than that theſe perſons, thus acting in a direct contrariety to their former judgement and practice, do now ſee they were miſtaken? and are, beginning at leaſt, to return unto thoſe paths fom whence they departed, and that theſe wayes, in which they and their forefathers have walked, are the <hi>Good Old Way</hi> in which reſt is to be found? <hi>Wo unto the world becauſe of Offences, wo alſo unto them by whom they come.</hi> Nor is the third Particular, <hi>viz.</hi> That hereby poor ſouls are hardened in their Rebellion and Blaſphemy againſt God, the Spirit, his Tabernacle, and them that dwell therein, to be in the leaſt queſtioned: We every day hear, to the breaking of our hearts, ſtout words ſpoken againſt the Lord, becauſe of the practice of ſome in this thing. What ſay the wicked of the world leſs, than that Religion, which many pretend to, is but a Fancy, that the Profeſſors thereof are but a Generation of Hypocrites, that will turn to any thing to ſave themſelves; that the ſpirit by which they are acted is but a ſpirit of Phanaticiſm and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion! yea, how do they bleſs themſelves that they are not, nor ever were (and reſolve ſo much the more, they will never be) of the number of ſuch Profeſſors! Ask them a Reaſon of all this, and they wonder you ſhould ask them, and ſpeedily reply to you, <hi>Do you not ſee how many of you, for fear of Perſecution, have diſſerted your former Principles, and are returned to our Aſſemblies and the Miniſtry thereof, and that any of you ſtand out ('tis from hence evident) that it is from a ſpirit of Pride and Obſtinacy, and not, as you pretend, from Divine Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, and the Leadings of the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> And what can we
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:43509:42"/> ſay to all theſe things? muſt we not with grief and ſorrow confeſs, that there is indeed too great an occaſion adminiſtred to them for their thus ſpeaking, though this will be no plea for them in the day of Chriſt. <hi>Bleſſed are they that are not offended in him.</hi> It remaineth then, that inaſmuch as the hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> pours out contempt upon the Wayes and Inſtitutions of Chriſt, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens perſons in a falſe way of Worſhip, Rebellion and Blaſphemy againſt the Lord: it's utterly unlawful for Saints to be found in the practice thereof. To all that hitherto hath been ſaid, we ſhall yet briefly add,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument. 10.</head>
                  <p>God calls his People out of, and ſtrictly charges them, <hi>not to go to the places of Falſe-Worſhip:</hi> Therefore 'tis unlawful for the Saints to attend upon the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi> The Antecedent is clearly proved, <hi>Hoſ. 4. 15. Amos</hi> 4. 4. The Reaſon of the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence is, Becauſe we cannot go to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> without we go to their places and aſſemblies of Falſe-worſhip (as the <hi>Common-Prayer-Book-Worſhip</hi> hath been proved to be.)</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 11.</head>
                  <p>That, upon the doing whereof Saints have no promiſe of a Bleſſing, not any ground to expect it, is not lawful for them to do. But in the hearing of theſe men, the Saints have no promiſe of a Bleſſing, nor ground to expect it. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> (or firſt Propoſition) will not be denied. As for the <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) That the Saints have no promiſe of a Bleſſing from God nor ground to expect it, in the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> may many wayes be demonſtrated. If there be any promiſe of a Bleſſing upon them from God, in their ſo doing, let it be produced, and we ſhall willingly confeſs, <hi>there is no weight in this Argument:</hi> But this we conceive to be no eaſie task for any to diſcharge, and that for theſe Reaſons:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Bleſſing of the Lord is upon Sion,</hi> Pſal. 87. 2. and 78. 68. <hi>there he dwells,</hi> Pſal. 9. 11. and 74. 2. Jer. 8. 19. Iſa. 8. 18. Joel 3. 17, 21. the preſence of Chriſt <hi>is in the midſt of the Golden Candleſticks,</hi> Rev. 1. 12, 13. and 2. 1. 'tis his <hi>Garden in which he feedeth</hi> and dwells, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6. 2. and 8. 13. and we are not ſurer of any thing (nor will it be denied by our Conforming Brethren) (many of them) than we are of this, That the Aſſemblies of <hi>England,</hi> in their preſent conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:43509:43"/> are ſo far from being the <hi>Sion</hi> of God, his <hi>Candleſticks,</hi> his <hi>Garden,</hi> that they are a very Wilderneſs, and that <hi>Babel</hi> out of which the Lord commands his People <hi>to haſten their eſcape,</hi> Rev. 18. 4.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. God never promiſeth a Bleſſing to a People waiting upon him in that way which is polluted and not of his appointment, as we have proved the Worſhip of <hi>England</hi> to be.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Lord hath expreſly ſaid concerning ſuch as run before they are ſent, <hi>That they ſhall not profit the People,</hi> Jer. 23. 32.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The Lord proteſteth, <hi>that ſuch as refuſe to obey his Calls, to come out of Babylon, ſhall partake of her Plagues,</hi> Rev. 18. 4.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Where the Lord is not, in reſpect of his ſpecial Preſence and Grace, there is no ground to expect any Bleſſing: but God is not ſo in the midſt of the Parochial Aſſemblies of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>England.</hi> Where are the ſouls that are converted, comforted, ſtrengthened, ſtabliſhed, that are waiting at the doors of their houſe? Though many will not ſee it, yet a ſad ſpirit of withering, and viſible decaies is to be found upon many that are waiting upon the teachings of the Miniſters of this day: And we hope the Lord will in mercy, cauſe thoſe that are indeed his, to ſee it, that they may remember from whence they have fallen, repent, do their firſt works, and watch to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the things that remain, <hi>that are ready to dye,</hi> for God hath not found their works perfect before him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="argument">
                  <head>Argument 12.</head>
                  <p>That, the doing whereof is one ſtep to Apoſtacy, is not lawful to be done. But the hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> is one ſtep to Apoſtacy. Therefore.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> Propoſition will readily be granted by all: The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of great evils are certainly to be reſiſted. Apoſtacy is one of the greateſt evils in the world.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Minor</hi> (or ſecond Propoſition) <hi>viz.</hi> That the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> is one ſtep to Apoſtacy, is evident.</p>
                  <p>1. It cannot be done (eſpecially by perſons of Congregational Principles) without a relinquiſhment of Principles owned by them, as received from God: That the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as National, is a Church of the inſtitution of Chriſt: That perſons not called to the Office of the Miniſtry by the Saints, are rightful Miniſters of Chriſt, muſt be owned, and taken for granted, ere the conſcience can acquieſce in the hearing of the preſent Miniſters (for we ſuppoſe
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:43509:43"/>
'twill not be aſſerted by thoſe with whom we have to do, that there can be a true Miniſtry in a Falſe Church, or that Falſe Miniſters may be heard; and yet the preſent Miniſters are Miniſters in, and of the National Church of <hi>England,</hi> and were never ſolemnly deputed to that Office by the ſuffrage of the Lords People.)</p>
                  <p>2dly. Nor can it be done without the neglect of that duty, which with others, is eminently of the appointment of the Lord, to ſecure from Apoſtacy, inſtanc'd in by the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, Hebr. 10. 25. Not forſaking the aſſembling of your ſelves together, as the manner of ſome is, but exhorting one another, and ſo much the more as you ſee the day approaching.</hi> In which the duty of Saints aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling of themſelves together, as a body diſtinct from the world, and its Aſſemblies, as alſo their frequent, and as often as may be, <hi>exhorting one another,</hi> as a <hi>medium</hi> to ſecure them (by the bleſſing of the Lord thereupon) from a ſpirit of Degeneracy and Apoſtacy from God, is clearly aſſerted: Whence it undeniably follows, That the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> (being inconſiſtent with the conſtant and diligient uſe of the means preſcribed for the preſervation of the Saints in the way of God: for whilſt they are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon their teachings, they cannot aſſemble themſelves ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcription of God in the forementioned Scripture) is at leaſt one ſtep to the dreadful ſin of <hi>Apoſtacy from God,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is it utterly unlawful for Saints ſo to do. And thus far of the 12th Argument for the proof of the aſſertion under our maintenance, <hi>viz.</hi> That tis not lawful for Saints to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> to which many others might be added: But we doubt not, to the truly tender and humble enquiring Chriſtian, what hath been offered will be abundantly ſufficient to ſatisfie his conſcience in the preſent enquiry. We ſhall only in the cloſe offer a few Queries to be in the fear of the Holy One, conſidered by the intelligent Reader.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Quer.</hi> 1. Whether the Lord Jeſus be not the alone <hi>Head, King,</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver</hi> to his Church?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether the <hi>Laws, Statutes, Orders</hi> and <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, be not faithfully to be kept, though all the Princes in the world ſhould interdict and forbid it?</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether to introduce other Laws for the Government of the Church of Chriſt and the Worſhip of his Houſe, be not an high ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance againſt, and intruſion into his <hi>Kingſhip</hi> and <hi>Headſhip?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:43509:44"/>4. Whether the Lord Jeſus as <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Head</hi> over his Church, hath not inſtituted ſufficient Officers and Offices for the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Holy Things in his Houſe, to whom no more can be added without a deſperate undervaluation and contempt of his Wiſdome, Headſhip and Soveraignty over it?</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whether the Officers inſtituted by Chriſt, are not onely<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Deacons</hi> and <hi>Helpers?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Whether the Offices of <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Lord-Biſhops, Deans, Sub-Deans, Prebendaries, Chancellors, Prieſts, Deacons,</hi> (as an order of the firſt ſtep to a Prieſthood) <hi>Arch-Deacons, Sub-Deacons, Commiſſaries, Officials, Proctors, Regiſters, Apparitors, Parſons, Vicars, Curats, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, Petty-Canons, Gospellers, Epiſtollers, Chaunters, Virgers, Organ-Players, Queriſters,</hi> be Offices any where inſtituted by the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in the Scripture?</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Whether the calling and admiſſion into theſe laſt mentioned Offices, their adminiſtration, and maintenance now had, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in <hi>England,</hi> be according to the Word of God?</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Whether every true viſible particular Church of Chriſt, be not <hi>a ſelect company of People,</hi> called and ſeparated from the world and Falſe Worſhip thereof, by the Spirit and Word of God, and joyned together in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel, by their own free and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary conſent, giving up themſelves to Chriſt and one another ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God?</p>
                  <p n="9">9. Whether a company of People living in a Pariſh (though the moſt of them be viſible Drunkards, Swearers, &amp;c. or at leaſt ſtrangers to the work of regeneration upon their ſouls) coming (by compulſion or otherwiſe) to the hearing of Publick Prayers or Preaching, are in the Scripture account Saints, and a Church of Chriſt according to the Pattern given forth by him: Or rather, be not to be eſteemed <hi>Daughters of the old Whore</hi> and <hi>Babel,</hi> ſpoken of in the Scriptures?</p>
                  <p n="10">10. Whether in ſuch a Church there is, or can rationally be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be, a true Miniſtry of the inſtitution of Chriſt?</p>
                  <p n="11">11. Whether the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> or ſtinted <hi>Lyturgies,</hi> be of the preſcription of Chriſt, and not of mans deviſing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention?</p>
                  <p n="12">12. Whether if one part of a Worſhip uſed by a People, be pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted, the whole of their Worſhip be not to be looked upon, in a Scripture account, <hi>as polluted and abominable,</hi> according to 1 <hi>Kings</hi>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:43509:44"/> 18. 21. 2 <hi>King. 17. 33. Iſa. 66. 3. Hoſ. 4. 15. Ezek. 43. 8. Zeph.</hi> 1. 5? ſo that if their Prayers be naught and polluted, their Preaching be not ſo too.</p>
                  <p n="13">13. Whether a Miniſtry ſet up in direct oppoſition unto a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of Chriſt, which riſeth upon its fall, and falls by its riſe, can by ſuch as ſo account of it be lawfully joyned unto?</p>
                  <p n="14">14. Whether ſuch as have forſworn a Covenant Reformation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the VVord of God, and ſwear to a Worſhip that is meerly of humane deviſing, that have nothing of the eſſentials of a Miniſtry of Chriſt to be found upon them, may be accounted of as his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and be adhered to?</p>
                  <p n="15">15. VVhether ſuch as ſhall ſo do, be not guilty of <hi>caſting contempt upon the Inſtitutions of Chriſt, and diſobedience againſt his Royal Edicts,</hi> commanding them <hi>to ſeparate from perſons of ſuch a complection?</hi> To which many others of the like nature might be added.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Arguments for the lawfulneſs of hearing the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England;</hi> 1. From the ſuppoſed Precept of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 23. 1.</hi> (whether the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Mat. 23. 1.</hi> were Magiſtrates or Miniſters, debated: If Miniſters, that their Office and Calling was lawful, proved. That Chriſt neither commands nor permits his Diſciples to hear them, proved.) 2. From the practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles. 3. From <hi>Phil. 1. 15. 4.</hi> From their preaching truth. 5. From <hi>Judas</hi> his preaching. 6. From their being good men. 7. From the practice of Learned and Good men in former dayes, and now. 8. From the Magiſtrates com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. 9. From the pretended Plea of their being true Miniſters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they convert ſouls. 10. From perſons not knowing whither to go to hear: Fully anſwered.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>HAving hitherto been upon the confirmation of the Truth aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by us, <hi>viz.</hi> That 'tis not lawful for Saints to hear the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> we come now to conſider, what is in this matter objected by our diſſenting Brethren. This is that they ſay,</p>
               <div n="1" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Christ commands (or at leaſt permits) his Diſciples to hear the Scribes and Phariſees (who were men as corrupt in their Doctrine, as vitious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in their lives, as the preſent Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>can be ſuppoſed to be</hi>) Mat. 23. 1, 2. <hi>Therefore it is lawful to hear theſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:43509:45"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw.</hi> This being the main Objection uſed by our diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in this day (as it was by others in times paſt) their very <hi>Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> in this controverſie, we ſhall ſpeak the more largely to it: Many things are ſuppoſed by the Objectors, and taken for granted (and muſt be ſo by all that judge any weight to be in what is from this ſuppoſed command of Chriſt argued) which they will never be able to prove; and yet are the very <hi>baſis</hi> upon which the ſtreſs of the Objection lies.</p>
                  <p>As 1. 'Tis ſuppoſed that the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> here ſpoken of, were in the Miniſterial Seat, <hi>Teachers</hi> and <hi>Expounders of the Law,</hi> which at firſt view ſeems to be a difficult task for any to demonſtrate. That ſome of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> (which were particular Sects among the <hi>Jews,</hi> as is known) were ſo, cannot be denied; that theſe here mentioned by our Saviour are ſuch, is not ſo evident. They are expreſly ſaid <hi>to ſit in Moſes Seat</hi> (not <hi>Aarons</hi>) who though he were of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> yet was not the Miniſterial, but Magiſtratical Seat committed unto him. To the Poſterity of <hi>Aaron</hi> did the Office of Prieſthood appertain (as is known to all that have but in the leaſt turned aſide to conſider of this affair) nor is it altogether frivolous, that is by ſome obſerved, <hi>That theſe Scribes and Phariſees are especially charged with the omiſſion of Judgment and Mercy;</hi> things moſt nearly relating unto the Office of Magiſtracy, to whom it doth eſpecially appertain to look thereunto. Now will it in the leaſt follow, That ſuppoſing Chriſt enjoyned his Diſciples to <hi>attend</hi> upon the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> acting as Magiſtrates, and conform to what is juſtly and righteouſly preſcribed by them as ſuch: That therefore it's lawful to attend upon the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England.</hi> But let this be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Suppoſe,</p>
                  <p>2. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> to be the Preachers and Expounders of the Law in that day, the Seat mentioned, to be a Miniſterial Seat; yet this will not at all help them in the matter in controverſie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be granted to them, that the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> were not a lawful, but a falſe Miniſtry, that had ſurreptitiouſly climbed up into this Miniſterial Seat (for who ſees not the invalidity and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thingneſs of this Argument, 'Twas lawful to hear the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> which were the lawful Church-Officers of that day, of the appointment of the Lord, acting by vertue of an Authority derived from him; Therefore 'tis lawful to hear perſons that have not any ſuch Authority from Chriſt, but are meer Intruders and Miniſters
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:43509:45"/> of Antichriſt) (as the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> have been proved to be.) Now this upon that ſuppoſition, that they were Miniſters, we cannot yeild, for theſe Reaſons. 1. The <hi>Phariſees</hi> are expreſly ſaid to be <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levits,</hi> John 1. 19. (and this is the record of <hi>John,</hi> when the <hi>Jews</hi> ſent <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levits</hi> from <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to ask him, <hi>Who art thou?</hi> ver. 24. <hi>And they that were ſent were of the Phariſees</hi>) which were the ordinary lawful Miniſters of that day. 2. Theſe of all others were moſt apt to queſtion the Authority of ſuch as taught the People: So when <hi>John</hi> appears Preaching and Baptizing, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes to them, that <hi>he was not the Chriſt,</hi> nor <hi>Elias,</hi> nor <hi>Prophet</hi> (who was expected by the People of the <hi>Jews</hi>) they immediatly queſtion his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>John 1. 25. Why baptizest thou then?</hi> which they could not be ſuppoſed to have the face to do, if they themſelves, of all others, had been the greateſt Intruders. Nay, 3. When they queſtion Chriſt himſelf about his Authority, he asks not them, From whence they had theirs (which doubtleſs upon that occaſion, he would have done, had they not been lawfully ſeated in the Seat they did poſſeſs) but from whence <hi>John</hi> had his, who was eſteemed as a Prophet. 4. We have the Lord Jeſus many times crying out above all others, againſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> condemning them of Pride, Hypocriſie, Avarice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not the leaſt tittle of the uſurpation of <hi>Moſes</hi>-ſeat, is by him charged upon them, or in the leaſt intimated, which doubtleſs would have been had they been guilty thereof. But let this alſo be granted, that we may hear this Argument ſpeak its uttermoſt, <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in Moſes ſeat;</hi> this Seat is a Miniſterial Seat, and they ſit not here by vertue of any lawful Authority, but are meer intruders; what follows from hence? why this, if it were lawful to hear the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, perſons vitious in their lives, corrupt in their doctrine, having no lawful call to the place they poſſeſſed: then it undeniably follows, that it's lawful to hear the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> though they have no lawful Authority or Call to the Office they aſſume. It muſt it ſeems, then 3dly, be granted, that when Chriſt ſayes, <hi>What they ſay unto you, do,</hi> he is to be interpreted, to <hi>command,</hi> or at leaſt, to <hi>permit</hi> an attendance upon their Miniſtry. But this is that we deny, and dare confidently aver, That it never entered into the heart of Chriſt to permit, much leſs to command any to attend upon the Miniſtry of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees:</hi> Nor is any ſuch thing in the leaſt inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the words under conſideration. For firſt, the words are in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:43509:46"/> the original, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which may more ſtrictly be rendered, <hi>the Scribes &amp; Phariſees have ſat in Moſes Chair, all things therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they have ſaid unto you, &amp;c.</hi> (i. e. <hi>whatever in times paſt, you have heard delivered by theſe men, according to the mind of God, do you not now reject becauſe of that Hypocriſie, Pride, Coveteouſneſs, &amp;c. you are made to ſee is predominant in them.</hi> Let the words be as they are rendered, <hi>whatever they bid you obſerve and do, that obſerve and do.</hi> Yet 2ly, who that hath but half an eye can chuſe but ſee, that an attendance upon their Miniſtry is remote enough from being their intendment? We had alwayes thought, that they might have been ſufficiently acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with, and been in a capacity of hearing and knowing what had been ſaid by theſe men through their particular occaſional meeting and diſcourſe with them, though they had never ſpent one hour in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon their Miniſtry. Which that our Saviour did not enjoyn, no nor ſo much as permit by that expreſſion, we ſuppoſe may be cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly demonſtrated from the enſuing conſiderations.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. There are not a generation of men of whom the Lord Jeſus doth ſpeak more contemptuouſly (and charges with greater enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) than he doth of that generation of <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees.</hi> In this very chapter he enforms us of their Hypocriſie, <hi>ver.</hi> 5, 23, 25, 27, 28, 29. and <hi>Pride,</hi> ver 6, 7. and tells us plainly that <hi>they ſhut up the Kingdome of Heaven againſt men, neither entering in themſelves, nor ſuffering thoſe that are entring, to go in,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>That they make their Proſelytes twofold more the children of Hell than themſelves,</hi> v. 15. <hi>that they are blind Guides,</hi> ver. 16, 19, 24, 26. <hi>perverters of the Scripture, ſuch as make void the Commandments of God by their Traditions,</hi> ver. 16, 17, 18. <hi>that they are Serpents, a generation of Vipers, that cannot eſcape the damnation of Hell,</hi> ver. 33. <hi>yea, ſuch as ſhall kill, crucifie, ſcourge, perſecute the Meſſengers of the Lord,</hi> ver. 34. And can it be imagined, that Chriſt ſhould have no more tenderneſs to poor ſouls, than to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them to an attendance upon ſuch perſons as theſe for teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings?—<hi>Credat Apelles!</hi> Are theſe likely motives to perſwade, or enforce any thereunto? Yet this is what he immediatly ſubjoyns, having ſaid, <hi>whatever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Doctrines owned by them are known: The <hi>Teſſera</hi> of their Sect, was, <hi>Juſtification by the works of the Law,</hi> which is diametrically oppoſit to the work Chriſt was then upon, and the Doctrine preached by him.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:43509:46"/>3. That they denied Chriſt to be the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> blaſphemed him in his Doctrine (as the deceiver of the people) in his Life (as a VVine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibber &amp; glutonous perſon) in his Miracles (as one that wrought them by the Devil, who are therefore condemned by Chriſt, as guilty of the very ſin of Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. 31.) is known, as being what is frequently remarked in the Scripture.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. We no where find the Diſciples attending upon the Miniſtry of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> notwithſtanding this ſuppoſed command or permiſſion of Chriſt. Nay,</p>
                  <p n="5">5. We cannot but think the ſuppoſition hereof, not onely incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant with, and oppoſite to that expreſſion concerning Chriſt, <hi>Mar. 6. 34. And Jeſus when he ſaw much People was moved with compaſſion to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, becauſe they were as Sheep not having a Shepherd</hi> (what? without a Shepherd, and yet the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> whoſe feeding they might lawfully attend upon; doth Chriſt pitty them in this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute ſtate, and not give them one word of direction to wait upon theſe profound and worthy Doctors?) but alſo contrary to that ſolemn command given forth from the Lord, <hi>Acts 2. 40. Save your ſelves from this untoward generation;</hi> and the practice of the Diſciples, <hi>who continued in the Apoſtles Doctrine and Fellowſhip, and breaking of Bread and Prayer,</hi> Acts 2. 42.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Were that the intendment of Chriſt, as is ſuggeſted (and the Argument uſed by our Brethren valid) a lawfulneſs to hear the varieſt Blaſphemer in the world, that denies that Chriſt is the <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms that he was a <hi>Deluder of the people,</hi> a <hi>gluttonous perſon,</hi> a <hi>winebiber, one that did Miracles by Beelzebub the Prince of Devils,</hi> that perſecutes even to death Chriſt in his People, might by a like parity of Reaſon be deduced. Chriſt commanded, or at leaſt permitted, his Diſciples <hi>to hear the Phariſees</hi> who were ſuch (as hath been proved) therefore 'tis lawful to hear perſons with the ſame characters upon them. But God forbid any ſuch injurious dealing ſhould be offered to Chriſt, or that any who pretend to fear God (and I hope do ſo in reality) ſhould ſtand by a cauſe which hath no better Arguments to defend it, than what may be as righteouſly every way made uſe of for the attending upon the Miniſtry of the greateſt Blaſphemer or Oppoſer of Chriſt in the world. Evident then it is, notwithſtanding the great flouriſh that many make with this Scripture, for the abetting of their attendance upon the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> that it refuſes to admit the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:43509:47"/> leaſt ſanctuary thereunto. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. 1, 2. may for ought we know be Magiſtrates, not Miniſters; if Miniſters, they were, as hath been proved, lawfully ſo: Chriſt ſayes concerning them, <hi>Whatever they bid you obſerve and do, that obſerve and do.</hi> Therefore 'tis lawful to attend upon the Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> whoſe lawful calling to their Office cannot be proved; yea, though there is not the leaſt intimation of a Command from Chriſt, or ſo much as a permiſſion to his Diſciples, to hear the <hi>Scribes</hi> &amp; <hi>Phariſees,—Nugae et tricae ſicula!</hi> If this be to diſpute, a man need not fear but to be able to multiply Arguments at an eaſie rate, for whatever he hath a mind to undertake the defence of: yet this is ſuppoſed by many to he of the greateſt moment in this controverſie.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 2.</head>
                  <p>If it be ſaid, <hi>But we find Christ, and the Apostles after him, going frequently into the Synagogues, were theſe Scribes and Phariſees preached.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We anſwer, firſt; That all that Chriſt and the Apoſtles did, is not lawful for Saints to practiſe, will not be denied: many inſtances are near at hand for its confirmation, ſhould it ſo be. 2. That 'tis one thing to go into the Synagogues, and another thing to go thither to attend upon the Miniſtry of ſuch as taught there: this is the preſent caſe, which that Chriſt or the Apoſtles ever did cannot be proved. 3. They went thither to oppoſe them in, and confute their Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Traditions in the VVorſhip of God, to take an opportunity to teach and inſtruct the People in his VVay and VVill: VVhich when any have a ſpirit to do, and are ſatisfied that they are thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to called by the Lord, in reſpect of the preſent Miniſters and VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of <hi>England,</hi> we ſhall be ſo far from condemning them therein, that we ſhall bleſs God for them. But this is not to the purpoſe in hand: the attendance of our Brethren upon the Miniſtry of <hi>England</hi> is quite another thing, that requires other Arguments for its ſupport, than we have hitherto met with.</p>
                  <q>—<hi>Parvas habet ſpes Troja ſi Tales habet.</hi>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul rejoyceth at the Preaching of the Goſpel, though 'twas preached out of envy,</hi> Phil. 1. 15, 16. To which briefly;</p>
                  <p>1. There may be cauſe of rejoycing in reſpect of the iſſue and event of things, by the wiſe Providence of God, though the means
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:43509:47"/> uſed for their production be evil; and not to be abetted or complyed with: In what have Chriſtians greater cauſe of rejoycing than in the death of Chriſt? Yet had it been utterly unlawful to have joyn'd in counſel with, or any wayes abetted or encouraged thoſe wicked per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that crucified and ſlew him. Should the Pope ſend ſome <hi>Jeſuits</hi> into any remote parts of <hi>America</hi> to preach the Goſplel to the poor <hi>Indians</hi> there, here were upon ſome accounts ground of rejoycing, yet no ground for Saints to attend upon a <hi>Jeſuitical Miniſtry.</hi> But 2ly, it appears not, that theſe <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, were not true Goſpel-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and ſo it reacheth not the caſe in hand: This being that, we have proved the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> guilty of, <hi>viz.</hi> an acting in the Holy Things of God without any Commiſſion from Chriſt, which when our Diſſenting-Brethren prove they have, we ſhall eaſily ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the lawfulneſs of attending upon their Miniſtry. 3ly, It follows not in the leaſt, that theſe the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, were either not real Saints, or not true Miniſters of Chriſt, becauſe they are ſaid to <hi>preach him out of envy;</hi> the object whereof was not Chriſt; (for had they envied him, they would never have preach'd him) but <hi>Paul, (thinking,</hi> ſays he, <hi>to add affliction to my bonds</hi>) which is conſiſtant with Grace, and a lawful Miſſion to the preaching of the Goſpel. Yet, 4thly, Here is not in this Scripture the leaſt word requiring <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to hear them. That becauſe <hi>Paul</hi> rejoyces at their preaching, therefore 'tis the duty of Saints to attend upon their <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> is ſuch a <hi>Non-ſequiter</hi> as will never be made good.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>preach Truth, and is it not lawful to hear Truth preached?</hi> We anſwer,</p>
                  <p>1. That 'tis lawful to hear Truth preached is readily granted: but this muſt be done lawfully, and in the way of Chriſt's Appointment. 2ly. All that preach Truth are not to be heard, nor will our diſſenting Brethren ſay they are. For, 1. There was never yet any Heretical-Preacher in the world, but he preached ſome Truth; is it lawful to hear ſuch? this will not be ſaid. 2. The Devil himſelf preached Truth, yet Chriſt forbids him, and commands that he hold his peace. 3. The Popiſh Prieſts preach Truth; yet who will ſay 'tis lawful to attend upon their Miniſtry? But, 3dly, As the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> preach Truth, So, 1. They preach it but by halves, and dare not for fear of the L. Biſhops Inhibition, preach any doctrine, though
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:43509:48"/> never ſo clearly revealed in the Scriptures, and owned by them as the Truth of Chriſt, he commands them not to meddle with. 2. The main Truths they preach (at leaſt many of them) are contradicted in their practice. They'l tell you that the Lord Jeſus is the great Prophet, and King of his Church; but how palpably this is contradicted by them in their practice, conforming to Inſtitutions and Laws that are not of his preſcription, who ſees not? This we have already abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly demonſtrated. 3. With the Truth they preach, they mingle many Errors, directly contrary to the Scripture, and the Revelation Chriſt hath made of his Will therein. Inſtances of this kind have been already exhibited, to which may be added many more: we ſhall mention but a few, 1. That the Miniſtry, Worſhip and Government which Chriſt hath appointed to his Church, is not to be received or joyned unto, unleſs the Magiſtrates (where they are reputed Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an) do allow it. 2. That the Apocryphal books which have in them Errors (2 <hi>Mac.</hi> 12. 44, 45. &amp; 14. 41, 42. <hi>Eccleſ. 46. 20. Wiſd.</hi> 19. 11.) Untruths (2 <hi>Eſd. 14. 21, 22, 23. 2 Macc. 2. 4-8. Tob.</hi> 5. 11, 12, 13. with 12. 15. <hi>Judith</hi> 8. 33. &amp; 10. 9, with <hi>v.</hi> 12. &amp; 11. 6, 12, 13, 14, 15. 1 <hi>Mac.</hi> 9. 3, 18. with 2 <hi>Mac. 1. 13 to</hi> 17. &amp; 9. 1, 5, 7, 9, 28, 29.) Blaſphemy (<hi>Tob.</hi> 12. 12, 15. with <hi>Rom. 8. 34. 1 Tim. 2. 5. Rev.</hi> 8. 3, 4.) Magick (<hi>Tobit</hi> 6. 6, 7, 8. &amp; 9. 2, 3. with 3. 7, 8. &amp; 11. 10, 11, 13. with 2. 9, 10.) and contradiction to the Canonical Scriptures, (<hi>Judith</hi> 9. 2, 3, 4. compared with <hi>Gen. 49. 5, 6, 7. Eſther</hi> in the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> chap. 12. 5. &amp; 15. 9, 10. with <hi>Eſter</hi> canonical, chap. 6. 3. &amp; 5. 2. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 46. 20. with <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57. 2.) may be uſed in the Publick Worſhip of God. 3. That the moſt wicked, and their ſeed, may be compelled, and received to be members of the Church. 4. That <hi>Marriage</hi> may be forbidden at certain ſeaſons, as in <hi>Lent, Advent, Rogation-week, &amp;c.</hi> 5. That <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is to be adminiſtred with a <hi>Croſs in the forehead,</hi> and that as a ſymbolical ſign. 6. That though the moſt notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous obſtinate Offenders be partakers of the Lord's Supper, yet the people that joyn with them are not defiled thereby. 7. That there may be Holy-dayes appointed to the Virgin <hi>Mary, John Baptiſt,</hi> to the <hi>Apoſtles, All Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> together alſo with Faſts on their Eves, on <hi>Ember-dayes, Fridayes, Saturdayes</hi> (ſo called heatheniſhly enough) and <hi>Lent.</hi> 8. That the <hi>Cope, Surplice, Tippit, Rocket, &amp;c.</hi> are meet and decent Ornaments for the Worſhip of God and <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the Goſpel. 9. That the Book of <hi>Common-Prayer</hi> is the true
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:43509:48"/> Worſhip of God. 10. That <hi>Chriſt deſcended into Hell</hi> (as if Chriſt deſcended into the place of the Damned, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold. 11. That Lord <hi>Biſhops</hi> can give the Holy-Ghoſt, and power to forgive and retain Sins. 12. That <hi>Altars, Candles, Organs, &amp;c.</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſeful in the Church of God. 13. That all Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren <note n="†" place="margin">Common-Prayer-Book of Publick Baptiſm.</note> when baptized are regenerate, and received by the Lord for his own Children by Adoption. Yea, 14. That Children being baptized, have all things neceſſary for their Salvation, and ſhall undoubtedly be ſaved. So they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs in the Order of Confirmation in the Common-Prayer-Book; with much more that might be offered in this matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 5.</head>
                  <p>Judas <hi>preached, though a wicked man; and no doubt 'twas lawful, yea the duty of Saints to hear him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this we ſay,</p>
                  <p>No doubt but it was ſo. But, 1. <hi>Judas</hi> was not a viſible wicked man at the time of his preaching, but ſo cloſe an Hypocrite, that he was not known to be ſo, no not to the Diſciples: But ſome of the preſent <hi>Miniſters of England</hi> are viſibly wicked and prophane.</p>
                  <p>2. <hi>Judas</hi> was choſen, and called by Chriſt to be an Apoſtle, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated by him to preach: but the preſent <hi>Miniſters of England</hi> are not ſo, as hath been proved. So that this is not at all to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in hand.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But there are ſome good men amongst them, and ſuch as belong to God, may we not hear good men?</hi> To which briefly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That there are ſome amongſt the preſent Preachers of this day, that are good men, we ſhall not ſtand to deny: Yet,</p>
                  <p n="2">2. We crave leave to ſay, That they are all of them ſuch as are ſadly polluted and defiled by their Complyance, in reſpect of their ſtanding in the <hi>Miniſtry Antichriſtian,</hi> whoſe teachings Saints have no warrant to attend upon.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The greater hopes we have of their goodneſs, the more caute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ſhould we be of encouraging them in a falſe way; that they by our relinquiſhment of them, and ſeparating from them (after we have diſcharged all other duties we are ſatisfied are incumbent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:43509:49"/> us to perform towards them) may come to ſee their ſin, repent, and do their firſt works, that God and we may again receive them.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Yet the goodneſs of any, as to the main, is no warrant for any to hold communion with them, or attend upon their teachings: There are Brethren that walk diſorderly, whom 'tis the duty of Saints to ſeparate from: that the very beſt of the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> do ſo, will not be denied. The Inceſtuous perſon, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. was, as to the main, for ought I know, a good man; yet were not the Saints at <hi>Corinth</hi> to hold communion with him, till upon his repentance he was again received, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 6.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. 'Tis utterly unlawful to communicate with a deviſed Miniſtry, upon what pretext ſoever.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. So is it for any to partake in other mens ſins (as hath been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved): but every uſurped Miniſtry is the ſin of him (though never ſo holy a perſon) that exerciſeth it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But many Learned and Good men (and ſuch as in conſcience could not conform to the Ceremonies of the Church of</hi> England) <hi>have in dayes paſt (and do now) hear the preſent Miniſters thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which we anſwer,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That the greateſt Scholars, and moſt accompliſhed for humane Wiſdom, Parts, yea viſible Holineſs, have not been alwayes on the Lords ſide, following him in paths of his own appointment; but many times have been found the greateſt Perſecutors and Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of Chriſt; the moſt ſtupendouſly ignorant of the Will of God in reſpect of the Truth, and Work of their Generation, of any perſons in the world: Witneſs the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> the Learned <hi>Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies,</hi> and Profound <hi>Doctors</hi> of that day, with what virulency did they oppoſe Chriſt and the Doctrine of the Goſpel preached by him?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That perſons of as great Holineſs, and renown for Learning, and all manner of Accompliſhments, as learned <hi>Ainſworth, Cotton, &amp;c.</hi> have been and are of the ſame apprehenſion with us in this matter: Not to mention the Reformed Churches, who generally renounce the Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not admitting any by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of it to the charge of ſouls (as they ſpeak.)</p>
                  <p>But 3. <hi>To the Law and to the Teſtimony,</hi> Iſa. 8. 20. if they ſpeak not according to this Rule, though Angels for knowledge and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:43509:49"/> they are not to be received, or heeded: One word from the Lord is of more weight to hearts made truly tender, than the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of an hundred Profeſſors can be: 'tis poſſible theſe may erre be <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay;</hi> but ſo cannot the Truth of God, which is alwayes the ſame, and will abide ſo for ever.</p>
                  <p>4. The Apoſtle hath long ſince determined this caſe, 1 <hi>Cor. 11. 1. Be ye followers of me as I am of Chriſt:</hi> So far as Saints follow Chriſt, I may and ought to follow them, but no further: So that the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Parts, or Holineſs of any that attend upon the preſent Miniſters of <hi>England,</hi> is no warrant for me ſo to do; nor will ever be a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwer to that enquiry, <hi>Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the Magiſtrate commands us, and ought we not to obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. That Magiſtrates have no power to command in matters of inſtituted Worſhip, where Chriſt is ſilent, or to govern in his Church, is affirmed by many.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Commands of <hi>Magistrates,</hi> when contrary to the Will and Way of Chriſt, are not to be ſubjected to. This caſe is long ſince ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and reſolved by the Apoſtle (<hi>Acts</hi> 4. 19, 20. and 5. 29.) and Spirit of the Lord, breathing long before in his renouned Witneſſes, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 16, 17. and 6. 10. nor is it denied by any that are ſober, or juditious. Whether the hearing of the preſent Miniſters of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> be contrary to the Word of God, the Will and Way of Chriſt, we leave, from what hath been offered, to the conſiderate Reader to judge; And ſhall onely adde what was long ſince aſſerted by <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in this matter, who<note place="margin">Auguſt. do Verb. Domini, Serm. 6.</note> was herein fully of the ſame mind with us; <hi>Sed timeo inquies ne offendas Majorem, time prorſus, ne offendas Majorem, &amp; non offendes Deum. Quid enim times ne offendas Majorem? Vide ne forſan major ſit iſto quem times offendere. Majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem certe noli offendere—quis eſt inquies Major eo qui me genuit a an ille qui Teipſum creavit?—qui enim reſistit Poteſtati, Dei Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioni reſiſtit: ſed quid ſi illud jubeat quod non debes facere?—timondo poſteſtatem ipſos humanarum rerum gradus advertite: ſi aliquid juſſerit Curator, nonne faciendum est? tam et ſi contra Proconſul jubeat, at non
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:43509:50"/> utique contemnis poteſtatem, ſed eligis Majori ſervire, nec hinc debet Minor iraſci, ſi Major praelata est. Rurſum ſi aliquid ipſe Proconſul jubeat, &amp; aliud ſubeat Imperator, numquid dubitatur in illo contemptu, illi eſſe ſerviendum? Ergo ſi aliud Imperator, &amp; aliud Deus, quid ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicatis? ſolve tributum, est mihi in obſequio, rectè! Sed non in Idolio, in Idolio prohibet, quis prohibet? Major Poteſtas. Da veniam! tu can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerum, ille gehennam minatur.</hi> He tells us plainly that ſuch as fear to offend their Superiours, ſhould much more fear to offend God, who is greater than all. The Emperours and Monarchs of the VVorld threaten us with a Priſon if we diſobey them; the LORD threatens us with Hell, upon our diſobedience of Him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 9.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the Miniſters of</hi> England <hi>are true Gospel-Miniſters, for they convert ſouls; which the Apoſtle makes the Seal of his Miniſtry or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip: Therefore it is lawful to hear them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To this we ſay,</p>
                  <p>That the Miniſters of <hi>England</hi> are true Goſpel-Miniſters, is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely denied by us; what is offered in this Objection, proves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Paul</hi> makes not the Converſion of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, a ſufficient Demonſtration, or convincing Argument of his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip; he only uſeth it, as what was moſt likely to win, and work upon their affections, who upon other accounts could not but know that he was an Apoſtle of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Converſion of ſouls is no Argument, either of a lawful Call to an Apoſtleſhip, or Miniſtry of Chriſt: For, 1. Many have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted ſouls, that were not Apoſtles, as ordinary Miniſters. 2. The Lord hath uſed private Brethren, Women, yea, ſome remarkable Providences, as inſtruments in his hand for the converſion of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſouls; yet who will ſay that private Brethren, Women, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providences are Apoſtles or Miniſters of the Lord Jeſus. But 3dly, ſhould it be granted, that Converſion of Souls is an Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a lawful Miniſtry, where are the Churches, nay where are the particular perſons converted by them? we have not heard of any, nor will it be an eaſie task for the Objectors to produce in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in this matter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="object">
                  <head>Object. 10.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But our Miniſters are removed, and we know not where to go to hear;
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:43509:50" rendition="simple:additions"/> would you have us ſit at home idle? we cannot ſo ſpend the Lord's day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To which we would humbly offer a few things:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That though we are not againſt any Ordinance of Jeſus Chriſt, yet we are afraid that thoſe poor ſouls, that know not how to ſpend the Lord's day without hearing, do too much idolize that Ordinance of God, and never knew what it was to ſpend that day with him.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. You need nor ſit at home; if you are enquiring after God, and communion with his People, you may ſoon hear of ſome one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Aſſemblies of the Saints, whither you may repair to wait upon the Lord with them.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. But thirdly, VVere it, or ſhould it be otherwiſe; Yet better be idle, than do worſe; better do nothing, than ſin againſt God, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others in their evil deeds, pollute and wound thy own ſoul, grieve the Saints, ſtumble and harden the wicked, and cauſe them to blaſpheme God, his Name, Sanctuary, and ſuch as dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. But,</p>
                  <p n="4">4. There is no neceſſity of being idle; If thou knoweſt not where to hear on that day, haſt thou no work to do ſave that? 1. Art ſure that God, and Chriſt, and Eternal Glory are thy portion and inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance? Thou walkeſt in the Light of Aſſurance, or thou doſt not? if thou doſt, is one day in ſeven too much to ſpend in the ſolemn ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of Grace, that ever ſo vile a creature as thou, ſhould be accounted worthy of ſuch unexpreſſible kindneſs and glory? what, O what will Eternity be then? If thou doſt not, are not theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of thy utmoſt diligence to get Aſſurance of? What, ſtand idle, and an Intereſt in God, Chriſt, and Eternal Glory to make ſure of! 2. Art thou ſufficiently acquainted with thine own heart? doſt know ſo much of thy ſelf as thou needeſt to know? or judgeſt thou this to be a work that requires not thy utmoſt diligence and attendance? 3. Haſt thou no ſin to be mortified, no want to be ſupplied, no grace to be quickned and ſtrengthned in thee? 4. Haſt thou as much communion with God as thou deſireſt? haſt heard as often from him by the teachings of the Spirit (the incomparably and infinitely beſt Teacher) as thou doſt wiſh? or doſt think that God will not manifeſt himſelf to, and teach in a corner, a poor ſoul that's there waiting for him alone, becauſe there be no Aſſemblies of Saints he knows of, to whom he might joyn himſelf, and he dares not have
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:43509:51"/> communion with Adulterers? If thou haſt not fellowſhip with God thou deſireſt, and teachings from him, (as who hath) ſtir up thy ſelf to lay hold on God, groan, and cry after him, till he hath brought thee into his Chambers, and afforded thee richer diſplayes of his Glory. 5. Art thou altogether ready trimmed (without more ado) for the Coming and Kingdom of Chriſt Jeſus? what ſhould I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thoſe important duties of reading the Scriptures, meditation on them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> haſt thou all this to do, and much more that might be added, and yet nothing to do on the Lord's day? Set about theſe things in good earneſt, &amp; when thou liveſt in the Light of Aſſurance, without the leaſt doubt or clouding, when thou art ſufficiently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with thine own heart, the VVill and Scriptures of the Lord; when thou haſt as much communion with God in retirement as thou deſireſt, and teachings from his Spirit; when thou haſt no ſin to be mortified, nor grace to be quickned and ſtrengthned; when thou art quite ready for the day of Chriſt, and needeſt no further fittings, we ſhall conſider what may further be ſaid to this Objection; but till then it cannot be pleaded, when ſouls have all this work to do, that they muſt ſit at home idle, if they go not to hear the Preachers of this day. But thus far of the Objections that are by ſome made againſt the Aſſertion of the Unlawfulneſs of attending upon the preſent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England;</hi> which are all of any moment we have yet met with: what of weight is in them, muſt be left to the judgment of the Chriſtian Reader to determine.</p>
                  <p>We ſhall add no more but this, That we have ſpoken our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſcience herein, as in ſincerity, in the ſight of God; with what meekneſs, Chriſtian tenderneſs, and fear of giving any juſt offence to the truly Conſcientious, he knows. The ſole of our aim in the whole, is, That Chriſt may be glorified in the recovery of any poor Lamb, that is turned aſide to the flocks of the Companions in this cloudy and dark day; that others that have hitherto kept them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Idols might be further eſtabliſhed in the Will of God, and ſtrengthned to follow Chriſt in his temptations, that they may inherit that Kingdom and Glory, prepared for them before the foundation of the world: May we but in the leaſt contribute, by Divine Bleſſing, hereunto, what-ever becomes of theſe Papers, or how ever they be by others accounted of, we have our end, and ſhall reſt ſatisfied.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:43509:51"/>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
